<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Apologia chyrurgica A vindication of the noble art of chyrurgery, from the gross abuses offer'd thereunto by mountebanks, quacks, barbers, pretending bone-setters, with other ignorant undertakers. Wherein their fraudulent practices are plainly detected by several remarkable observations, their fair promises prov'd fictions, their administrations pernicious, their confident pretences injurious and destructive to the welfare of the people. By Daniel Turner, practitioner in chyrurgery. Imprimatur. Datum in comitiis censoriis ex ædibus collegii nostri, Jan. 11. 1694. John Lawson, president. Samuel Collins, Richard Torless, Edward Tyson, Martin Lister, censores.</title>
            <author>Turner, Daniel, 1667-1741.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63873</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219447</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830915</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830915</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35377</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63873)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35377)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2084:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Apologia chyrurgica A vindication of the noble art of chyrurgery, from the gross abuses offer'd thereunto by mountebanks, quacks, barbers, pretending bone-setters, with other ignorant undertakers. Wherein their fraudulent practices are plainly detected by several remarkable observations, their fair promises prov'd fictions, their administrations pernicious, their confident pretences injurious and destructive to the welfare of the people. By Daniel Turner, practitioner in chyrurgery. Imprimatur. Datum in comitiis censoriis ex ædibus collegii nostri, Jan. 11. 1694. John Lawson, president. Samuel Collins, Richard Torless, Edward Tyson, Martin Lister, censores.</title>
                  <author>Turner, Daniel, 1667-1741.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 140 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, and are to be sold by J. Whitlock near Stationers-hall, and the booksellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Surgery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Apologia Chyrurgica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A VINDICATION Of the Noble Art of <hi>Chyrurgery,</hi> FROM The groſs Abuſes offer'd thereunto by <hi>Mountebanks, Quacks, Barbers, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Bone-ſetters,</hi> with other Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Undertakers.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN Their Fraudulent Practices are plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected by ſeveral remarkable Obſervations, their Fair Promiſes prov'd Fictions, their Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions pernicious, their Confident Pretences injurious and deſtructive to the Welfare of the People.</p>
            <p>By <hi>DANIEL T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNER,</hi> Practitioner in Chyrurgery.</p>
            <q>K <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="lat" subtype="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Datum in Comitiis Cenſoriis ex Aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Collegii no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri, <date>Jan. 11. 1694.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Lawſon,</hi> Preſident.</item>
                           <item>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Samuel Collins,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Richard Torleſ,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Edward Tyſon,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Martin Liſter,</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <trailer>Cenſores.</trailer>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>LONDON Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>J. Whitlock</hi> near <hi>Stationers-hall,</hi> and the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> 1695.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:4"/>
            <head>TO THE Moſt Ingenious and Truly Learned Dr. EDWARD TYSON, One of the preſent Cenſors of the <hi>College of Phyſicians,</hi> Fellow of the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> and Phyſician to the Hoſpital of <hi>Bethlehem.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'TIS the common Fate of Learned Men, that they are more than ordinarily expos'd to the importunity of ſuch as are in want of their aſſiſtance; and tho' it be Preſumption in their Petitioners, 'tis in them however a generous Condeſcention, that they encline to gratifie the Requeſts of their needy Supplicants.</p>
            <p>I am ready to acknowledge my ſelf little ſhort of the ſame Arrogance, in that I am become troubleſome ſo ſoon as honour'd with your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Eminent</hi> ſeem indeed to be placed in a ſublimer Sphere, not ſo much that they might pity the Ignorant as to protect the Indigent.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:5"/>
            <p> Being conſcious of my own inſufficiency to withſtand the Teſt of Critical Cenſure, it was reaſonable I ſhould endeavour to find a Patron that might (in ſome meaſure) ſecure me from the Obloquy of my Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>When I had conſider'd upon whoſe friendſhip I might moſt happily rely, it was the effect of my Ambition to ſingle out Your Self, for one of the greateſt and moſt learned amongſt others, whom I had thought on: to make which choice (Sir) I was the rather encourag'd, ſince you had ſo lately oblig'd me with a very kind ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of ſome looſe Papers I had by me, which upon your communicating were by the <hi>Royal Society</hi> eſteem'd not unworthy, to be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their Philoſophical Tranſactions. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the experience of ſo much Civility on a firſt or ſecond conference, I had the leſs reaſon to diſpute your Goodneſs upon the occaſion I have had of a farther correſpondence.</p>
            <p>The enſuing Diſcourſe, which I am endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to ſhelter under the Umbrage of your Favour, was compiled about four years ſince, in which time it was moſtly in the cuſtody of ſome particular Friends, who were not a little earneſt with me for its publication; tho' on other accounts I might have rely'd upon their Judgments, yet with this I could not ſo readily comply, becauſe as I had never appear'd in Print, I was the leſs capable to imagine the Difficulties and Diſadvantages I had to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: I did already foreſee ſome, which put me
<pb facs="tcp:35377:5"/> upon thinking, and was afraid to meet with others that ſhould (when paſt recovery) be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Repentance.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, I valued not the Reſentments of malicious and deceitful Men, ſince I doubted not but the more honeſt and judicious would eſpouſe my Cauſe: But when I reflected on the extream Nicety of the Town, many wherein are fonder to expoſe what they call Wit, by their Comments upon an Author's Language, prying for <hi>Errata's,</hi> and ſearching out his Lapſes, rather than regarding the Uſefu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſs of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, or heeding whether it anſwers the End for which 'twas enterpriz'd. Of theſe men I had reaſon to be fearful, eſpecially perceiving that more learn'd Diſcourſes were frequently attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an apologetick Entrance that might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate their Cenſure.</p>
            <p>Amongſt other worthy Authors, I could do no leſs than take notice of the almoſt too great Modeſty of the late incomparable Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> who when he had written never ſo elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately upon what he undertook, is not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding excuſing himſelf, as if guilty of ſome Blemiſh or Imperfection. It ſhould ſeem by this his ſingular Humility he was as worthy of, as he could be willing to procure a general Eſteem and Admiration: And yet, according to the concluſion of a <hi>Panegyrick</hi> on the Curious <hi>De Graaf,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:35377:6"/>
               <l>Quis Jove, major erat, magno quis major Homero,</l>
               <l>Ille tamen Momum: Zoilon Alter habet.</l>
            </q>
            <p>However, if ſo great and famous Men have every where thought it Prudence to arm them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the <hi>Zoiliſts</hi> of the Age, what abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant cauſe had I to remain ſilent, and keep out of their reach?</p>
            <p>A farther motive to induce me for ſome time to retard the impreſſion, was, That as I hop'd there would not be wanting thoſe, who would judge aright of my Undertaking, ſo I as little queſtion'd to find others ready enough to think me more deſirous to be reputed an Author, than by being ſo to ſerve the Publick Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe (Sir) were the more material Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments to my Conſent, till on the other hand I bethought my ſelf how ſerviceable ſuch a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery as this might be at a time that ſeem'd extraordinarily to require it; and finding thoſe who were perhaps better capacitated wholly negligent therein, I was the rather prevail'd with to lend my mean aſſiſtance towards the redreſſing ſo univerſally-prejudicial an Aggrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance; ſo that in whatever I have expos'd my own Weakneſs, I ſhall think my ſelf enough fortunate if the ſame be imputed to my Zeal for the General Good, by uſing my utmoſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to ſuppreſs all baſe <hi>Pretenders</hi> to our moſt Noble Art, and vindicating the ſame from their Ignominy and Reproach.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:6"/>
            <p> I have no reaſon to doubt but your ſelf, at ſome times, in the variety of your Practice, have remark'd how eaſily many reputable Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have been impos'd on by a Pretence to Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and how fatally deluded with a Promiſe of Recovery; from whence, if I miſtake not, there will be little room for a Surmiſe, whether a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of this tendency may be advantageous. However I may happen to be aſpers'd, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may be thought of the Diſcourſe it ſelf, I fear not to be diſcommended for my choice of ſo fit a Perſon, by the benefit of whoſe counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance both may be defended from the too rigid Cenſure of thoſe who will ſtill be condemning all but their own Offspring, if it be but to ſhow the Parts which a more refined Education hath conferr'd upon them above the reſt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <p>I have here a fair opportunity (ſince I can ſay little for my ſelf) to make a modiſh Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue upon your Accompliſhments; but rather than treſpaſs on your Modeſty, I ſhall omit to ſay any thing of that nature.</p>
            <p>I am, I muſt confeſs, very much of opinion with the Noble <hi>Mackenzy,</hi> (in an Epiſtle to Eſquire <hi>Boyle)</hi> with reſpect to Dedications, and do believe an Author much more concern'd to procure for his Patron him who hath conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly render'd himſelf truly worthy, than one ſo made by Flattery or Adulation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:7"/>
            <p> Were I minded to ſpeak to ſo large a Theme as your Merit would afford, I might ſay much, I'm certain, before the greateſt of your Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents would accuſe me as a <hi>Sycophant.</hi> To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Reflection, I ſhall only take the liberty to give the World my Wiſh, That we had been longer happy in your acceſs to, or poſſeſſion of our <hi>Anatomical Chair.</hi> And, that your indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable Induſtry therein may be imitated by your Succeſſors, is the Deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your much Obliged Servant, <hi>D. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:7"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Cuſtom of Apologizing is grown ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhionable, and become ſo very common, that we meet with it at ſome times in thoſe Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where the <hi>Critick</hi> himſelf hath thought it ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous. I muſt own, it ſeems to me not only ſavouring of a becoming Modeſty, but highly reaſonable that an Author excuſe himſelf, where he foreſees Objections will be rais'd againſt him.</p>
            <p>He is now ſuperlatively happy, who can either write or ſpeak without a <hi>Penitet,</hi> or at leaſt a <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det;</hi> and yet if no one would beſtir himſelf on the account of Cenſure, we muſt be ever liable to a much greater Miſchief, occaſion'd by our Silence.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only mention, that the almoſt continual Avo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations by Buſineſs, when this Diſcourſe was penn'd, gave me at ſome times ſo great interruption, as may have render'd the ſame the more incoherent, and will, I hope, prevent an Expectation of any thing studied or accurately curious, which was, as I may ſay, ſtol'n from the ſpare minutes of another's Service.</p>
            <p>The Practiſe of <hi>Chyrurgery,</hi> in which I have been educated, gave me many opportunities to inſpect its Abuſes; and though it was long before I could reſolve to publiſh my Remarks, yet knowing them to be exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſentaneous to the Truth, which ſome few can
<pb facs="tcp:35377:8"/> atteſt, I believ'd they might conduce to the convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at leaſt of ſome of thoſe who have too long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd themſelves to be deluded by Fiction and fair Stories.</p>
            <p>As I have endeavour'd to ſhun a uſeleſs redundancy of words, by abreviating what ſeem'd to run too far upon Speculation, ſo I have likewiſe labour'd to avoid Contention, which was not enforced. However bold it may appear, I can ſatisfie the Reader, that if he comes not prepoſſeſs'd with ſome unreaſonable Prejudice, but will candidly and impartially ſuſpend his Opinion, till he hath conſiderately weigh'd the whole, he will find little wanting towards the making good my Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions, of the neceſſity of a Reformation.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the particular Cauſes of the Contempt of <hi>Chyrurgeons,</hi> and that Art which they profeſs, I have firſt of all expos'd the Empirical Practitioner, whom we call a <hi>Mountebank;</hi> you have here a view of the Origin of his Skill, by which may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gueſs'd how far he hath contributed both to the diſcredit of <hi>Chyrurgery,</hi> and the Peoples ruine.</p>
            <p>Indeed the very ſence of this man's Practice being built upon Tradition only, and his ſo raſhly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting his deteſtable Concluſions on Humane Bodies, ſhould methinks afford us the moſt plenary Intelligence, that his Claim to this Privilege is altogether illegal, and that for this we ought to hold him as the general Object of our Scorn and Averſion; to be much more fearful of him than the ſuppoſed Poyſon he ſwallows down, that his more poyſonous Antidote may be thought ſalubrious.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:8"/>
            <p> You may find, after him, a plain deſcription of the <hi>Libelling Quack,</hi> or <hi>Practiſing Pamphleteer,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting ſome of the Frauds he makes uſe of to delude the Unwary; how meanly he is qualified for the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Phyſick and Surgery, as alſo with what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment both to Purſe and Perſon he is rely'd on.</p>
            <p>Farther, you have an account of the <hi>Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick Barber,</hi> his great Injuſtice to aſſume what he has no right to, his Preſumption for intruding on the ſame, contrary to thoſe Laws that are in force againſt him, and laſtly, his moſt ſhameful Ignorance, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding which he will be tampering out of the reach of his Reaſon, to the ſcandal of every legal Artiſt, and to the preſent diſeſteem of the Art it ſelf.</p>
            <p>There is from hence a digreſſion to give you a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Practice of a <hi>Pretending Boneſetter,</hi> as well inveſtigating his juggling contrivance to amuſe the People, and draw them into a great Opinion of him, as laying open the falſity of his Predictions in point of Practice.</p>
            <p>I have endeavour'd to inform you by ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable Inſtances, how extreamly ignorant this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhews himſelf, and how abſurdly ridiculous, when the real Practice of Boneſetting falls under his care, by which you may learn, that his pretence to the ſame is but a knaviſh Contrivance to cheat men of their Money, and (as it often happens) to ſpoyl them of their Limbs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:9"/>
            <p> Finally, amongſt thoſe who have ſcandaliz'd the Practice both of <hi>Phyſick</hi> and <hi>Chyrurgery,</hi> I have moſt truly characteriz'd our <hi>City Doctreſs,</hi> expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her in all her Qualifications and Endowments, how forward ſhe is to promiſe, and how capable to perform. By the method of her proceedings, you may gain a foreſight how ſerviceable ſhe hath been to rid her Country of ſome thouſands of its Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, and to bring the moſt contemptible Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on our Art, by the burthenſome encroachment ſhe hath made thereon.</p>
            <p>Theſe, with ſome more general Annotations on the Practices of others, are the Contents of the enſuing Diſcourſe, which if the Reader take the pains to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe, he will find neither deliver'd on a meer Report, nor repreſented from a malicious Suggeſtion, but the Caſes truly ſtated, as they happen'd in reality to fall under my obſervation.</p>
            <p>I have been ſo far from impoſing any Miſconſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as to endeavour with the utmoſt caution, that no one Reflection or Remark of Conſequence ſhould eſcape upon a bare Surmiſe or Suppoſition.</p>
            <p>Now, conſidering the great and almoſt unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Comforts we are bleſsd with, in the moſt eminent Reſtorers of our Health, and Preſervers of our Limbs and Lives, I believe there is ſcarce any Nation ſo unfortunately miſerable as ours in their Bodily Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſters, and all upon the account of our moſt intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſufferance of baſe Impoſitions on thoſe honourable Profeſſions; which adds to our Affliction, How is it likely we ſhould be ſecur'd from the fraudulent and knaviſh practices of deceitful men, at a time when
<pb facs="tcp:35377:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> they are ſo much countenanc'd, and even tempted by the ſmall care taken to ſuppreſs their diſingenious and dangerous proceedings; or what other can we expect, than a perpetual decay of Learning, from our great neglect to encourage and promote the ſame; a want of able Practitioners, from the diſcouragements they are ſubjected to, and the conſequence hereof, <hi>viz.</hi> a Univerſal Damage accrewing to the People, till Care be taken to inſpect theſe matters, and remove out of the way the Authors of our Calamities?</p>
            <p>The painful Mr. <hi>Tho. Gale</hi> thought he had abundant reaſon for his Complaint, That there were no leſs than Sixty Women who intermeddled in the Art of Surgery; I doubt not but we have at this time as many ſcore, who in one reſpect or other will preſume hereon, as well to the diſcredit of the Art, as to the deſtruction of the Unwary; there are not many Streets in <hi>London</hi> without three or four, nay, it is a Chance (and that a great one too) if the good Gentlewoman of almoſt every Houſe doth not aſſume the liberty to tamper from <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi>'s Directions.</p>
            <p>Such indeed is the frail Judgment of many in Chyrurgick Affairs, that they believe thoſe men to have the leaſt Knowledge therein, whoſe ſole Right and Propriety it is to practiſe in this worthy Art: The more eminent the <hi>Chyrurgeon</hi> is, he muſt be attended (in their Opinion) with a Conſequence of the greater <hi>Tyrannizer;</hi> or, The more learned the <hi>Artiſt,</hi> the more <hi>fraudulent Oppreſſor.</hi> If you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult any one of theſe, you are told, He will make a Cure, or, That you muſt expect the Work of a <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:35377:10"/> But if you adviſe with any Runnagade <hi>Intruder,</hi> ſome practiſing <hi>Old Wife,</hi> or strowling <hi>Empirick,</hi> ſome boaſting <hi>Quack, Barber,</hi> or <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Undertaking Boneſetter,</hi> with the reſt of this pernicious Tribe, you are to look for honeſt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, fine promiſes, and fair stories. After all, when you recover, which you are not to doubt under their management, you purchaſe Health at a much eaſier rate, than when you expoſe your ſelves to the Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>bloody-minded Surgeon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the frightful <hi>Bugbears</hi> that amuſe the People to ſuch a strange degree of Folly and Indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that from a Relation of this nature, by ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous perſon, they will fly a mile or two, oftentimes a ſcore, from a Faithful Practitioner, to enter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the moſt ordinary handling of an <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Undertaker.</hi> So that our preſent Caſe, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, will reaſonably bear a <hi>Prognoſtick</hi> of this nature, that we may eaſily ſee how matters tend, when the moſt illiterate are advanc'd to a prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence above the Learned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>—Didiciſſe ſideliter artes,</hi> was heretofore accounted the moſt ſerviceable Expence of Time in the whole courſe of Life, as well in reſpect of the profundity of Knowledge, for which Men were formerly ſo highly reputed, as alſo for that (on this account) they were look'd on much better capacitated, and more eminently qualified to counſel ſuch as were in Affliction, and to ſuccour thoſe in Diſtreſs; but it is now far otherwiſe, ſince not ſo much the ſolidity of a Man's Underſtanding (which is his moſt worthy and honourable Endowment, nay, his true and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick
<pb facs="tcp:35377:10"/> Worth) renders him Taking with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People, as his unjuſtly-aſſumed Confidence to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himſelf what he is not, on the most unwarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and unreaſonable grounds imaginable. To be, and to pretend to be, are much at one with them, till they experience the great difference at the cost of their Limbs, and oftentimes at the hazard of Life it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Since therefore I have taken this opportunity to give a ſmall Inſight into their diſhonest Actions, I hope there will not be wanting ſome generous Spirit, who may conſummate the Deſign of our Good Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, at least ſo far as to put a Check to the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Preſumption of baſe men, and to put us (with all Well-wiſhers to the Publick) upon taking ſome ſuch courſe as may ſecure us from being endanger'd by them for the time to come.</p>
            <p>There remains to my ſelf however this Satisfaction, that I have us'd my Endeavours to convince the most incredulous, and on that account have all-along taken care, that the Verity of my own Sentiments and Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, with reſpect to the Abuſes put in practiſe by every of theſe perſons, might be confirm'd by the most demonſtrative Evidence taken from Obſervation of their own Proceedings.</p>
            <p>I have been the leſs ſollicitous to embelliſh or adorn my Diſcourſe after the manner of <hi>Rhetoricians,</hi> ſince I intend it not ſo much for the peruſal of any practical Author, neither to raiſe a <hi>Theo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ical</hi> Diſputation on ſome <hi>novel Hypotheſis,</hi> as for the conviction of the People, who have and do still ſuffer themſelves to be impos'd on.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:11"/>
            <p> Let me give the Reader this farther aſſurance, that I have in no wiſe been perſwaded, over-rul'd, or gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Bait of a particular Intereſt, or other ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Advantage to my ſelf; neither have the Sweets of a Revenge, thruſt forward by ſome inbred Malice for a ſuppos'd Wrong receiv'd, induced me to this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication; but the deep ſenſe I had upon me (for want of ſome ſuch information) how liable we are to ſuffer under the worſt and moſt miſerable circumſtances, from the Practice of Injudicious Men, and withal (which I muſt needs ſay was a conſiderable motive) I was the more willing to appear in publick, out of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Reſpect I am oblig'd to pay that truly worthy and noble Art we call <hi>Chyrurgery,</hi> and no leſs to the Profeſſors thereof; I mean ſuch of them as are quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by a Legal Education to adminiſter herein, whom I was extreamly troubled to ſee ſo ignominiouſly us'd by the Opprobrious Reflections of many Ignorant yet Malevolent <hi>Detractors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Proceed now in charity with a favourable Cenſure, and if thou meet'ſt with thoſe Errors which have eſcap'd mine, or the examination of the <hi>Preſs,</hi> be pleas'd to alter and amend the ſame; if they prove ſuch as are not worthy <hi>Correction,</hi> in kindneſs paſs them by, and let them (with many other trivial <hi>Corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genda)</hi> be look'd on as unavoidable Overſights, through the Weakneſs of the Author's Judgment.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35377:11"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>IT is one of the grand Axioms, or Epithets, given by Philoſophers to (their almoſt Deify'd) Nature, that She is <hi>Sui Conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix;</hi> and as generally believ'd by others, that there is a natural Propenſity in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Kind, to attempt the ſpeedieſt means of Self-preſervation: But truly conſidering the degeneracy of Humane Reaſon in ſome, from what it was of old, and their contradictory Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in the more eminent concerns of Life, we have juſt reaſon to diſpute, whether there be ſuch an inherent Principle or not, that directs infallibly to the Means of Reſtauration, when we are ſubjected to Bodily Infirmities.</p>
            <p>Did not <hi>Ignorance,</hi> with her Darling <hi>Impudence,</hi> caſt a miſt before our Eyes, and darken the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, we might have hopes to ſee this Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Tenet indubitably verified: But whilſt the ingenious Artiſt is exploded, and the <hi>Artleſs Pretender</hi> mean while advanc'd; whilſt the Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Methodical Remedies of the former, are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35377:12"/> held contemptible, and the Empirical Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the latter, (tho' with the greateſt detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to thoſe that uſe them) highly extoll'd and embrac'd: I ſay, till Men can make a more clear diſtinction betwixt one and the other, we may the leſs unreaſonably ſuſpect the Truth of this applauded Notion; and as we have juſt cauſe to compaſſionate the hard fate of the Vulgar, who are daily impos'd on and deluded by the ſpecious Pretences of the moſt Unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, too often to the hazard and forfeiture of their Lives; ſo, I think, it may be accounted the moſt neceſſary piece of ſervice we can do them, to undermine the Foundation of theſe Infamous Impoſtors, to diſſect their pernicious Principles, and lay open the treachery and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety of their Dealings.</p>
            <p>Hereby the unprejudic'd Reader may obtain a Proſpect of the greateſt Benefit that can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crew from the beſt Performances of ſuch a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous ſort of People.</p>
            <p>I conceive it no unpardonable Deviation, if we look back upon Antiquity, and take a view of that ſublime Reſpect which was formerly paid to the true and faithful Practitioner of this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Art.</p>
            <p>Since it will be needleſs to ſpend our time in ſearching for its Original, I ſhall only intimate by the way what is recorded by the Ancients, who are differently opinion'd in the point of Invention.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:35377:12"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Apollo</hi> is very early taken notice of for his profound Wiſdom, particularly in the divine Myſtery of Healing, on which account there was a noble and rich Sepulchre built after his deceaſe, nam'd by the Founders <hi>The Temple of Apollo. Aeſculapius</hi> is thought by ſome to be deſcended of <hi>Apollo,</hi> though <hi>Virgil</hi> ſeems to think him firſt happy in the Diſcovery, and that he was for the ſame dignified by the <hi>Epidauri</hi> with the Title of <hi>a God:</hi> as were alſo his two Sons <hi>Podalirius</hi> and <hi>Machaon,</hi> whom <hi>Celſus</hi> does particularly mention as very eminent for Chyrurgery, being carried from <hi>Crete</hi> to the <hi>Trojan</hi> Wars. But if what is reported of the renowned <hi>Chiron</hi> be true, that he was Maſter to <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> I think with more reaſon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedence will be his. The ſame <hi>Celſus</hi> does far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuppoſe <hi>Hippocrates</hi> to be the Parent of all Medicine, and delivers the Chyrurgick Practice rather from him than any before him. <hi>Soranus</hi> ſays, 'twas <hi>Apollo</hi> firſt invented Medicine, that <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> enlarg'd, and that <hi>Hippocrates</hi> finiſh'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſame, after whoſe death the <hi>Grecians</hi> erected <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n perpetual remembrance of his honourable deeds, a moſt ſtately and fair Tomb, at <hi>Delphi,</hi> near <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> where they ſolemniz'd his Obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, and ſuperſcrib'd this Epitaph:</p>
            <q>Hippocrates <hi>of</hi> Theſſalia, <hi>and by kind of the Country of</hi> Coos, <hi>lies buried in this place: He was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egotten of the Seed of the immortal god</hi> Phebus, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd hath left in the World many Books of Medicine,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:35377:13"/> 
               <hi>to put away Sickneſs, and to preſerve Health: what ſhall we need to ſay more of this worthy Man? there is no man's cunning that can give him his condign Praiſe.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>In the ſucceſſion after theſe, there is mention made of <hi>Galen, Aetius, Paulus Aegineta, Avicen Albucaſis, Guido Cauliacus, Joannes Tagaltius, De Vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>go, Lanfranc,</hi> with many others.</p>
            <p>Farther, in the more ancient times, it is inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated by Dr. <hi>Willis,</hi> (in one of his Prefatory Epiſtles) that before the Medicinal Art wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> methodically digeſted, when Phyſick was give<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at random, as 'tis now-adays by Empiricks an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> old Women, they held their experimental <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe</hi>'s (which had been try'd, and prov'd ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) in ſo great eſteem, that they were look'd o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as ſacred Monuments of Mercy, and diligently reſerv'd in their conſecrated Temples: but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> after-Ages, when their Underſtandings wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more refin'd, and a more general ſucceſs atten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded the rational adminiſtrations of ingeniou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Artiſts, it is recorded, that the ſuperſtitiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Greeks were blinded with ſuch a fervent zea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as to Deifie their more eminent profeſs'd Chy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rurgions, and adore them in the number of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gods.</p>
            <p>The wiſeſt of Men, from the beginning o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the World to this latter Age, in conſideratio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that our Art hath for its exerciſe the moſt n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble of Subjects, which is no other than the Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vine Image of the Creator, conſidering lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35377:13"/> the many Caſualties that were ſtill wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to ſubvert the Oeconomy of Man's corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtate, have, for theſe Reaſons as well as others, reputed and accounted Us the Hands of the Almighty.</p>
            <p>But if we enquire what particular Perſons they were that had this Homage render'd them, we ſhall find them ſuch as were legally conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, for the diſcharge of ſo great a Duty as lay incumbent on them. There were no ſuch Swarms of <hi>Pſeudo-Medici &amp; Chyrurgi,</hi> as now diſturb the Town, and poyſon its Inhabitants, admitted into their Reverend Societies. They paid not this Reſpect to any, unleſs thoſe who had been educated <hi>(ab incunabulis)</hi> by the moſt diligent ſervice under the greateſt Maſters; for they look'd on Humane Life of too high a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern to be tamper'd with by the barbarous H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nds of a rude and ignorant ſort of People. They found no reaſon in thoſe days to prize and overvalue the famous <hi>Italian</hi> or <hi>High-Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Doctor, thereby to degrade and deſpiſe the more worthy Phyſicians their fellow-Citizens; neither would they confide in the moſt ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous abſurd Predictions of the calculating <hi>Piſs-prophets</hi> that now moleſt us. For why? There was a communicative Knowledge to each other, that the ſuperſtructure of theſe mens Aſs-trologick Judgments, was founded on their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſatiable deſire of Gain, which they procure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o themſelves out of the Spoils of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:35377:14"/>
            <p> We read not, till of late, of any inferiour <hi>Mechanic</hi> ſo ſpeedily advancing as to commence preſently Doctor of Phyſick, profeſs'd <hi>Chyrurgick Operator,</hi> yet ſtill a <hi>Mountebank.</hi> No, <hi>Petticoat Practitioners</hi> were formerly accounted <hi>Oracles,</hi> or their Skill eſteem'd valuable in competition with the legal Surgeons: They were endow'd with greater Prudence than to run a mile or two af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an ignorant Butcher, to enquire whether the ingenious Artiſt had perform'd his Duty: but in all times of their Calamities, and on all emergent occaſions, could ſafely ask Counſel, and confide in the true and genuine Sons of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> expecting from the Endeavours of theſe men (under God) the Reſtauration and Preſervation of their Limbs and Lives.</p>
            <p>If we would reflect now on the great and mighty illuſtration the Medicinal Science hath receiv'd in the preſent Age by many rare and admirable Inventions of ſome modern and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Spirits, we might ſuppoſe they have had great reaſon to expect rather an augmentation than diminution of that Honour which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to their Predeceſſors; not only for the conſiderable Advantages they have made by their Diſcoveries, in order to compleat and perfect both Study and Practice of Phyſick, but alſo for their great Induſtry, and the pains that it hath coſt them to erect another Fabrick on the Baſis of ſolid Reaſon, whereby they have adapted the moſt intricate, obſcure, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectural
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35377:14"/> 
               <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of the Ancients to plain, eaſie and practical Demonſtrations.</p>
            <p>We have had indeed ſuch conſiderable and magnificent Contributions towards the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating of this worthy Science, that the moſt voluminous of the Ancients, nay, (if it may be pardonable to ſay ſo) the whole Body of Phyſick, as then confuſedly and darkly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pil'd, is a rude and indigeſted <hi>Chaos,</hi> compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively to one ſingular Invention of the <hi>Neote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks,</hi> whoſe ſublime Speculations and proficu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Experiments are elegantly deſcanted on by Dr. <hi>Charlton,</hi> in the account he gives a Friend in <hi>France,</hi> of the conſiderable improvement of Learning here in <hi>England,</hi> where he thus accoſts him in ſome parts of his Diſcourſe.</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <hi>In the College of Phyſicians in</hi> London, <hi>which (without offence to any thing but their own Modeſty) I may pronounce to be the moſt eminent Society of Men for Learning, Judgment, and Induſtry that is now, or at any time hath been in the whole World. Here you may behold the Houſe of</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon; <hi>ſome there are who conſtantly employ themſelves in diſſecting Animals of all kinds, as well living as dead; and faithfully recording all Singularities that occur to their obſervations, both in the ſeveral Species and Individuals; that ſo they may come to know what is perfectly natural, what preternatural, what rare and monſtrous amongſt the Parts of them, and alſo what reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance there is betwixt the conformation of the Parts in the Body of Man, and thoſe in the Bodies</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:35377:15"/> 
               <hi>of other Animals, ordain'd by Nature to the ſame or like and equivalent uſes. Others there are who daily inveſtigate Arguments to confirm and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance that incomparable Invention of the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> Harvey, <hi>in his Circulation of the Blood, and have already brought the Doctrine thereof to ſo high a degree of perfection, that it is not only ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and admired by all the Schools of</hi> Europe, <hi>but the advancers of it alſo are able to ſolve moſt of the difficult</hi> Phoenomena <hi>in</hi> Pathology, <hi>only by this Hypotheſis; and frequently effect ſuch Cures by having reſpect thereunto, in their Intentions and Preſcripts, as well in</hi> chronick <hi>as</hi> acute <hi>Diſeaſes, as would not be hoped from any other Ground-work formerly laid.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Indeed this ſingular tranſcendent Diſcovery hath given more light to the <hi>Materia Medica</hi> than all the laborious Tryals, Inventions, and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments that had been practis'd in former Ages; I may ſay, that the whole <hi>Syſtem</hi> of Anatomy, Phyſick, and Chyrurgery have hereby receiv'd ſuch g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat amendments and alterations, that the quondam Clouds of Ignorance ſeem wholly to be diſpers'd. Here is no flying to occult cauſes for an explanation of ſeeming Difficulties, (which was the Refuge of the Ancients) nor any other <hi>Aſylum</hi> left for the Unlearned; but the progreſs of each Diſtemper incident to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, with its various appearances in the <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, augment, ſtate, and declenſion,</hi> are perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly ſaid open and unfolded from an <hi>Aetyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> built upon Inferences gather'd from this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35377:15"/> and laſting Foundation. But to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute a little farther the aforeſaid Author, where he proceeds;</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <hi>There are moreover amongst the Members of this Venerable Society, who purſuing the hint given them ſome few years ſince, by</hi> Jacobus Mullerus, <hi>in an academical exerciſe of the Nature of Animal and Voluntary Motion, have gone far towards the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Reaſons and Manners of the motion of the Muſcles, by the Principles of</hi> Mechanicks; <hi>an Enterprize of great difficulty, and long deſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as leading us to underſtand the</hi> Geometry <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd by the Creator in the Fabrick of the</hi> Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſm, <hi>and the verification of Anatomical Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by Demonſtrations Mathematical. There are others who have found out a more commodious uſe of the Glands than all antecedent Anatomiſts aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to them; with other conſiderable Diſcoveries that have been made, ſuch as the Motion of the Chylous Juice from the Stomach to the</hi> Receptacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Chyli; <hi>the falſity of that Opinion, that the Liver was the immediate inſtrument of Sanguifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is now found inſervient to no other uſe than the ſequeſtration of the bilious Particles of the Blood, conveying the ſame into the Gall, to be thence excluded into the Guts, the diſcovery of the Lympha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Veſſels, with many others.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Moreover, were we deſirous to take a view of the conſiderable Improvements that have been made by ſome learned Men of our own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Profeſſion, we need but take the trouble of peruſing thoſe elaborate Lectures of Dr. <hi>Reed,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:35377:16"/> Mr. <hi>Woodall,</hi> with many more, not forgetting to make particular mention of thoſe methodical and practical Obſervations of Mr. <hi>Serjeant Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, amongſt others, are the Helps we have receiv'd from the unwearied Labours of Men eminent in our Art, ſo that if the College of Phyſicians is allow'd metaphorically to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Solomon</hi>'s <hi>Houſe,</hi> I think we may pronounce our <hi>Anatomick Theatre</hi> in Surgeons Hall, to be a very ſplendid and glorious apartment thereof; not ſo much for the curioſity of Structure, as for the Streams of Eloquence and good Litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, flowing from thoſe Fountains of True Wiſdom Dr. <hi>Brown</hi> and Dr. <hi>Tyſon,</hi> whoſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did and impartial Diſcoveries for the ſupport of what we all deſire, <hi>viz.</hi> Health and its continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, will never ſufficiently be compenſated by this purblind Age.</p>
            <p>Have we not then a juſt cauſe to ſtand ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at the predominant Folly of ſome, who will rather chuſe to truſt their Bodies in the hands of <hi>Quacks</hi> and other fraudulent Profeſſors, than in thoſe of the moſt judicious and skilful Practitioners: and truly, if the learned Dr. <hi>Feat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> thought he had ſuch great reaſon to inveigh againſt the Sufferance of <hi>Laymen</hi>'s impoſing on the Miniſterial Function, who took on them (the moſt unlearned <hi>Mechanicks)</hi> to expound the Sacred Scriptures, to the diſgrace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopal Authority:</hi> Have not we, I ſay, as great occaſion to diſſent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35377:16"/> from, and admire at the preſent toleration of thoſe great Abuſes, which by the moſt illegal and ignorant Intruders are offer'd to the noble and divine Myſtery of Healing. I may truly juſtifie the word <hi>Myſtery,</hi> ſince it is ſo undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, to thoſe who by their moſt impure and nocuous conceptions thereof, their evil Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and oftentimes fatal Performances therein, have brought a general Scandal on the moſt noble of all Arts, an Art which was deliver'd unto fallen Man by the Almighty himſelf, and hath been accounted the moſt excellent of all others, by the wiſe and ſupreme Donor, as well as in the ſight of Princes; which made King <hi>Solomon</hi> adviſe us to give Honour to the Phyſician, ſince the Higheſt Lord hath created him for our Help and Health. The moſt wiſe <hi>Hebrecion</hi> gives this Encomium of Medicine, That it proceeds from the Moſt High, and that the ancient and moſt wiſe men of the Land have brought it forth; he that is wiſe will not deſpiſe it.</p>
            <p>What pity is it, and how juſtly do we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, that this our honourable Art, which in former times the moſt renowned Kings and Princes did not diſdain to dignifie, not only by their Contributions to render its Fame immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, but alſo by diligently practiſing themſelves therein, that it ſhould now unworthily be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench'd on, and degraded by the unjuſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of the very Scum of the Earth? This the vaunting <hi>Emperick,</hi> and couzening <hi>Quack,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:35377:17"/> the confident <hi>Barber,</hi> the fraudulent <hi>Bone-ſetter,</hi> and ignorant Old <hi>Woman;</hi> This all people, of whatever Condition or Occupation, take on them to adminiſter and intermeddle withal: Nay, theſe men tell us ſo many Stories of their grand Atchievements, of the ſafe, certain, ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and infallible Remedies they have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd by their multiply'd Experience, that it ſhall eſcape them hard if they poſſeſs us not with a Belief, that we run the greateſt hazard in the truſting our Diſtempers to the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any other (though infinitely more skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) than themſelves; the meaneſt of their Medicines outvys all other Compoſitions for their Vertues; and the moſt inferiour of their Adminiſtrations muſt be reputed a <hi>Panacea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great and only ſupport of theſe mens Credit is built on ſuch lying and romantick Stories; and though the perſon that hath once try'd the beſt of their Performances moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly carries about him (perhaps to his Life's end) a ſufficient Remembrancer of their abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Practice, yet for a more publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, and that I may deter others from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into their hands, I ſhall uſe my weak En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to diſplay theſe notorious Cheats in their true and proper colours, to divulge their wheedling Inſinuations, and expoſe to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Eye as well the weakneſs of their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens as their Miſcarriages in moſt, if not all, their inſolent Undertakings, that ſo the World may ſee we are as willing to preſerve them
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35377:17"/> from, as to recover them out of Danger.</p>
            <p>I am ſenſible, that for want of ſuch a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Mark between Art and Ignorance, there have been many well-meaning and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Perſons, who have ſhipwrack'd both their Health and Fortunes by their moſt dangerous encounters with ſuch, who as they value not their Reputation in the forfeit of their Credit, ſo are they the leſs concern'd at the loſs of (what they never had) a Good Name, if thereby they can accumulate their unjuſtly-acquir'd Gain; the diſcharge of Conſcience is to them of no concern, for if they heeded that, the bare ſenſe of their Guilt in a moſt groſs Simplicity would fly in their Faces, and debar them of thoſe Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges they now endeavour to engroſs unto themſelves.</p>
            <p>If the confident declaration of a Man's own Skill to the World be of ſufficient force to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the People to employ him, without an impartial conſideration whether there be any thing of Merit to render him acceptable; or if his own poſitive Aſſertions of thoſe great and mighty things he has perform'd, without any thing of diſquiſition, be capable to conſtrain their applauſe, we have the leſs reaſon ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly to admire how ſome Men have gain'd ſuch conſiderable ground amongſt Rational Creatures.</p>
            <p>With reſpect to the moſt welcome and eaſie admittance to the Truſt and Confidence repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by incautelous People, in the extravagant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35377:18"/> boaſting of <hi>Emperical Quackſalvers;</hi> and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration that their Breach of Promiſe, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their unſucceſsful Practice, have been but little available to forewarn others how they ruſh into the ſame Miſchiefs; theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections ſhould, in my opinion, encourage eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man who reſpects the Miſerable, to take care that they be not deluded by the ſpecious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of thoſe who have preſum'd to ſtile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Metropolitan Phyſicians,</hi> the moſt <hi>infallible Health-Reſtorers of the People,</hi> having gain'd their Knowledge by <hi>ten, twenty,</hi> ſometimes <hi>thirty years</hi> Induſtrious Study; when 'tis a Chance at the ſame time if they ever look'd on any other piece than <hi>Queen Elizabeth's Cloſet, Culpepper's Engliſh Phyſician,</hi> and his <hi>Midwifry, Ariſtotle's Problems,</hi> or his <hi>Maſterpiece,</hi> with ſome other choice Cabinet of <hi>Phyſical Receipts.</hi> And on this ſmall ſtock of Knowledge, with a much greater proviſion of undaunted Impudence, they account themſelves deſerving ſuch ſounding Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, whereby they inſinuate themſelves into the Peoples favour, and by degrees draw them into a perſwaſion, that they are the only Men fitted for the cure of all Diſtempers, as well by Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Remedies as Topical Applications.</p>
            <p>It is unlikely I ſhould frame a more ſuitable deſcription of theſe wonderful <hi>Operators,</hi> than we have given us by an ancient Author, in his Office of a Chyrurgeon, on which account I ſhall take the liberty to tranſcribe what is moſt for our preſent purpoſe, in his own words.</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:35377:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is requiſite</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that this Artiſt be not only learned in the Theory, but alſo that he be brought up under ſome cunning Man, which hath good Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the ſame Art; for otherwiſe it is not poſſible to come to the exact and perfect knowledge thereof. If I ſhould tell you of the ungracious Witchcrafts, and of the miſchievous Abuſes and Miſuſes that have been in times paſt, and yet in our days continually uſed, ye would a little marvel thereat: But foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it hath not only turned to the diſhonour of God, but alſo to the ſtate of the Common-wealth, I have thought good to declare unto you part of their wicked doings, that it may be unto you who profeſs this</hi> Art <hi>an Example, to avoid the like wretched Deeds. Theſe things I do not ſpeak to you of Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, but of my own Knowledge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Year One thouſand Five hundred Sixty two, I did ſee in the two Hoſpitals in</hi> London, <hi>St.</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas<hi>'s and St.</hi> Bartholomew<hi>'s, to the number of Three hundred and odd poor people, that were diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of ſore Legs, ſore Arms, Feet, and Hands, with other parts of the Body, ſo grievouſly infected, that One hundred and twenty of them could never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd without loſs of Leg or Arm, a Foot or Hand, Fingers or Toes, or elſe their Limbs crooked, ſo that they were either maimed or undone for ever. All theſe were brought to this Miſchief by Witches, by Women, and by Counterfeit Javils, that take upon them to uſe the Art, not only robbing them of their Money, but of their Limbs and perpetual Health. And I</hi> (ſaith our Author) <hi>with ſome others, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently Examining theſe poor people how they came by</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:35377:19"/> 
                  <hi>their grievous Hurts, and who were their Chyrurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that look'd unto them; they confeſs'd that they were either Witches, which did promiſe by Charms to make them whole, or elſe ſome Women that were to cure them with Herbs, and ſuch-like things, or ſome Vagabond Javil, that runneth from one Country to another, promiſing unto them Health, and deceiving them of their Money.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Fault and Crime of the undoing of this Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, were laid unto the Chyrurgions, I will not ſay by part of thoſe who were at that time Maſters of the ſame Hoſpitals; but it was ſaid, that Carpenters, Women, Weavers, Coblers, and Tinkers did cure more People than the Chyrurgions themſelves; but what manner of Cures they did, I have already told you, ſuch Cures as all the World may wonder at; yea, I ſay, ſuch Cures as makes the Devil in Hell to dance for joy, to ſee the poor Members of Jeſus Chriſt ſo miſerably tormented. What ſhall I ſay hereunto, but lament and pray unto our Lord Jeſus, for his precious Blood ſake that was ſhed upon the Croſs, to illuminate the Hearts of the Magiſtrates, for amendment hereof; and that this Rabblement of Runnagates, with Witches, Bawds, and the Devil's Southſayers, with Tinkers, Coblers, and Sowgelders, and all other the wicked Coherents of theſe ſame Deviliſh Sects, which do thus abuſe the Noble Art of Medicine, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and amended; and every one to get their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with Truth in the ſame Arts that they have been brought up in; elſe to be grievouſly puniſh'd, as they be in other Countries, and as they have been here in times paſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:35377:19"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>I think the Prince is bound in Conſcience to puniſh thoſe falſe and wicked pernicious Deceivers, who do not only deſtroy the Limbs of Man, but his Life alſo. Of this ſort</hi> London <hi>is as well ſtor'd as the Country, for I believe there be not ſo few therein as Threeſcore Women, who practiſe in the Art of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick and Surgery: Of theſe (ſome are called wiſe Women, or holy and good Women) there are many ſorts and ſects, as ſome for ſore Breaſts, ſome for the Stone and Strangury, ſome for Pain in the Teeth, others for Scald Heads, ſome famous for ſore Throats, others for ſore Legs, with a Thouſand more;</hi> Galen <hi>in his Book of Sects never made mention of half ſo many. I think, if this worſhipful Rabblement were gather'd together, they would make a much greater proceſſion than ever did the Monks, Fryars, and Nuns, when they ſwarmed moſt in</hi> London.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This unprofitable Company have ſo encreas'd in this City, that all the Countries in</hi> England <hi>have taken notice thereof; yea, and at this day all the Countries in</hi> Chriſtendom <hi>may wonder at our Laws, in ſuffering and maintaining of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well, I ſay, we will let theſe paſs with Tinkers, Carpenters, Old Women,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and a great many of other Occupations, whereof ſome come out of</hi> France, <hi>ſome out of</hi> Germany, <hi>and ſo of other Countries, ſome for Religion, and ſome to pick Pockets. And all theſe are now become great</hi> Phyſicians, <hi>and</hi> Chyrurgions, <hi>to the no ſmall advancement of this noble Art of Medicine; for their worthy Cures do bear ſuch witneſs thereof, and give ſuch a Report unto them, that at this day the learned</hi> Phyſicians
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35377:20"/> 
                  <hi>and</hi> Chyrurgions <hi>may not a little rejoice. I ſay no more, but God amend all, and unleſs theſe things are quickly amended, I think the diſeaſed people with Wounds, Ulcers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are like to have ſmall help; and if it ſhall chance the</hi> Prince <hi>to have Wars, then are this Company that I have ſpoken of like to ſerve. And I doubt nothing, but that the Souldiers ſhall have great courage to fight, foraſmuch as they ſhall have ſuch a goodly company of Chyrurgions to cure them when they are wounded: As for others, there will be but few left, unleſs better order be taken, and that with ſpeed.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Thus we ſee that in thoſe days the unwearied Endeavours of illiterate and baſe People were not wanting in their Knaviſh Practices to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Medicinal Art; but leſt I tire my Reader with a preliminary Diſcourſe, I ſhall haſten to expoſe (which was the drift of my Undertaking) the Principal Intruders on and Pretenders to the ſame, by whoſe diſingenuous Practice it hath receiv'd ſo great a diminution in the eſtimate of ſome reſponſible, but moſtly the common People; each of which you will find the Subject of a particular Section.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:35377:20"/>
            <head>Apologia Chyrurgica.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p>UPON enquiry into the Cauſes of the Contempt both of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> and <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions,</hi> we ſhall find in the firſt place (as one great Promoter hereof) the perfidious Practices of a Fellow whom the Vulgar entitle <hi>Mountebank.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He is one whoſe true and fixed Character, with reſpect to his unſetled ſtate and condition, cannot properly be render'd, and therefore we will content our ſelves with a deſcription of his Employment.</p>
               <p>An <hi>Emperick</hi> or <hi>Mountebank</hi> (after Dr. <hi>Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card</hi>'s conciſe and pithy remark on him) is one who vends his irrational and immethodical Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines to the Rabble that ſurround him; for being mounted on the publick Stage of his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, he blows ſo loud the Trumpet of his (otherwiſe inſupportable) Fame, that the Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35377:21"/> who paſs by him run as great hazard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing infected from his Diſcourſe, as did the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> when they ſtop'd their Ears, to prevent being captivated by the charming <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, the muſical concord of his Notes cannot be ſuppos'd ſo tempting as was theirs; yet by reaſon of thoſe fatal Events which do at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Unwary, that by this Bait are hauled into his Net, he may be look'd on as more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous than thoſe ficitious Muſicianers.</p>
               <p>Having ſent his Fool before him, with his other antick Attendants, by ſome pleaſing, tho' ridiculous Geſtures, to allure the People; when his Auditory is ſomewhat numerous, Sir <hi>Fop</hi> himſelf (upon notice given) immediately mounts the Stage, and after a very reverend Congee to his ignorant Admirers, addreſſeth himſelf to this purpoſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Gentlemen,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The deep ſence of your ſubjection to Bodily Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and your want of the moſt true and neceſſary means for your recovery: I ſay, weighing in my Mind the multitude of Diſtempers which my fellow Creatures are liable to undergo, if not redreſſed by the hands of Art; and withal well knowing your want of able Phyſicians, I thought in this great exigency there was an abſolute neceſſity for me to force my ſelf from that private and contemplative life I lead in the free enjoyment of a plentiful Eſtate, to make known to you my Abilities in the practiſe of Phyſick as well as Surgery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:35377:21"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>I will aſſure you, Gentlemen, I have obtain'd ſuch stupendious ſpecifick Remedies, for the cure of most, if not all your Diſtempers, as no Mortal beſides my ſelf can reaſonably pretend to.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Now having his Man ready that attends his motions with his Diſh of Trumpery for the entertainment of his Gueſts, he firſt pulls out his little Box of Electuary, and proceeds.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here is firſt of all, Gentlemen, my true and only famous</hi> Orvietan, <hi>a Medicine of ſuch admirable property, that it expels all manner of Poyſon, which is incident to the whole Race of</hi> Adam<hi>'s Poſterity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gentlemen, this only adminiſtration ſtrikes at the very Root of Diſtempers, and perfectly eradicates the worſt of their Concomitants. The</hi> Orvietan <hi>of it ſelf, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, is very well worth your Money, but 'tis the conſideration of your Wants, and the real neceſſity that there is to keep ſuch things by you, that occaſions me out of a cordial love and reſpect to your welfare, to let you have ſome other things, almoſt</hi> gratis, <hi>into the bargain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here are next of all, Gentlemen, my</hi> Pilulae Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentiſſimae, <hi>a moſt incomparable Purge I will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, Gentlemen, which anſwer all Intentions of purging Phyſick, and are the moſt friendly to Nature of any thing yet known: They ſweep the Stomach, cleanſe it of all Impurities whatſoever, and carry them forth of doors with the greateſt eaſe imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:35377:22"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>You have next, Gentlemen, my</hi> Pulvis contra Vermes, <hi>or Pouder which kills all Worms: This Pouder, Gentlemen, not only expels thoſe Crudities, and the Corruption which engenders thoſe troubleſome Inſects, but alſo procures a good Appetite, makes a light Heart, and recreates all the Spirits, as well natural, vital, and animal. And now, Gentlemen, that you may ſee I am as willing to take care of thoſe outward Accidents you are prone to, as your inward Diſtempers,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I give you, Fourthly, my</hi> Emplaſtrum divinum, <hi>which for its wonderful Vertues may truly be ſo call'd. It cures all Aches proceeding from Heat or Cold, Pains of what kind ſoever in any part of the Body; it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves Tumors of all ſorts, tho' never ſo obdurate and hard to be dealt withal by other Remedies. In ſhort Gentlemen, you need no other Plaiſter to keep by you on any account whatſoever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You have laſtly, Gentlemen, my</hi> Balſamum Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum Virtutum, <hi>which cures all Wounds, Ulcers, Fiſtula's, and what not? for indeed it is of ſufficient force to withſtand all putrefied Humours lodged in any part of the Body. So that you ſee, Gentlemen, I am as willing to ſave you the unreaſonable Fees of other Phyſicians, as the extraordinary Sums of Mony which a Chyrurgeon requires for a ſmall and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Cure.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Having made this learned Harangue to the People, and rehears'd the ſame two or three times over, he leaves them to pauſe a while, and then diverts them with an Interlude of his fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35377:22"/> Drollery; which being over, and <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur</hi> the <hi>Doctor</hi> majeſtically withdrawn, his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate Juggler</hi> (almoſt as good an Oratour as himſelf) begins to this effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Gentlemen, I would earneſtly entreat you, for your own ſafety, to embrace this fit Opportunity of purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing theſe moſt infallible Medicines, whilſt you may have the great benefit to find the Doctor in Town, which will be but a week at fartheſt.</hi>
                  </q> (At the ſame time he deſigns to ſtay till he is forc'd to fly the Town.) <hi>But,</hi> continues he,</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I'll aſſure you, Gentlemen, you will never meet with the like Opportunity as long as you live.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Doctor,</hi> Firſt <hi>of all, preſents you, Gentlemen, with his moſt famous</hi> Orvietan, <hi>which is the greateſt Wonder in Nature, to procraſtinate your Health and Lives.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>He almoſt gives you his</hi> Pilulae Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiſſimus, <hi>in Engliſh,</hi> The moſt excellent of Pills.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>Here is the Dr's</hi> Pulve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Vermibus, <hi>or his Pouder to kill all manner of Worms in Men, Women, and Children.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>You may have his</hi> Emplaſtrum divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, <hi>or a Plaiſter to cure all manner of Aches, Pains, Swellings, or Tumors whatſoever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fifthly, <hi>and laſtly, Gentlemen, here is the Dr's</hi> Balſamum multutum vertarum, <hi>which heals all Wounds, Ulcers, and other Accidents proceeding from what Cauſe ſoever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:35377:23"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>You have all the whole Pacquet, Gentlemen, for the inconſiderable price of one Shilling.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gentlemen, 'tis not the ſmall Gain which is gotten hereby that maintains the Doctor's charge of his Coach and Horſes; no, Gentlemen, he does it purely for the benefit of poor People, as well as others, who are willing to be rul'd by his Directions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now Gentlemen, thoſe that are willing to be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of theſe ſerviceable Remedies, let them throw up their Mony in Glove or Handkerchief, and the whole Pacquet ſhall be return'd them therein. If you make not uſe of the preſent time, you muſt not blame the Doctor, when it ſhall pleaſe him deſervedly to debar you of this great privilege, by his ſpeedy abſence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>I have been the rather willing to impoſe the trouble of peruſing theſe great Impertinencies, in regard that from this exact Copy of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, the whole Deſign may be more commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly gueſs'd at; for, firſt of all, his elevating the Minds of the conceited <hi>Vulgar</hi> with the title of <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> (without which he ſcarce repeats a ſentence) argues his Endeavour from bringing them into a high opinion of themſelves, that they may harbour the ſame of him, and that he the more unſuſpectedly may carry on his Cheats.</p>
               <p>Secondly, His frivolous Circumlocution and repetition of the ſame Diſcourſe, implies as well his Ignorance, as his inceſſant appetite of Lucre.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:35377:23"/>
               <p> Thirdly, His thus openly publiſhing himſelf to the World doth clearly indicate his want of Merit to be ſought after, and the ſhift he is put to for to purchaſe a Living, by making this abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable fabulous proclamation.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, His vain Oſtentation by the antick Fooleries of his <hi>Tumblers</hi> and <hi>Ropedancers</hi> beſpeaks him to be the greateſt Spend-time of the People, who are the rather willing to tarry, when the thought of their Buſineſs is diverted by the Conceits of <hi>Merry Andrew,</hi> and the Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bank in the Interval, finds the Sweets of an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to put off and vend his Empirical Compoſitions.</p>
               <p>Truly, this Fellow may moſt juſtly be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the Common Enemy of the People, not only for the Time he cheats them of, which ſhould be otherwiſe employ'd, but alſo for their Money, which (if they want not for their own or their Family's ſubſiſtence, and know not to employ it more advantagiouſly) is better thrown to Swine, who will not evilly reward them, than given to theſe deceitful <hi>Quack-pretenders,</hi> who prey both on their Purſe and Perſons.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, and laſtly, (which is the number of his Medicines) His inconſiderately aſcribing ſo many and different Vertues to each ſingle and improper Remedy, without reflecting on the various Intentions and Alterations that are eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially made in <hi>Surgery,</hi> before we can accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh the cure of any compound Indiſpoſition, doth abſolutely demonſtrate him to be ignorant
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35377:24"/> and knaviſh, and as great a Novice in <hi>Surgery</hi> as his <hi>Hireling Jack-pudding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having given you this curſory view of the <hi>Mountebank</hi> upon his Stage, we will now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct you to his Lodging, which is commonly near thereto, in ſome publick Victualling-houſe or Inn, where his Hoſt (perhaps for botching up ſome former Clap, or out of an expectation of Cuſtom to his Houſe) ſuffers him to live Rent-free.</p>
               <p>His Chamber is commonly ſet off with Skele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons of <hi>Puggs, Doggs, Rabbits,</hi> and other Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, which he has got ſome Butcher's Boy to anatomize and ſet together for him. There are likewiſe the ſtuff'd Skins of <hi>Crocodiles, Panthers,</hi> and <hi>Sea-Lyons,</hi> and theſe, he tells the People, are ſuch as have been preſented him, for ſome remarkable Cures in his dangerous Travels thro' the remoteſt parts of the World.</p>
               <p>In his Window it's poſſible you may find half a peck of Teeth, ſome of which (as he tells you) he threw out on the Stage with the Point of his Sword, others with an imperceptible touch of the fore-finger of his right hand.</p>
               <p>In other parts of his Chamber you may ſee Humane Bones, being ſuch (he would inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate) as he hath amputated or diſmember'd on neceſſitous occaſions, yet by a more particular Enquiry we ſhall find he procur'd them after the ſame manner as his <hi>Caemiterean</hi> Teeth, or thoſe from the Church-yard.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:35377:24"/>
               <p> I ſhall conclude theſe Remarks with the reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of an Account I had given me ſome time ſince, of a certain famous <hi>Empirick,</hi> who upon a Viſit made him by a Gentlewoman for his Advice, about a Pain in her Breaſt, ſhe chanc'd to eſpy under a Glaſs in his Cloſet a very black and deform'd piece of Fleſh, which (out of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity) enqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, the Mountebank very impudently told her, that it was a Cancer'd Breaſt which he had taken from the Body of a certain <hi>Indian</hi> Queen, whom he had recover'd in three weeks afterwards. The Gentlewoman, ſurpriz'd at the Skill of this famous Operator, when ſhe came home, imparted it to ſome of her Neighbours, upon which the whole Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture was detected<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Breaſt prov'd no other than that of a poor Womans, by which Exciſion he had ſent her into the other World, and kept her Breaſt as a Pledge for payment of the Mony, till ſhe ſhould come back again to redeem it; which when he had boyl'd, as <hi>Ketch</hi> does his quarter'd Members, (to preſerve them from being tainted by the Air) he kept as a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of his admirable Dexterity.</p>
               <p>It would be too tedious to enumerate all the Cheats ſuch Perſons practiſe, to render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves famous; and therefore waving their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Enarration, I ſhall give you as ſhort an account of his Education or Initiation in the Practiſe of Phyſick, by which you may perceive the utmoſt of his accompliſhments in that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime Science.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:35377:25"/>
               <p> By an <hi>Enquiry</hi> of this nature you will find, that the whole of his Judgment proceeds from a Twelvemonths cohabitation with ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Practitioner, who after covenanting that he ſhould not moleſt him when he practiſeth for himſelf, (for a ſmall Stipend) permits this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truder to inſpect his Buſineſs, till the expiration of ſuch a term of time; when the little Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Conceit, thinking himſelf ſufficiently flegg'd in Knowledge, having thrown aſide his Leading-ſtrings, begins to ſoar aloft on the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of his unbounded Pride, and ſcorning thoſe mean Retirements of an obſcure Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, who permits himſelf to be ſought to, he thinks he hath already a ſufficient Call to publiſh himſelf to the World; and thereupon immediately erects a Stage in ſome City or Market-Town, where he perpetrates the moſt enormous Miſchiefs, under the notion of a moſt undoubted Preſerver of the People's Lives.</p>
               <p>If this does not exactly quadrate with his ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, but that he deſcends from a better Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny than the former, having ſpent his Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny through his extravagant living, and diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to labour otherwiſe for his Bread; in this exigency he can find out no better method for an idle and eaſie life, than that of turning Mountebank; in order whereto, conſidering likewiſe that it was abſolutely neceſſary he ſhould be skill'd in ſome Terms of Art, the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of a few Simples, and the making up ſome vulgar Remedies (which he can eaſily diſguiſe)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35377:25"/> to amuſe the People. On ſuch-like Reflections he betakes himſelf to the turning over ſome plain and intelligible Author, from a ſhort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with whom, together with the advantage of indifferent Natural Parts, he ſets up for the moſt experienc'd <hi>Phyſick</hi> and <hi>Chyrurgick Profeſſor</hi> about Town: yet at the ſame time, if he were brought to the Teſt, 'tis moſt certain, that he (nay, the ableſt of them all) knows not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to deliver either <hi>Diagnoſtick</hi> or <hi>Prognoſtick</hi> in the moſt uſual of diſaſtrous occurrences to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Life, and ſo much a Stranger to <hi>Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery,</hi> that you will find him unable to give a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerning Queriſt a ſatisfactory definition of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Wound</hi> or <hi>Ulcer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now theſe are the fit <hi>Idols</hi> of the Peoples Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, whoſe quacking and diſhoneſt dealings meet with leſs Calumny and Oppoſition than the juſt and artificial proceedings of the <hi>Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate Practitioner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One great Bait wherewith this <hi>Pretender</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnares his <hi>Auditory,</hi> is his fair Carriage and ſplendid Equipage: and indeed (what is moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be lamented) when by the influence of a Friend at Court he can skrew himſelf into the Prince's favour, he then bears all before him, with his aſſumed Title of a <hi>Regius-Profeſſor ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narius,</hi> or (as <hi>Medicaſter Medicatus</hi> in his Banter upon <hi>J. B.) One of the King's moſt Ordinary Practitioners.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:35377:26"/>
               <p> The two notorious <hi>Empiricks,</hi> that have for ſome years paſt infeſted <hi>England,</hi> when they had by the like means procur'd, as they call it, the Signal Teſtimony of a Prince's Favour, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were no ſooner mounted on the Stage, but it was expos'd to the Peoples view, who were from a proſpect of this Royal Gratuity to reſpect them as it were by conſequence for very emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Phyſicians.</hi> But did not the many fatal Errors committed by them in moſt parts of the Town declare their Arrogance, as well as Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance: yet I am well ſatisfy'd, that a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Perſon can value no man ſo much on a gaudy appearance, as on that of a ſound and rational Judgment, which is not only furniſh'd by <hi>Autopſy,</hi> in a continued ſeries of Practical Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, but adorn'd with the Theory of the choiceſt Authors.</p>
               <p>It may not be from our purpoſe, if I inform you, that notwithſtanding the Titles of <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> and <hi>Chyrurgions in Ordinary,</hi> that very Prince himſelf we were juſt now ſpeaking of, neither before nor at the time of his unhappy diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, did think it reaſonable to confide, or truſt his Life in the hands of ſuch his ſpurious <hi>Regii Profeſſores.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After my endeavours to prove this Upſtart as dangerous a Perſon as the People can converſe with, I ſhall lay down ſuch a faithful account of his Practice, as will, I doubt not, render his Name ſo ignominous and deteſtable in the Peoples Ears, that in conſideration of thoſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35377:26"/> many Outrages he commits on their Bodies, they may as well venture their Perſons amongſt ravenous Beaſts, as truſt their Health, Limbs, and Lives to the management of ſuch <hi>Intruders</hi> on the Phyſician's and Chyrurgeon's Duty.</p>
               <p>I have already acquainted you with his Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which if not poſitively the ſame, I have intimated, yet circumſtantially you will find it correſpond.</p>
               <p>I am ſatisfy'd it was never known of any <hi>Empirick,</hi> that he acquir'd the Skill he boaſts of by a diligent Service under a legal or rightly-qualify'd <hi>Chyrurgeon,</hi> or commenc'd gradually <hi>Phyſick-profeſſor</hi> at a Univerſity, but all from ſuch ſiniſter clandeſtine methods, as renders their Pretenſions as unjuſt as their Practice deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive.</p>
               <p>It's but a few months from the writing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that a late <hi>Mountebank</hi> or <hi>Stage-player</hi> in <hi>M—F—</hi>was conſulted by a Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man then labouring under the ſevere Symptoms of an ulcerated Cancer, ſeated on her Breaſt. She had been tampering ſome time before with a noted Doctoreſs about <hi>C—,</hi> famous for ſuch Cures, who labour'd all ſhe could to put it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuppurating (for you muſt know ſhe had been concern'd before it ulcerated) ſhe took much pains to perſwade the Patient there was no other way for cure, but (as ſhe expreſs'd it) by letting out that corrupt Humour which was continually gnawing of her, and fed her Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:35377:27"/>
               <p> She ſaid ſhe had cur'd ſeveral by this new way, which the ableſt Chyrurgeons durſt not meddle with: hereupon, by the inceſſant ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of hot Topicks, and powerfully at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive (to uſe the ancient expreſſion) Pultiſſes, ſhe in a little time accompliſh'd her deſire, but<hi>—Quis talia fando,</hi> with ſo evil a tendency of all things for the worſe, that from this (as was to be expected) the before occult and quiet Cancer now manifeſted its rage and cruel fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs more than ever; there was ſoon after the diſcharge a pertinacious <hi>Fungus</hi> thruſt forth in ſeveral parts of the Abſceſs, and the virulent Humour by eroſion, having open'd the mouths of the Veſſels, finding a clear paſſage, gave a free egreſs to the vital Spirits with the Blood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any the leaſt provocation.</p>
               <p>By this the Patient was debilitated, and her Spirits much exhauſted, ſo that of neceſſity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compel'd to diſmiſs her Female Undertaker, and to add more Fuel to her inextinguiſhable Flame, upon the rumor of a noted <hi>Empiric</hi> (one of the before-mention'd) ſhe refers her caſe to him, who finding the Breaſt movable <hi>(ſure he thought it ſhould not long continue ſo)</hi> moſt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly orders a Bottle of ſtrong Spirits, for to bath the part affected, and half a dozen Papers of purging Pouder, to be taken every other day, which when ſhe had roundly paid for, ſhe took home with her to her Houſe near <hi>M—.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:35377:27"/>
               <p> Upon the very firſt application, the moſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſive Particles of the ſubtile Spirit, fermenting with the bilious aduſt Humour, lodged in the Glandules of the Breaſt, ſoon haſten'd an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation, by an encreaſe of fluxion; which when by circulation the morbid taint was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to the reſt of the bloody maſs, there was preſently excited ſo great an efferveſcence, and ſuch a continued Feaveriſh Ebullition, that notwithſtanding the too late aſſiſtance of an eminent Chyrurgeon, the vital Flame was ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly extinguiſh'd, and this miſerable Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man untimely hurried to her Grave.</p>
               <p>I think we ſhall have no occaſion to produce a more evident demonſtration of <hi>Empirical Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> than this of the foregoing, where we find the application of a burning Spirit to an inflam'd ulcerated Cancer, which was as likely to effect a Cure, as 'tis that the Fire ſhould be put out by a combuſtible Sulphur.</p>
               <p>I was the rather free to inſert this Paſſage, for that being an eye-witneſs, and enquiring what had been done, they ſhew'd me the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebank's Bottle of Spirits, which (as I could imagine) were no other than an inflamable <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Turpentine,</hi> impregnated with <hi>Galbanum, Ammoniacum,</hi> and other <hi>Gumms;</hi> and his Pouder that of <hi>Jalap Root;</hi> a very likely thing to prove beneficial, where the moſt lenitive Purgation oftentimes puts the Humours into an over-eager ferment, to the diſturbance of the part.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:35377:28"/>
               <p> A Caſe likely to have been as fatal as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, you may underſtand by this, that when (a little while ſince) a Chyrurgeon had been ſent for to take a view of a weakly Child, he found one of our preſent Mountebanks there before him, who had already made a demand for his intended Cure, and was preparing for his Work: He told the Practitioner, that the Child had ſo large a <hi>Carnoſity,</hi> or fleſhy Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, by the Fundament, that it hinder'd him from going to Stool; but he did not queſtion he ſhould ſoon cure him, by cutting of it away: The Chyrurgeon being curious to ſee it, deſir'd a view of this ſtrange caſe, which being gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he found nothing more than a bearing down of the Fundament, or Prolaps of the Inteſtine, by cutting off which (if not providentially pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented) this bold Undertaker had moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly kill'd the Child.</p>
               <p>Did not the fear of being burthenſome to your Patience take me off from ſuch a deſign, I could relate ſome ſcores of my own obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on theſe mens Practiſes, where the Succeſs hath been much at one with the former, more eſpecially in their Pretenſions to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of Chyrurgick Operations, ſuch as couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Cataracts,</hi> extirpation of <hi>Wenns,</hi> and other preternatural Excreſcences; their cutting Men for the <hi>Stone,</hi> and extracting the ſame from the Female Sex <hi>per dilatationem,</hi> where their prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly expanding and lacerating the <hi>Urinary Ductus,</hi> if no worſe Symptom intervene, yet
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35377:28"/> by this violent uſage they ſo far weaken the Muſcular Fibres, that the Patient from thence labours of a <hi>Paralyſis</hi> in that part, and is atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with an involuntary Miction all her Life after.</p>
               <p>Surely if ſuch abſurd Practices and daily Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages as theſe, are not ſufficiently conducing nor enough prevalent, there can be nothing more coercive to rectifie Mens Judgments, or to caution them from their application to a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Mountebank,</hi> who not only acts out of the reach of his capacity, by ſurreptitiouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenching upon Medicine and its Profeſſors, but alſo (which is of much worſe conſequence) by ſo doing he too frequently brings the overcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous into danger of their Lives.</p>
               <p>It was no raſh Opinion of him who deliver'd his Thoughts to this effect; That if Juſtice had taken place, a great number of theſe <hi>Vagabonds</hi> had long ſince ſuffer'd by the hands of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Executioner, as juſt <hi>Memento's</hi> to forewarn others how they tempt their Stars beyond their Light. And the Compariſon made by another is as little diſagreeable, That there is no farther diſproportion between the <hi>Mountebank</hi> and <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering Robber</hi> than this, that the former, by a pretence of Service, having bereav'd the unwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Paſſenger of both Mony and Life, paſſeth undiſcover'd; whilſt the latter, to accompliſh the ſame ends, more certainly ſuffers condign Puniſhment, on the account of open Violence. There is alſo this diſparity between the Caſes of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35377:29"/> ſuch who fall into the hands of either, that the one ignorantly as it were conſents (tho' upon a different expectation) to be depriv'd of his Life, whilſt the other is compel'd to reſign the ſame, when overpower'd by his Adverſary. In ſhort, they are both ſacrific'd to the Intereſts of baſe Men, and if either be the more eligible, 'tis he who gives us time enough to fly from him, or defend our Lives.</p>
               <p>That I may take off what may ſeem to ſome a too rigid Cenſure on the Failings of theſe men, I ſhall give you the concurring Teſtimony of one of <hi>Galen</hi>'s Commentators.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſoever</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doth take upon him to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter in the Medicinal Profeſſion, for the ſafety of Man's Life, and being ignorant in the Principles thereof, he adminiſtring therein, and the Man periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Hands, or under his adminiſtration; I ſay that this is Murther, and the practiſing Pretender anſwerable for the ſame, as well to humane as divine Juſtice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truly 'tis great pity that ſuch Treſpaſſes as theſe come not under the Verdict of a skilful and inquiſitive Jury, that the <hi>Treachery</hi> being hereby detected, the <hi>Tragick Actor</hi> might receive his <hi>Praemium.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:35377:29"/>
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>AS a farther occaſion that thoſe honourable Profeſſions of <hi>Phyſick</hi> and <hi>Chyrurgery</hi> have been ſo meanly reputed, and ſo much under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued, I ſhall give you an account of the abuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Practices of other <hi>Quack Pretenders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Quack</hi> is by a certain facetious Author de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd as a kind of baſtardly Breed, engender'd by the Congres of a <hi>Mountebank</hi> and a <hi>City Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctreſs,</hi> from whence is ſaid to reſult this defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med lump of Impudence.</p>
               <p>He is by others ſaid to have been <hi>Jack of all Trades,</hi> yet could never live by any; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having well acquainted himſelf with the extravagant Humour of ſuch who can't diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh Truth from what is otherwiſe; without farther deliberation he preſently turns <hi>Doctor:</hi> but conſidering that his ſudden pretence to the cure of all Diſtempers would raiſe ſuſpicion of his being no more than a Pretender, he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (encourag'd by the predominant Vice of the Age) profeſſeth at firſt, that he is only Maſter of ſome pleaſant, private, and ſpeedy method for the cure of the <hi>Lues</hi> or <hi>French Pox,</hi> and according as this takes, if there be Mony in the caſe, there's nothing comes amiſs to him.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:35377:30"/>
               <p> Theſe <hi>Quack Practitioners</hi> were never ſo nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as they are at preſent, there being ſcarce a corner in either City or Suburbs, where one or other of theſe <hi>Intruders</hi> have not ſhamefully crept in.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, I can't ſuppoſe him full out ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous as the former, on account that his meaner and more private ſtation, doth not admit him (if otherwiſe willing) to make ſuch heavy ſlaughter among the People.</p>
               <p>There is alſo this farther inequality, That the former having ſummons'd a concourſe of People, is the cryer of his own Abilities, by thoſe fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Stories he delivers to them; whilſt this Perſon (for want of ſo much confidence) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents himſelf by employing ſome Hackney Scribe, who ſends abroad for him a <hi>Noverint Univerſi,</hi> or Advertiſement where to find the Habitation of ſuch an eminent Profeſſor both of Phyſick and Chyrurgery, as will undertake to cure them when left off by others.</p>
               <p>We are ſo peſter'd now of late with theſe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Libels, that you cannot walk from <hi>Temple-bar</hi> to <hi>Charing-croſs</hi> without being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd on to inſpect three or four of them. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the divertiſement they afford an ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reader, may in ſome meaſure requite him for his expence of time in the peruſal, it being certainly as pleaſant to ſuperviſe ſome ſuch as are eſpecially intermix'd with a few doggril Rhimes, as to be Spectator at a Farce. <hi>Riſum teneatis?</hi> may very well be queried, there being
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35377:30"/> ſuch of them diſpers'd about the Town, as would conſtrain a ſmile from the moſt mortify'd <hi>Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite</hi> or recluſeſt <hi>Hermit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is ſcarce a Corner-houſe in Town, or Entrance to a publick Thorowfare, where you may not find a <hi>Quack-pretender</hi>'s Bill.</p>
               <p>The one preſents you with his <hi>Aqua Tetrachy-magogon,</hi> a word as far above his Comprehenſion to etymologize, as the <hi>Zenith</hi> from the <hi>Nadir.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſecond offers a moſt ſpecious and grave Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Read, Try, Judge, and ſpeak as you find;</hi> which when they do, it is commonly utter'd with a ſhower of heavy Oaths and Execrations on the Author, for his trying Concluſions, and leading them on from an inconſiderable Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, <hi>(viz.</hi> a recent Venereal <hi>Gonorrhoea, Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, Bubo, &amp;c.)</hi> into the moſt lamentable, excru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciating, nocturnal Dolors, and often many more irrepairable Diſaſters.</p>
               <p>A third gives you to underſtand, that at ſuch a place lives <hi>the only, true, and approved Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician of Twenty odd years Experience:</hi> But to ſolve this <hi>Aenigma,</hi> we may make it out thus: The firſt ſeven years, perhaps, were ſerved in an Apprenticeſhip to ſome Country <hi>Apothecary,</hi> or practiſing <hi>Barber,</hi> where he had the liberty to ſee his Maſter oftentimes let Blood, and cut holes up and down the Body, which he calls his Iſſues. After the Foundation was thus laid, we may imagine that a ſecond ſeven (being youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful days) were ſpent in rambling foreign parts, where there might be as much Knowledge
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35377:31"/> gain'd in Phyſick or Chyrurgery as amounts to a Cypher. The laſt ſeven were not improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) ſpun out in working Journey-work, when coveting the Title of a <hi>pater familias,</hi> (he ſets up for himſelf, and ſpends the remainder of his days in diligently conning over his Grandmother's Receipt-book.</p>
               <p>Here he finds ſuch admirable Titles to all his ſeveral Medicines, that he can ſuppoſe he hath already purchas'd a greater Talent of Knowledg than his Brother who ſends out the <hi>Three Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Remedies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is firſt of all an incomparable Direction to make <hi>Lucatellus Balſam,</hi> which the good old Woman would never impart to any one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her death. In another place he finds a Receipt for <hi>Diachylon</hi> and <hi>Melilot Emplaſter,</hi> for the cure of Cuts, Bruiſes, Splinters, and ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. In a third place there is a never-failing Mercurial Water, ſubſcrib'd, <hi>This is that Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Water with which my Lady—cured Thouſands of poor people, and was bequeath'd as her Legacy to her Nurſe Mrs.—.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With this Solution of ſublimate Mercury in fair Water the Dr. dreſſeth all <hi>Tumors,</hi> I ſhould ſay <hi>Swellings, Wounds, Ulcers,</hi> and the ſeveral ſpecies of them, under any appellation whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. And amongſt the reſt, he hath found out a cheaper way (that he might be abſolutely compleat) than any as yet diſcover'd, to make <hi>Pil. Cochiae,</hi> with another famous Purger in all caſes, made of <hi>Aloes, Rhubarb, Coloquintida,</hi> and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35377:31"/> 
                  <hi>Jalap,</hi> brought into a <hi>maſs,</hi> (or in the old Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomans Phraſe a <hi>conſiſtence)</hi> with the Syrup of <hi>Buckthorn-berries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have here a proſpect of the <hi>Baſis</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is built the wounderful Skill of the Rabble's many years Practitioner, from whence it will be no hard matter to judge of his Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Phyſick and Chyrurgery. And now if (your Spring being drained) you are not obliged to withdraw, you may behold upon another piece <hi>Cure without Poyſon,</hi> and that in Capitals.</p>
               <p>This Gentleman ſpeaks as truly as the reſt, but only under the notion of <hi>No Poyſon</hi> he would poſſeſs the People with a Belief, that from the Legal Artiſt they muſt expect <hi>Poyſon</hi> in their <hi>Cures,</hi> when at the ſame time ſome of theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders ſhall not ſcruple to vend the worſt of Poyſons in their dangerous Compoſitions</p>
               <p>Indeed, if our ſweet ſublim'd Mercury muſt deſerve no other name than Poyſon (though one of the moſt noble Medicaments yet known) I dare be confident there never was any conſiderable Venereal Cure (pretend they what they pleaſe) effected ſecurely without its exhibition. And of the ſame opinion we ſhall find the moſt reputable Authors who have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upon its Uſe and Vertues: I think the ingenious <hi>Harvey,</hi> and the late Mr. <hi>Richard Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> have ſaid enough to evince the great truth of this Aſſertion. However, to clear farther the treacherous proceedings of one of theſe bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35377:32"/> inveighers againſt <hi>Mercury,</hi> I ſhall impart what was communicated to me from a perſon of good credit, who himſelf pretending an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for a Box of Pills, bought about two drams of a <hi>Quack,</hi> who had wonderfully decry'd the Uſe of a <hi>Mercurial</hi> Preparation in Phyſick, when by a Chymical <hi>Analyſis</hi> of the Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he found therein contain'd half a dram and fifteen grains of crude <hi>Mercury</hi> or <hi>Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After all, to bring up the Reer, another tickles you with the pleaſing invitation of <hi>No Cure No Money.</hi> This honeſt man may, not unlikely, tell you, That 'tis cuſtomary however for his Patients to give him a ſmall Fee of a Piece or two for encouragement, which he calls your <hi>Admittance;</hi> and when he thinks he hath done enough for this, he knows how to accoſt you, upon your next appearance, with a Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this nature.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Sir, or Madam,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Finding the dangerous ſtates of your Diſtemper to encreaſe upon you, and that altogether through your own neglect, in not conforming to my Directions, I am wholly taken off the thoughts of farther proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with you; nay, I am as well ſatisfied, by your inordinate living, and by the appearance of new Symptoms, that you have stray'd and got a freſh Miſchance, as if I my ſelf had been the perſon you have ſo lately been concern'd with: Now, you know, it was by no Covenant or Bargain of mine promis'd,</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:35377:32"/> 
                     <hi>that I would cure one Clap upon another, without being ſatisfied for the firſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Here you find there is no Remedy left (eſpecially if you would be genteel) but to throw down a couple of <hi>Guineas</hi> more before you are diſcharg'd, and then you have the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſeek out a ſecond <hi>Quack-ſalving Phyſician,</hi> in a much worſe plight than you came to the firſt.</p>
               <p>Whatever may be the Practice of particular Undertakers, who ſend abroad theſe Papers, I know it hath been a courſe taken with ſome, who have inſinuated to the Patient, they would have nothing till they perform'd their Cure; indeed, ſuch are uſually the Hypocritical Shams and Evaſions of ſelfiſh Ignorants, who are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enough to lay their own Miſcarriages up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Errors of their Patients, when it's poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the ſame time they were never otherwiſe guilty, than being overforward to ſwallow down their prepoſterous and improper <hi>Drenches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would therefore ſeriouſly adviſe the Unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Sons of <hi>Venus,</hi> who have been paid the Wages for their Works of Leachery, that they as ſafely hazard a freſh encounter with their darling <hi>Curtezans,</hi> in hopes (and with as much likelihood) to find an <hi>Antidote</hi> where they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd their <hi>Infection,</hi> as to rely for Relief upon the Counſel of a <hi>Quack Pretender;</hi> for by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of their amorous Delights, they can but propel the malign <hi>Seminaries</hi> a little farther
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35377:33"/> into the Body, and by the inconſiderate and raſh adhibition of theſe mens Medicines, the ſaid Infection is carried as far inwards, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mix'd with the (now thorowly polluted) maſs of Blood, produceth as dangerous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate effects.</p>
               <p>That which principally incites the People to make uſe of this <hi>Intruder,</hi> is, his retail vending of his Medicines; for being inform'd, that of ſuch a famous Phyſician they may have an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Box of Pills,</hi> of another an <hi>Incomparable Pleaſant Liquor,</hi> of a third a <hi>Never-failing Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, Lozenge,</hi> or <hi>Elixir,</hi> and all theſe undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſervative, as well as curative, in the <hi>Pox,</hi> with its Attendants: Being allur'd, I ſay, with ſo plauſible an Invitation, they ſcruple not to ſend their Mony by ſome truſty Friend, to purchaſe theſe Medicaments, wherewith (as they are told) they may cure themſelves, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hindrance of Buſineſs, or knowledge of Relations.</p>
               <p>Hereby accrews this great advantage to the <hi>Quack,</hi> that he's not oblig'd to credit; for were not the Mony paid upon the receipt of what he ſells them, there are few People (upon a too late repentance of their Bargain) would come to return their Thanks.</p>
               <p>It is the pleaſing hopes to keep their Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chances ſecret, with the promiſe that they meet with of ſo eaſie and cheap a Remedy to reſtore their Health, makes them look upon theſe Bills as ſo many <hi>Oracles,</hi> and what they deliver to be
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35377:33"/> purely <hi>orthodox;</hi> but alas, the Event renders them the greateſt Objects of our pity, who by ſplitting upon theſe Rocks of Diſſimulation, have ſhipwrack'd their Lives and Fortunes.</p>
               <p>I can do no leſs than admire that any Man ſhould be ſo inconſiderate, not to ſay ignorant, as to take for granted, that an Eighteen-penny Box of Pills, an Halfcrown Bottle of Tincture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould be of ſufficient energy to withſtand or profligate a radicated Pox, in all its ſeveral ſhapes and diverſity of appearance, when at the ſame time it is not often known that any the moſt recently contracted Virulency was ever throughly expel'd by theſe frequently miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous and prejudicial adminiſtrations.</p>
               <p>I have heard of a certain <hi>Quack</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> who (upon a bare Recommendation from as wiſe a perſon as himſelf) undertook, and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exhibited the Pouder of <hi>Cantharides,</hi> or <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Flyes,</hi> in order to carry off the Flux of a <hi>Gonorrhoea,</hi> but with ſo fatal a conſequence, that hereupon the miſerably afflicted Patient dy'd ſuddenly convulſive.</p>
               <p>We have an account of two Caſes of ſome affinity with the former, related by <hi>Meekrin,</hi> in his Chyrurgick Obſervations, which for the extraordinary circumſtances at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, I ſhall copy from the aforeſaid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, in page 141.</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:35377:34"/>
                  <p>Bartholomeus Cabrolius, <hi>Anatomicus Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpelienſis, Obſervationem ſingularem (huc facientem) adfert his verbis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AVenionem evocatus, ut quendam majori in femore Sclopeto ictum, curarem, una cum</hi> Joberto Guilimeo <hi>&amp; aliis; è diverticulo, ad Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem, enormi laborantem Satyriaſi viſendum ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſimus. Res ita habet, laborat quartana Aeger, in qua profliganda ſtrigae auxilium petierat, quae illi poculum ex ℥j. ſeminis urticarum, Canthari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>ij. ſeſqui drachma coeparum aliiſque concin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narat: hinc it a exarſit in venerem, ut Uxor ejus per omnia ſacra dejerarat, ſe ab binoctio octuagies ſepties initam, interea ſaepius in lectum ſemen effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſe: imo nobis adſtantibus, brevi momento ter ſe polluit, pedem lecti pro foemina ſubagitans: hinc in ſtuporem verſi, quidquid fieri potuit remediorum adhibuimus, ſed ipſe paulo poſt libitinariis pollincto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ceſſit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Huic affine, retulit Dominus</hi> Chauvet Avenio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis <hi>Doctor, aiebat ille, annis abhinc</hi> 32, <hi>Evo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum ſe Gaderouſam ad hominem eadem Satyriaſi correptum, &amp; limine domus obvia fit Uxor, de praepoſtera libidine (rarum in mulieribus querelae genus) mariti expoſtulans; quadragies illam una nocte hortum ſuum fodiſſe; ſimul laceratam nimla affrictu oſtendebat vulvam, remediumque <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>olori juxta ac colori quaerebat. Simili potione malum</hi>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:35377:34"/> 
                     <hi>Aeger contraxerat, quam praebuerat Mulier Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dochio ancillans tertianae arcendae, qua hic in tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam amentiam verſus fuerat, ut catenis obſeſſi inſtar ligandus erat. Aderat cum Domino</hi> Chaveto <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos, qui cum verbis ſolari Hominem vellet: rogabat uti ſe deliciis iſtis immori ſineret: Foeminae cum linteo oxycrato immerſo cinxere. Mane mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus, hiantiore membro<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> gangraena correpto, inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ridenti ſimilis eſt rictu quem Sardonium vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>I have the rather made this Digreſſion, that the World may ſee what intolerable Miſchiefs an unskilful Perſon may be guilty of, when countenanc'd the moſt illegally to practiſe in our Art.</p>
               <p>If it be reply'd, That many who have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Venereal Infection have been cur'd by <hi>Quack Practitioners;</hi> I muſt needs ſay, that I am ſo far diffident, as to queſtion their Security from the danger of Relapſe. I very well know they have obtain'd a Truce, or ſhort <hi>Requies,</hi> with their Diſtemper, in which Interval the <hi>Undertaker</hi> fues for ſatisfaction; but after ſome little time <hi>(remanente cauſa)</hi> there has been found to the Patient's ſorrow, a Pejoration of all Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, ſuch as from the patching up a Venereal <hi>Ulcer,</hi> the retroceding of a malign <hi>Bubo,</hi> by refrigerant and repelling <hi>Topicks,</hi> or the untimely ſtopping of a <hi>Gonorrhoea</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringent Injections, or otherwiſe, have imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptibly tranſmigrated into the moſt inveterate
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35377:35"/> 
                  <hi>Cephalalgia's,</hi> extream Laſſitudes, the moſt pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive nocturnal Dolors, with other univerſal excruciating Pains in all parts of the Body. Indeed from ſuch <hi>Ignorants</hi> you muſt expect no other, than to be carried from a ſimple ſlight Infection, and that moſt inevitably into the ſtrongeſt Contagion; when if you ſeek Redreſs of your Phyſician, you are told, That he hath already commanded the <hi>Pox</hi> out of your Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and theſe are no other than Symptoms of a predominant <hi>Scurvy,</hi> contracted by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe drinking of Wines and other ſtrong Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, with your liberal ſeeding upon Salt and Spiced Meats.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the Pretences of ſuch illiterate and Empirical Pretenders; ſcarce any one of which ever freed a Patient of any Venereal Concern, without the ſevere Relicks of a Pocky <hi>Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute,</hi> which when arriv'd at their Extream, are ſufficient to emaciate the moſt corpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Body, and unleſs reliev'd by Medicine, will unavoidably induce a lingring <hi>Chronick</hi> Sickneſs, oftentimes terminating in Death it ſelf.</p>
               <p>I hope now, from the already recited In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Remarks, there will need the fewer Arguments to diſſwade Venereal Patients from their application to a <hi>Quack,</hi> and in his room to introduce the true practical Chyrurgeon, where, upon diſcovery of their Misfortune, and an enquiry into the progreſs of their Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, they may with as much Secreſie, and far
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35377:35"/> greater Safety (from a rational and well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded method of Proceeding, without which the ſlighteſt Symptoms are no more than palliated) expect Recovery without the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture acceſs or danger of a Relapſe; for let Men boaſt never ſo much of their <hi>Specificks,</hi> or infallible <hi>Noſtrums,</hi> as an Eighteen-penny Box of <hi>Pills,</hi> a ſmall Vial of their <hi>Antivene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Elixir,</hi> with the reſt of their Empirick Remedies, they are all, I ſay, the fantaſtick Notions and Chymera's of ſelf-intereſted and deceitful Intruders on the Medicinal Art, who have invented theſe fabulous Stories to amuſe and fool the People, defraud them of their Mony; and run them not ſeldom into the hazard of their Lives.</p>
               <p>There is the leſs reaſon to exemplifie by more particular Remarks the Cheats by theſe Men practis'd to beguile the Unwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſince the ſame begin now to be ſo publick and notorious, that you ſhall ſcarce light into the company of a clapp'd <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur,</hi> who is not preſently reviling of his Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, and lamentably condoling his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, for raſhly confiding in the Judgment of a <hi>Quack Profeſſor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſincerely and heartily wiſh, that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed <hi>Gallican</hi> may be hereby warn'd, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I have diſcharg'd my Duty, with reſpect to the <hi>Praemonition;</hi> and if the Proffer of an
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35377:36"/> undoubted Salutary <hi>Antidote</hi> be oppos'd or wilfully rejected by an infected Patient, we have the leſs reaſon to be concern'd, when the Poyſon he hath receiv'd ſhall prove as fatal.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:35377:36"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>ANother great cauſe for the Scandal and Male-reflection upon <hi>Chyrurgery</hi> and its true Profeſſors, is, the baſe and burthenſom In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion made thereon by the Practiſe of a <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> who by his Title ſeems to cry Halfs with the <hi>Chyrurgeon,</hi> and bears as great a ſway in the good Opinion of ignorant People as the Legal Artiſt.</p>
               <p>Indeed the very Notion of a <hi>Barber-Surgeon</hi> ſeems in ſome meaſure to countenance the Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance of theſe men, and hath ſo far impos'd on ſuch as are unacquainted with the Truth, that they have never imagin'd the great difference between the <hi>Chyrurgeon</hi> and this bold <hi>Undertaker;</hi> neither will they be perſwaded that the latter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs a Penalty, by his aſſumed Confidence to intermeddle in the Duty of the former.</p>
               <p>Now have we not juſt reaſon to ſtand ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at the Preſumption of theſe men, who are ſo numerous in all the out-parts of the Town, that it's almoſt a Rarity to find one of their <hi>Poles</hi> without a Frame of Porringers, or ſome other Signal of their Pretenſions to Chyrurgick Practiſe: Nay, ſome of them have of late years preſum'd ſo far upon our negligence to ſuppreſs
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35377:37"/> them, as to hang out for their Sign the <hi>Arms</hi> of our Profeſſion; ſo that, as far as I perceive, it may in time be no eaſie matter to know the rightly qualified Profeſſor of our Art, from the perſon of whom we are now giving you a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription.</p>
               <p>However, that I may render my deſign the more compleat, and ſhew my willingneſs to rectifie thoſe mens Judgments who have been hitherto miſguided, I ſhall give you a true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Original, that you may ſee with how great Injuſtice he takes upon him to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in our Art.</p>
               <p>If we look back on his Deſcent, we ſhall find his Riſe from ſome honeſt contented <hi>Barber,</hi> with whom having liv'd a little time in perfect abhorrence of ſo ſtrict a confinement, he waits for an opportunity and ſteals off to Sea, where he paſſes indifferently for a Barber's Boy, till his Maſter dying; after a firſt or ſecond Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, he ſteps into his Place; and now being acquainted with the cuſtom of the Seas, on his next ſetting out he is, after ſome ſlight <hi>Examen,</hi> introduc'd as the <hi>Surgeon's Mate;</hi> in which ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion having purchas'd much Experience, and tir'd with rambling, full fraught with Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, he comes on ſhore, where ſetling in ſome obſcure part of the Town, he goes by the name of an able <hi>Barber</hi> or <hi>Sea-Chyrurgeon,</hi> and acquaints the People with ſuch wonderful Stories of his extraordinary Atchievements in our Art, that they are ready to repute him for as worthy a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35377:37"/> Practitioner as either <hi>Galen</hi> or <hi>Hippocrates</hi> were in former times. You may be ſure to find him talking (where he fears not to betray his Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) of nothing leſs than <hi>Fractures, Diſlocations, Gangreens, Mortifications,</hi> and <hi>Amputations,</hi> with other ſcraps which he hath pick'd from ſome ancient Author, and launching out into a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liberty of romancing, is continually boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how many ſcores of Limbs he hath taken off, on which his ignorant Auditory ſhall ground a ſuppoſition, that without a ſufficient know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the Practice of the Seas, it muſt be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for the Land Profeſſor to be truly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd, or well qualify'd for adminiſtration in the Medicinal Art.</p>
               <p>To remove this Scandal, I muſt ingeniouſly confeſs, that were I to deliver my own Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I ſee very little reaſon to make diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in point of Knowledge between the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Sea Profeſſor</hi> and the Town <hi>pretending Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> I know they are not ſeldom a Reſult one from 'tother; and I ſhall farther remark for our advantage, that in conſideration of the moſt ſlovenly and uncouth Practice, together with the abſurd (that I may not ſay ignorant) Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings too commonly attending a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of theſe <hi>Sea Practitioners,</hi> I am ſenſible there will be found as great difference between ſuch a perſon and the City Chyrurgeon, as betwixt a deceitful <hi>Artleſs Pretender</hi> and a Maſter in the ſaid Art.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:35377:38"/>
               <p> I would not be thought herein by any means to reflect on thoſe legal and ingenious <hi>Practitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> employ'd in His Majeſty's Naval Service, but what I have ſpoken hereto, is on account of the great Abuſes committed by thoſe ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Intruders on the Practiſe, who by making Friends to the Superviſers, have clandeſtinely procur'd the Title of <hi>Chyrurgeons Mates,</hi> to the no ſmall detriment and perſonal damage of the King's good Subjects, whoſe Health and Lives, in the <hi>Chyrurgeon</hi>'s abſence, are in the hands of theſe ſo lately <hi>Barbers</hi> and Apothecaries Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</p>
               <p>'Tis not many years ſince a meer <hi>Novice</hi> in Surgery, humbly requeſting a Grant for the Office of a <hi>Mate,</hi> upon a tryal if he was fitted for the diſcharge of ſuch a Truſt, when he was ask'd, what he thought was the firſt intention in the treating of a penetrating Puncture on the <hi>Thorax,</hi> he reply'd, He had never ſeen ſuch a thing in his life. Being farther queſtion'd, if he knew where the ſaid part, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Thorax,</hi> was ſituate in a Humane Body, he as ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pointed to the Hypogaſtrick Region of the <hi>Abdomen,</hi> and might (according to his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) as well have ſhewn the Palm of his Hand: yet this Perſon, as I am credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, quickly after obtain'd his deſire, and got off to Sea.</p>
               <p>The ſmall converſe I have had with theſe men, and the inſpection I have made into their Buſineſs, hath afforded me many opportunities
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35377:38"/> of beholding as indifferent Practice as might be expected from a tampering <hi>Old Woman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A certain noted <hi>Sea Practitioner</hi> had ſome time ſince a Patient here on Shore, who was afflicted with a malign <hi>Paronichia</hi> on his Finger, which he treated ſo long with Suppuratives that the Ligaments were corrupt, and the Bone ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; at length there happening a ſpontane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſcharge of <hi>Pus,</hi> the ſinuoſity was dilated, and the Bone denudated for ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oliation. Now to recover his former negligence, in ſuffering the malignity to lye ſo long conceal'd, he as prejudicially dreſt the Patient with <hi>Baſilicon</hi> and <hi>Oyl of Hypericon,</hi> laid immediately on the Bone, whereby the Putrefaction and <hi>Caries</hi> encreas'd, a large <hi>Fungus</hi> thruſt out, and after all there was a neceſſity for an <hi>Amputation,</hi> which was ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily perform'd.</p>
               <p>I could recite many other inſtances where the Succeſs hath been much the ſame, with the foregoing, but whoſoever will take the pains to look over the Obſervations of Mr. <hi>Richard Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> will, I doubt not, be confirm'd in my Opinion, with reference to the common <hi>Sea Profeſſor,</hi> and his Brother the <hi>Barber-Chyrurgion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is another ſort of the laſt mention'd preſuming Undertakers, by whoſe Abuſes the Chyrurgick Profeſſion hath ſuffer'd a diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her <hi>quondam</hi> Credit and Repute: He is one who not daring to run the hazard of the Seas for his Experience, and finding that the Trimming Trade does not anſwer expectation,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35377:39"/> enters himſelf as a <hi>Cubb</hi> under an <hi>Hoſpital Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor,</hi> or thruſts himſelf into the acquaintance of a Chyrurgeon's Servant, who in his minori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is perhaps induced, by the gratuity of a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to ſuffer this <hi>Intruder</hi> to take a Proſpect of his Maſter's Practiſe, and to give him an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of phlebotomizing Poor People.</p>
               <p>This is too commonly the Foundation of a Barber's Knowledge, who after ſome few ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous tryals couragiouſly turns <hi>Adventurer,</hi> and punctures all who come unto him.</p>
               <p>I believe it will not be altogether foreign to our preſent task, if I ſpend ſome little time in making a diſcovery of their pernicious Practice in their pretence to that part of Chyrurgery which we term <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> or <hi>Venaeſection,</hi> ſo mightily now-adays in requeſt, that there is rarely an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition which ſeems not in the Peoples opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to indicate a neceſſity of emptying the Store-houſe of the Vital Spirits, by the drawing forth of Blood.</p>
               <p>This frequent Cuſtom were the leſs to be condemn'd, did not the Patient ſo raſhly truſt the performance hereof to the management of a <hi>Barber,</hi> who is generally unknowing in the many times prejudicial conſequences attending this Operation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>It will be impoſſible</hi> (ſaith the famous Dr. <hi>Willis) to preſcribe general Rules according to the particular caſes of every individual perſon, whereby the quantity in letting of Blood may be</hi>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:35377:39"/> 
                     <hi>exactly proportion'd according to the Diſeaſe or the ſtrength of the Patient; but let this be left to the Judgment of the prudent Phyſician, let his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands be ever exactly obſerv'd; and let not, as it every where is, ſuch leave be given to Quacks, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piricks, and Barbers, to play with Humane Life, who every where raſhly and wickedly uſe</hi> Phlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy; <hi>and if the Blood ſpring more freely, and appear diſcolour'd, therefore bragging of the Veſſel's being well pierced, they ſay it muſt be let out more plentifully, becauſe it appears bad, when oftentimes on the contrary it ought to be ſpar'd.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would not be thought ſo much affected with the Chymiſt's Principles, as abſolutely to condemn <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> for ſuch a Remedy as will prove at all times of worſe conſequence than the Diſeaſe; neither can I cordially promote the too frequently unneceſſary adminiſtration thereof; and therefore, as I am well ſatisfied that it is beyond diſpute preſervative in many affects, after other Preparatives, as in an <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexy, Lethargy, Carus, Megrim, Mania,</hi> on the occaſion of Inflammations, as in the ſeveral ſpecies of an <hi>Angina</hi> or <hi>Quinſey, Peripneumony, Pleuriſie,</hi> with other Feaveriſh Ebullitions of the Blood; ſo I would not adviſe ſuch as are about to undergo its extraction to conſide in the mean Judgment of a Barber; but rather let them take Counſel of the worthy and able Phyſician, and if he approve thereof, let them rely on the performance of an expert Chyrurgeon; for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35377:40"/> did not the ill ſucceſs attending them in their puncturing of <hi>Tendons,</hi> and Arteries for Veins, with other almoſt as prejudicial, their intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtive and ſuperfluous Venaeſections: Did not this, I ſay, give us a demonſtration of their Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, yet notwithſtanding there may be thoſe among them, who know indifferently to penetrate thoſe azure meandrous <hi>Channels</hi> of the <hi>Microcoſm,</hi> yet are they little knowing the damage or diſadvantages enſuing thereon. This was the ill fortune of a young Gentlewoman at St. <hi>J—,</hi> who being already enclining to a <hi>Chachexy,</hi> at the inſtant of labouring under a periodical Evacuation of the <hi>Menſes,</hi> was ſeized (as is uſual to ſome at thoſe times) with a great Pain in her Head, Back, and Hypochondria. Her impatience till the Uterine <hi>Ferment</hi> ſhould have ſecreted thoſe monthly Superfluities, put her upon asking Advice of a Phyſician, who order<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d forthwith, that ſhe ſhould be blooded in the Foot; and for this purpoſe there was ſent for a noted Barber near at hand, who not daring to venture on the <hi>Saphena,</hi> or any of its Branches, notwithſtanding ſhe had inform'd him on what account it was ſo order'd: He confidently told her, it would be equally beneficial if ſhe were blooded in the Arm; and thereupon overper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading the unhappy Maiden, he drew from her to the quantity of 12 ounces of Blood, but with ſo miſchievous a conſequence, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon there follow'd a total ſuppreſſion of the Flux, and the noxious Particles which were
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35377:40"/> them critically to have been diſcharg'd by the Womb, regurgitating into the maſs of Blood, brought on ſeveral <hi>hyſterick Paroxyſms,</hi> with <hi>Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope</hi>'s and continued faintings; from which (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt wearied of her Life) ſhe was in three weeks time reſcued by the Preſcriptions of the Phyſician ſhe had before conſulted.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee the Practice of ſuch a one, who right or wrong, rather than hazard the loſs of his Fee, will perpetrate the greateſt Wickedneſs, and ſeldom fail of bringing thoſe who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd with him into jeopardy of their Lives.</p>
               <p>I remember, ſome years ſince, I breathed a Vein for a poor Woman juſt then come from a Barber in <hi>S—,</hi> who had been attempting it in the following manner.</p>
               <p>The Woman was very corpulent, her Limbs of the largeſt ſize, and withal ſo very fat, that her Veins were neither viſible, nor indeed (by what I perceiv'd) at all perceptible to the Touch in her right Arm, where he had been trying; and telling her it was never cuſtomary to bleed in the left, he was the more eager to make a tryal of his Skill; whereupon once more laying his Fingers on her Arm, and finding no other part that was ſo tenſe, and perhaps to his apprehenſion turgid, as the Tendon of the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps,</hi> after ſome little pauſe, gave his opinion, That this was certainly the Vein, but it lay ſo very deep, as made him fearful he ſhould not pierce it. The Woman being herewith diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, was about to leave him; and he, unwilling
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35377:41"/> that another ſhould go away with the Prize, overperſwades her, with ſome difficulty, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a tryal of his Abilities: Upon this he bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plunges in his Weapon, and had not a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Providence interven'd, had undoubtedly made ſuch a breach in the <hi>Tendon</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Muſcle,</hi> as had been moſt certainly paſt his Skill (not improbably that of any other) to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair'd, without hazarding the loſs of her Limb, if not her Life.</p>
               <p>Surely the moſt ignorant perſon could not have been guilty of greater Simplicity, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Office of a Chyrurgeon, than this arrogant Intruder on the foreſaid Duty, who with the reſt of his Brethren <hi>Quacks, Empiricks, &amp;c.</hi> ought no farther to be truſted with a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, than a <hi>Lunatick</hi> with any Weapon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may either miſchief himſelf or others.</p>
               <p>I do imagine, that this Woman's fortunate deliverance was effected by her own fearfulneſs, ſhe (not unlikely) withdrawing, or ſome how altering the poſition of her Arm, in the time of his inciſion, whereby the foreſaid Tendon ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping from him, moſt happily miſſed the Point of his <hi>Piercer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed, ſuch-like commiſſions, or the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſo odious and abominable actions, muſt not altogether be imputed to the free choice or delight of the People, who are daily injur'd thereby, becauſe not knowing the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a wounded Tendon, neither what a Tendon is, or the difference between an Artery
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35377:41"/> and a Vein, they are eaſily induc'd to make uſe of the next Barber they come to, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſo long as he can any ways fetch the Blood out of their Bodies, that he alſo eaſe them of the weight of their Purſes. But I think we have juſt reaſon ſeverely to reprehend and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Preſumption of ſuch men as are ſo wonderful ambitious to be reputed for Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, when they neither are ſo, nor ought to practiſe in that worthy Art; and who, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they know themſelves to be <hi>Intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> that the beſt of them is incapacitated to perform the part of an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> will nevertheleſs dare to intermeddle for the hope of Gain, making their Shops ſo many Slaughter-houſes, and deteſtably expoſing Humane Blood on their Windows and Benches, to invite the unwary Paſſenger to partake of their bloody Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets.</p>
               <p>It is not often known, that the loſs of Blood is not advis'd in almoſt every Diſtemper of the Body by theſe Men, out of the ſordid deſire of Gain <hi>per fas nefaſque.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This truly, with his undertaking to make an Iſſue, are the chief and main points of Surgery that this pretending Barber could ever arrive at; not but that there are ſome of them too forward to encounter with more difficult caſes.</p>
               <p>Having however ſhewn you his dexterity in <hi>Venaeſection,</hi> or opening a Vein, I will here take the opportunity of diverting you with a ſhort view of his Performance in cutting of an Iſſue,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35377:42"/> which is likewiſe a Practice ſo frequently now<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adays in uſe, that rarely Man, Woman, or Child, nay, Infants themſelves, but what (as the 'fore mention'd Doctor ſaith) muſt have their Skins prick'd full of Iſlet-holes: and did not the advantageous event attending this Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſufficiently countenance the continuance thereof, we might have grounds to cenſure what is amongſt all at preſent in ſo great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
               <p>I would be underſtood, that a <hi>Fontanel</hi> or <hi>Iſſue</hi> made upon good advice, by the hand of a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Artiſt, is a very preſervative, and oftentimes curative, Remedy in a multitude of Infirmities that are wont to infeſt us; otherwiſe I have and do daily find, that they are moſt commonly painful, perverſe, and attended with many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies as well as Prejudice to the Health. Such generally are thoſe which are attempted by a Barber, who not knowing how or in what part they are moſt commodiouſly inſtituted, thinks it ſufficient that he can make a <hi>Solution</hi> of <hi>Continuity,</hi> or a hole in the Skin which will hold a Pea, not heeding the appropinquating Reſult, which is very commonly the ſending for a Surgeon, to afford the Patient a little eaſe in the extremity of his pain, ariſing from the inartificial making this little Ulcer upon the body of ſome Muſcular part, where it would have been continued with the moſt intolerable vexation, and no ſmall danger to the welfare of the Limb.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:35377:42"/>
               <p> Thus I have known ſome Pounds deſervedly beſtow'd on an eminent Chyrurgeon, for his trouble in reſiſting the ſevere Accidents of an Iſſue, which hath been a product of the Proceedings of this bold Undertaker.</p>
               <p>Both Reaſon and Experience dictate, that if an Iſſue be not made as near as it is poſſible in the Interſtice of the Muſcles, or the ſpace between two fleſhy parts, it is generally kept open with ſo great trouble and perplexity to the Patient, that the inconſiderable benefit of its diſcharge is in no meaſure equivalent to the great Miſchief and Miſery that accrews there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from.</p>
               <p>Now the People, as I hinted before, not knowing this diſtinction between Art and its Oppoſite, or the legal Chyrurgeon and the Perſon we are ſpeaking of, are as ready to comply with the one as 'tother, to be blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or to have an Iſſue made, not minding the ſometimes-fatal Prejudice by the hazard of the former, and as little imagining that there is any peculiar diſtinct part of the Body, whereof theſe men are ignorant as themſelves, and wherein only the Operation is to be perform'd.</p>
               <p>The ridiculous Practice of this nature, which I have ſeen ſuch as have aſſum'd the Title of Chyrurgeons guilty of, would make one really ſtand amaz'd at their profound Ignorance, and admire by what means they keep up their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute and Credit with ſuch as are more ſtupid than themſelves, and will not take warning by
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35377:43"/> the Fate of others, till a Self-tryal, conjoyn'd with a too late Experience and Repentance, make them ſenſible of their Error.</p>
               <p>It is truly a difficult matter to find one Iſſue in One and twenty in a convenient or proper place, or that can be long continued without manifeſt detriment to the Safety of ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as hath employ'd therein a <hi>Barber,</hi> or a <hi>Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticoat Practitioner.</hi> Some I have ſeen come from them with an Iſſue made on the body of the <hi>Bicep</hi>'s Muſcle in the Arm; others on the <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chialis Externus;</hi> ſome on the outſide of the <hi>Deltoides;</hi> and one that I was advis'd about, with the moſt intolerable pain threatning a <hi>Gangreen,</hi> made not a Finger's breadth from the <hi>Tendon</hi> of the <hi>Biceps,</hi> in the bent of the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit.</hi> In the Thigh I have found them directly on the muſculous part of the <hi>Vaſtus Internus,</hi> others on the ſame in the <hi>Rectus.</hi> In the Leg they have been made on the middle of the <hi>Gaſtroecnemius,</hi> where every extenſion thereof, beſides other Accidents, was ſubject to throw out the Pea.</p>
               <p>There is, I am certain, no occaſion to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large farther hereon, ſince the Truth is ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to every judicious perſon, that I dare aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure my ſelf there are not many of the ſame Profeſſion, who have not made ſuch-like Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks in the Variety of their Chyrurgick Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences; ſo that in theſe two Particulars, and indeed in the general practice of Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:35377:43"/> we have abundant cauſe to account this Perſon an unallowable Undertaker, conſidering that ſome of the moſt noted amongſt them have all-along, and do ſtill diſcover to us as much ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance as is taken notice of in any other the moſt inſufferable Intruder.</p>
               <p>What groſs and moſt ridiculous Actions do we find committed in the Examples of ſuch bold Encroachers on our Art, which are deliver'd to us by a multitude of worthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, particularly in the Obſervations of Mr. <hi>Wiſeman,</hi> who hath in ſeveral places given us very neceſſary hints of the extream injury the People receive from the toleration of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> in the Practice of <hi>Chyrurgery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall here tranſcribe one more remarkable than ſome others, from his Obſervations upon Wounds of the Head, where he tells us, that</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>A young fellow, who was Servant to a Horſe-courſer, was thrown off his Horſe againſt ſome of the Barrs in</hi> Smithfield, <hi>whereby the</hi> Calvaria <hi>or hairy Scalp was torn up from the Coronal Suture to the Temporal Muſcle on the left ſide; the Skull was bared about two or three inches in breadth: He was led to the next Barber, who cut the piece off, and hanged it up in his Shop. The day after the Patient was brought to me; I caus'd the Hair to be ſhav'd off from about the Wound, and dreſs'd the Bone and Lips with</hi> Linimentum Arcei <hi>warm, and embrocated the parts about</hi> cum Ol. Roſarum <hi>and</hi> Chamomeli, <hi>and apply'd</hi> Emplaſtrum Ebolo
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:35377:44"/> 
                  <hi>over the Wound, with</hi> Compres <hi>and</hi> Bandage <hi>rowling up his Head. He had been let Blood the the day before, without conſideration of the great quantity he had loſt from his Wound: I continued the former way of dreſſing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it was cured as Wounds with loſs of ſubſtance, a troubleſome and vexatious work to the Patient and Chyrurgeon, which might at firſt have been cured by Agglutination, with a leſs Cicatrix, and thereby he might have enjoy'd the natural tegument of his Hair, whereas that part remained bald and unſeemly.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Were it abſolutely requiſite for a fuller ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, I could from my own Remarks on theſe mens Practice, acquaint you with divers caſes tending to evince the weakneſs of their Judgments. 'Tis but a very little while from the writing hereof, that one of them happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to puncture a Tendon in the Foot of a Maid-ſervant, would have ſolv'd the buſineſs by upbraiding the Artiſt, who was afterwards em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd, for that he, by his improper applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, had haſten'd thoſe dangerous and important Symptoms.</p>
               <p>I remember Mr. <hi>Young</hi> of <hi>Plimouth</hi> gives us an account of a buſineſs of the like nature, though more troubleſome, occaſion'd from ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's puncturing of the <hi>Bicep's Tendon</hi> in the Arm of a Woman, an Inhabitant thereabouts. This fellow (having no better Subterfuge) went about to juſtifie his Proceeding, ſtrenuouſly affirming and aſſuring the Patient, that theſe Accidents
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:35377:44"/> were no other than uſual Symptoms frequently attending a diſorder'd Body, abounding with evil Humours.</p>
               <p>If the Reader think it worth his while to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe the ſaid Author's Treatiſe of <hi>Ol. Terebinth.</hi> he may be farther inform'd with how great trouble, the pertinacious Symptoms of this Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture were overcome, and at length an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent uſe of the Arm reſtor'd.</p>
               <p>Surely if theſe Events were no more than uſual Conſequences of <hi>Venaeſection,</hi> (as the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender intimates) I am apt to think we ſhould not find ſuch great numbers of People thus willing to be blooded on every ſlight occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>I may truly ſay, it is the much to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſufferance or toleration of ſuch Knaveries hath been one great cauſe that we meet with ſo many obſtinate and oftentimes incurable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers. Indeed, the firſt <hi>Surgeon</hi> ſought for amongſt the meaner ſort of People, when an Accident befals them, is commonly no other than a <hi>Barber,</hi> who when he hath ſhown his Skill by the moſt contrary adminiſtrations, and marr'd inſtead of mended the buſineſs, they are then at liberty to refer themſelves to the true practical Chyrurgeon, whoſe demands of a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Gratuity for his officious care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in performing the Cure, is not ſeldom requited with the opprobrious Language of <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable;</hi> becauſe, forſooth, that ſuch a <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> (who to gain Experience at the coſt of their
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:35377:45"/> Lives, will run a mile or two to purchaſe Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's Hire) would have dreſs'd them ſo long for little or nothing.</p>
               <p>What great pity is it, that the Sons of Art ſhould be vilified and diſeſteem'd for their not complying with the baſe and ſordid Principles of ſuch men, who have already ſo far diſgrac'd and undervalued this moſt noble Art, that in time it may (not unlikely) be forced to ſtand in competition with the meaneſt and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible mechanick Occupation.</p>
               <p>Were not the Art it ſelf as far above the reach of his Capacity, as it is from being a legal appertenance to his Calling, we could expect no other, but that it would be held the meaneſt and moſt deſpicable of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, not only for the multitude of ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders thereunto, but alſo for that the ſucceſleſs Events of their Chyrurgick Undertakings, are by too many, undeſervedly imputed to ſome Knavery in the Art it ſelf; they hence infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that the Profeſſion, at beſt, is no more than Pretence or Contrivance to delude the People, and deceive them of their Mony: And indeed, how can we expect leſs, than that the beſt of Arts ſhould partake of ſuch a diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Fate, when ſo great a liberty is allow'd the moſt Ignominious to practiſe without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation.</p>
               <p>When we conſider the great and moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexing difficulties that we are oftentimes obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to encounter, the many intricate and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35377:45"/> Undertakings that we meet with, where the Lives of our fellow-Chriſtians lye at ſtake; did we ſeriouſly and impartially reflect on this, we ſhould imagine it to be no ſuch eaſie Task for the moſt diligent in our Art to attain Perfection; much leſs might we expect an Artificial Performance from any Ignorant <hi>Profeſſor.</hi> Did we farther conſider all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances attending ſome People's Complaints againſt us, I as little queſtion but we ſhould find Chyrurgeons are not the men ſome ignorant and malicious Spirits have endeavour'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent them. How raſh a Cenſure is that of their being <hi>unconcionable</hi> (one of the great Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections) becauſe they endeavour to ſet a ſmall value on that moſt noble Art, which can never be too highly eſteem'd.</p>
               <p>Is it not Ingratitude, that the worthy <hi>Artiſt</hi> ſhould be requited with Revilings for his care in the performance of a Cure, the reaſonably demanded Recompence for which is thought a Crime, becauſe it hath already coſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſo much Mony under the hands of ſeveral falſe Practitioners? If ſuch a ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t'ling <hi>Doctreſs</hi> hath filch'd ſo much, ſuch a <hi>Practiſing Barber</hi> as much more, and ſuch a <hi>pretending Boneſetter</hi> as much as both, yet ſtill the Patient is left in a condition much worſe than before; is it not unjuſt, that the Chyrurgeon, who is laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, when he hath diligently recover'd and reſtor'd them to their Health, ſhould be ſo mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly look'd on, or ſo evilly rewarded?</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:35377:46"/>
               <p> I remember where a late <hi>Upſtart Pretender</hi> was entertain'd by a Gentlewoman, in order to treat a <hi>Scrophulous Tumor</hi> on her Son's Knee, when for Two Years attendance he demanded but Forty ſhillings, he was thereupon thought a very honeſt and able Artiſt, till it was made apparent to the Patient's Friends, that they had better have given him as many Pounds never to have undertaken it.</p>
               <p>When the good Gentlewoman perceiv'd no likelihood of her Son's recovery, ſhe thought fit to diſmiſs the <hi>Undertaker,</hi> who, as a Mark of his Judgment, left behind him this <hi>Prognoſtick,</hi> That if they waited till Time or ſome caſual application ſhould put the Swelling on Apoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating, there would then be no queſtion of a probability for cure.</p>
               <p>In ſome months afterwards the Wiſh of their preſaging Chyrurgeon was accompliſh'd, but ſo fatally to the Patient, that ſoon after the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of an indigeſted wheyiſh matter, and ſometimes a ſlimy viſcous <hi>Pus,</hi> there enſued an inveterate <hi>Synovia,</hi> accompanied with a moſt foetid Stench, proceeding from the parts affected, and undoubtedly arguing a <hi>Carioſity;</hi> the Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were corrupt, and the Joynt ſo looſe, that the <hi>Apophyſes</hi> or Extremities of the Bones at length ſhew'd themſelves in the <hi>Abſces,</hi> as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſeparated as in a diſlocation.</p>
               <p>This Gentleman was truly the moſt miſerable Spectacle under ſuch-like Circumſtances that I have ſeen, and ſo far from hopes or a poſſibility
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35377:46"/> of cure, (without Amputation, which he would not admit) that when he had languiſh'd many months, he painfully reſign'd his Breath.</p>
               <p>I was the rather guilty of this prolixity, ſince the Example ſeems to afford us as pregnant a demonſtration as we need deſire, of the Abuſes committed by unskilful People in their Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick Adminiſtrations: for, firſt of all, when the Patient had got an Accident of a contus'd Wound, he was committed to the care of one who went by the name of a <hi>Barber-Surgeon,</hi> where when he had ſuffer'd conſiderably through Ignorance, to rectifie the Miſtake, he referr'd himſelf to a moſt incomparable <hi>Doctreſs,</hi> who was Miſtreſs of a famous Pultiſs, to work Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: Under her hands the Tumor was render'd ſchirrous, and the Joynt immovable. When there was an unlikelihood of recovery perceiv'd here, being ſtill miſguided and flatter'd by fair Promiſes, he unhappily ſubmitted himſelf to the management of another Pretender, and finally dy'd under the too late care of an eminent and approv'd Chyrurgeon, whoſe Advice, or that of any judicious Practitioner, if he had firſt been govern'd by, I think it is not to be imagin'd that ſo ſlight a Contuſion, in the worſt habit of Body, ſhould ever have arriv'd to ſo incurable a Malady.</p>
               <p>Whilſt I was writing theſe Obſervations, I was diverted for ſome little time, being call'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to let one Blood, who took occaſion in Diſcourſe to tell me, That he had never
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:35377:47"/> been blooded more than once before, and that was by reaſon of a Wound he had receiv'd into his Body, which, he ſaid, had like to have coſt him his Life; hereupon his Mother, being by, immediately ſlip'd back his Shirt, and ſhew'd it me: I ask'd him who had been his Surgeon; he reply'd, <hi>One Mr.—, a very able man in</hi> C—ſtreet: I told him, 'twas like the Workmanſhip of ſuch an Intruder on our Art; <hi>Truly,</hi> anſwer'd the good Woman, <hi>we have great cauſe to reſpect him, ſince he ſav'd my Son's Life; for he told us when we came to him firſt, that the Wound was but an Hairs breadth from his Heart; and that had it been a little larger, his Bowels would have fallen out:</hi> yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this imminent danger, her Son had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd in about three weeks time.</p>
               <p>Thus the Caſe had been repreſented, the moſt notoriouſly falſe that could be, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſolve the Doubts of the ſurmiſing Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I ſhall impart the Truth in all its Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, that we may ſee how eaſily the People are impos'd on, and take all for granted that is put upon them by deceitful Men.</p>
               <p>The Wound was a Puncture, occaſion'd by a Fall againſt an Iron Spike, ſuperficially entring the <hi>Cutis</hi> and Carnous Membrane, and ſtopping, without hurt to the <hi>Sternon,</hi> a hand's breadth or more above the <hi>Enſiform Cartilage.</hi> This inſignificant buſineſs, which would (not unlikely) have admitted of a Cure by the firſt intention, and perfectly healed in two or
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:35377:47"/> three days time by the application of Aggluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natives, was tented ſo long, and afterwards ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly dreſſed up with ſome ſlabby <hi>Sarcotick Unguent,</hi> till an <hi>Hyperſarcoſis</hi> thruſt forth as large as a Small Nut, which the Operator not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what to do with, or what it was, however thought it neceſſary to alter his Medicine, and by chance, moſt probably dreſſing it with ſome powerful <hi>Epulotick,</hi> at length produc'd a Cica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix thereon, leaving the ſame deform'd, as if there had been a <hi>Ganglion</hi> or Wenny Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>Could any man have plaid the Knave and Ignorant in a greater meaſure than this <hi>Pſeudo-Chyrurgus?</hi> Firſt, his keeping open a not pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating Puncture; ſecondly, his ſuffering a <hi>Fungus</hi> to thruſt forth; and thirdly, his not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting the ſame, but cicatriſing on the Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, doth as evidently declare the weakneſs of his Judgment as his unbecoming Arrogance; the former, in ſo irrationally treating an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Puncture; and the latter, for his aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing ſo much of Art and Induſtry, where there was nothing more viſible than the greateſt want of Honeſty and Diſcretion.</p>
               <p>I cannot chuſe but reflect moreover on the Patient's Weakneſs, who could ſo eaſily believe that a Protuberance on the Breaſt-bone, was occaſion'd from ſome of his Bowels preſſing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to get out.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:35377:48"/>
               <p> We have really (conſidering the over-cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity of the People in Chyrurgick matters) great cauſe to bewail the neglect of the Civil Magiſtrate and all other Powers therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, who are ſo little careful to ſuppreſs <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders,</hi> and to take notice after what manner Men are qualified for the publick profeſſion of the Art of Surgery. I am ſatisfied that the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizing ſuch a Task as this would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly commodious, and the Reaſons for ſuch an Undertaking are, I think, as extraordinary weighty, if it were but on conſideration of thoſe evil and dangerous conſequences continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reſulting from the toleration of illegal Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitioners; a fatal Inſtance whereof you may find from the ſubſequent account.</p>
               <p>A Youth aged about Fifteen years, labouring of a malignant Feaver, when by a <hi>Metaſtaſis</hi> or critical tranſlation, the peccant matter was thrown forth of the bloody maſs it produc'd an <hi>Eryſipelas,</hi> ſpreading it ſelf on the right Arm, from the <hi>Cubitus</hi> or Elbow to the top of the <hi>Os Humeri,</hi> upon which the Patient began his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of a violent and intenſe heat affecting his whole Arm; in order to the removal whereof, it was thought neceſſary by his Friends to ſend for a <hi>Barber-Surgeon</hi> of their acquaintance, who coming to take a view of the caſe, told the young man, that he had got a <hi>St. Anthony's Fire,</hi> but he would ſend him ſomething that ſhould kill it before the next morning. Whereupon, without making any manner of Revulſion, or
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:35377:48"/> otherways preparing of his Body, he imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately orders an expreſſed Juice (ſuppoſed to be that of <hi>Houſe-leek)</hi> in which the Patient was to dip a folded Linnen Cloth, and bind the ſame upon his Arm. After ſome few repetitions of this Remedy, the heat was indeed abated, and the Inflammation (before highly red) gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually enclin'd towards a livid complexion. But now the Youth's Complaint was, of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Stupor or Numbneſs poſſeſſing the whole Arm, as if ſomewhat had been ſtrictly ty'd about the ſame. He was moreover hence diſturb'd with a <hi>Subſultus Tendinum,</hi> or light Convulſive twitches, now and then infeſting, and plainly arguing the danger which enſued; upon which the <hi>Barber</hi> was again conſulted, who thinking it time to lay aſide his firſt application, inſtead thereof, preſcribes an <hi>Embrocation</hi> of <hi>Unguentum de Althaea,</hi> by the uſe whereof the Patient receiving nothing of advantage, but finding himſelf much worſe, and wholly depriv'd the uſe of his Arm, for farther ſatisfaction, a more eminent Practitioner was call'd in, who found a confirm'd <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croſis,</hi> or Mortification, which had already ſeized the whole Arm, ſpreading it ſelf for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards over the <hi>Clavicle</hi> and <hi>Pectoral Muſcle,</hi> and reaching backwards the whole compaſs of the <hi>Scapula.</hi> The ſphacelated Member was however immediately taken off, but to little purpoſe, the mortification ſtill encreaſing and oppoſing the moſt powerful Endeavours, ſoon
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:35377:49"/> oblig'd the Patient to a ſurrender, and accept of a <hi>Quietus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I hope this may Warn a practiſing Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, how he intermeddles in Chyrurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (quite out of his Element) to the loſs of his Credit and Reputation, and oftentimes to the irreparable danger of the Patient; as in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going caſe.</p>
               <p>We may, I think, imagine it one of the worſt of Sins, thus ſhamefully to trifle with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Humane Life; and doubtleſs, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the impartial method of Divine Juſtice, the Miſcarriages of thoſe poor Creatures, who have thus miſerably ſuffer'd through wilful Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, calls aloud for vengeance on the Heads of ſuch as have in the manner here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd, been acceſſary thereto. What a burthen muſt there lye upon his Conſcience, who by an unjuſt pretence of a Call to the Practice, will intermeddle in another's buſineſs (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the knowledge of his inability to perform what is requir'd) till by ſuch his unwarrantable actions he hath brought the Patient into the moſt miſerable ſtate imaginable?</p>
               <p>I think I ſhall not need (though I am farther furniſh'd) to make other Reflections, ſince thoſe already mention'd may abundantly ſatisfie an inquiſitive Perſon, with how little Reaſon the Barber boaſts himſelf a Surgeon, and with how great detriment to the People his Chyrurgick Undertakings are countenanc'd without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:35377:49"/>
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>THAT the <hi>Chyrurgick Art</hi> hath been yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſrepreſented, and its legal Profeſſors by many People render'd ignominious, we are not a little oblig'd to the ſordid and baſe Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of thoſe men, who affect to be known by the peculiar name of <hi>Boneſetters;</hi> as if becauſe they particularly apply themſelves to that only part of <hi>Chyrurgery,</hi> they would be the more eſteem'd, or for ſuch their Pretences thought more famous and ſucceſsful than other Men.</p>
               <p>The Fame of an <hi>Experienc'd Boneſetter</hi> ſounds ſo great in the Ears of a Vulgar Apprehenſion, that thinking the reduction of a fractur'd or broken Limb, or the repoſition of a Bone diſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, to its place, more properly his Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they wholly neglect conſulting with the more eminent <hi>Chyrurgeon</hi> herein, as believing it no appurtenance to his Profeſſion.</p>
               <p>Why the Legal Practitioner ſhould be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from this ſo conſiderable a part of his Duty, is ſomewhat ſtrange, and much more ſo (in my opinion) that the particular Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers hereof ſhould be more than ordinarily confided in, or ſo wonderfully ſought unto.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:35377:50"/>
               <p> If we make a ſcrutinous enquiry into the Practice of theſe men, I am ſatisfied we ſhall find, that they have not been wanting by their unworthy proceedings to bring as great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon us as any of the reſt: And this, in a great meaſure, hath been brought to paſs by their deteſtable as well as impious Principles of conſtantly aſſerting for an undeniable Truth, That almoſt all Accidents that happen where they are requir'd to lend their aſſiſtance, are no leſs than <hi>Fractures,</hi> or undoubted <hi>Diſlocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If your Arm be ſo weaken'd, as that you have not the compleat and perfect motions, by a Contuſion, overlifting or reaching, by which the Ligaments and Tendons of the Muſcles may be extended beyond their <hi>natural tone;</hi> if you ſeek Redreſs herein of one who calls himſelf a <hi>Boneſetter,</hi> you are preſently inform'd with the ſorrowful tydings, That your Limb is out of Joynt. If by ſlipping of your Foot aſide, or treading the ſame awry, you are diſabled for the preſent to walk without ſome pain, you will (if you refer your ſelf to him) be ſure to find a broken Legg, or an Ancle out of its proper place.</p>
               <p>It is no difficult matter for any confident Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaker, to perſwade Men (of a large capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city in other reſpects) that when they come under the reſtraint of a Cubicular Confinement, by any outward Miſchance, it is for no ſmaller matter than a broken or disjoynted Member;
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35377:50"/> out of which ſeeming conſiderable Misfortune, when (by the moſt immethodical courſe taken) they have the good hap to be recover'd, the operating <hi>Boneſetter</hi> is then applauded for a Skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Perſon, and certainly very Honeſt, becauſe he try'd no Practice with them, neither kept them ſo long in hand as is uſual with Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons.</p>
               <p>This is too commonly a Practice made uſe of by theſe <hi>Boneſetters,</hi> to deceive the Ignorant; and we have the leſs reaſon to admire that the Knavery is not detected, when we conſider how little difficult it is for him who can thus ſtifle the Dictates of his Conſcience, to delude the Unwary, and impoſe upon their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>I have oftentimes found, when call'd to ſuch as by the occaſion of a Blow or Fall have been incapacitated for the wonted motion of their Limbs, they have been ready enough to imagine them either fractur'd or out of Joynt. Nay, I have farther met with ſome of ſo peeviſhly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet a Temper, that when they had litt on a Diſaſter proving troubleſome, beyond their own imagination of the Cauſe, would tax the Artiſt of want of Judgment, if unwilling to treat them (though meerly fictitious) as really broken or diſlocated Members.</p>
               <p>This was the caſe of a Victualler not far from <hi>B—street,</hi> who by a fall down Stairs had receiv'd a Contuſion on his Ribs, forwards to the Breaſt-bone, for which he was let Blood,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35377:51"/> and rationally treated by an expert Practitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, with hopes of ſpeedy recovery. The night enſuing, from the abortive tattle of ſome igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Old Woman, he was importun'd, and at length prevail'd on to ſend again for his Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon; who haſtening, found him lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Misfortune, being redoubled from his Wive's Complaint, and pitifully condoling his caſe, in being neglected, for ſo much as he was now fully aſſur'd, that his Ribbs were bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
               <p>Hereupon, for his farther ſatisfaction, he was again ſtrictly reſearch'd, and his indiſpoſition more diligently enquir'd into; although no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could give conjecture or ſuſpicion of a Fracture: yet however, the diſcontented Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient would by no means reſt ſatisfied till the Surgeon (contrary to his own honeſt intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) had favour'd him in his opinion, that there might be a broken Rib, and by <hi>Compreſs</hi> and <hi>Bandage</hi> dreſt him up again: for his farther Security <hi>Venaeſection</hi> was repeated, and a <hi>Trau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick</hi> decoction, with a <hi>Pectoral Linctus</hi> were preſcrib'd; but from the ſecond day that he was bound up, he grew well of his Conceipt, and ſoon after went about his Affairs.</p>
               <p>By this we may be acquainted where a Man is minded to act a Knaviſh Part, how cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly his Abuſes are entertain'd by ignorant People; and indeed, if ſuch a Practice as this be at all tolerable, it muſt be allow'd in ſuch a caſe, where the Patient proves obſtinate to the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35377:51"/> Advice of his Chyrurgeon, being reſolv'd to pay for his own Folly, in augmenting the value of an inconſiderable Cure.</p>
               <p>Indeed, it is abundant pity that a free and entire ſubmiſſion or condeſcention in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to his Chyrurgeon's Honeſty, ſhould be ſo evilly requited as it is by too many of theſe only <hi>Titular Boneſetters,</hi> who are certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome of the vileſt, for their treacherous Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes on the People, of all other the ſpurious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to this worthy Art.</p>
               <p>It's not unlikely to be objected, That I am too ſevere in my Cenſure of theſe men, who without queſtion, in the diverſity of Caſualties happening in their way, muſt certainly at ſome times meet with real Fractures and Diſlocations, and if then they were deficient in Judgment to manage one as well as the other, doubtleſs they would be decry'd for the moſt notorious Cheats, and wholly unable to keep up their Repute.</p>
               <p>To this I reply, That as I doubt not but there are many Miſchances of this nature, which in reality ſometimes preſent with other Buſineſs to their Care, ſo I ſhall require no other (neither deſire any better) Proof of their Indiſcretion or want of Knowledge ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially to adminiſter Relief; than to ſuperviſe their Proceedings with any Patient under ſuch an Affliction.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:35377:52"/>
               <p> Were I to give my Opinion, I muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that I look upon that perſon's caſe to be very dangerous, if not deſperate, who in order to his Cure hath apply'd himſelf to ſuch an one as we are at preſent diſcourſing of; and my Reaſons that he hath been ſtill enabled in ſome meaſure to preſerve his Credit with the World, are theſe: firſt of all, his ſlight and careleſs looking after a ſimple Strain or Contuſion, after a pull and hawl or two, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, That it was a Fracture or Diſlocation, and is now ſet to rights. The ſpeedy Succeſs, I ſay, attending ſuch-like Operations, is one great cauſe that he hath been ſo wonderfully eſteem'd by the beguiled, who can well enough wink at ſome few Failings now and then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervening. Furthermore, his Diſappointments of this nature, if they are not more numerous than his ſucceſsful Enterprizes, are look'd on by the Deluded to proceed from Cauſes extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary: or, where the caſe hath been ſo full of danger (though no more than a ſimple Fracture) that the Patient, in all likelihood, muſt have miſcarried under any other the moſt able hand.</p>
               <p>That the matter in debate will bear a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection of this nature, I ſhall now endeavour to demonſtrate; and I think we may prove from Experience, that upon the reduction of a Bone, which hath been diſplac'd through a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble force, whereby a defluxion is excited, and the part (till ſuch Accidents which enſue, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd)
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35377:52"/> render'd unapt for motion. I ſay, that notwithſtanding the ſaid Bone hath been ſafely reduc'd, it is a very unlikely thing that the late ſuffering Member ſhould ſo ſuddenly recover its wonted ſtrength, or that it ought to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſo ſpeedily to exerciſe its uſual functions. I am very well aſſur'd, that if the buſineſs were poſitively ſo, as it is too often repreſented, notwithſtanding the Patient's Endeavour to exert the utmoſt of his Strength, he would find to his ſorrow, an inability, and that he was, for very great cauſe, debar'd the privilege of ſo haſty a Recovery.</p>
               <p>I know it is a uſual thing with many of theſe men, when they have perſwaded the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient that his Limb was luxated, but is now cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, by their diligence and care, replac'd, to permit him preſently to go about his buſineſs, without binding, keeping up, or any ways to favour the Limb ſo lately out of Joint; neither is he to regard the wearing of more than one Cerecloth (as they call it) and the uſe of a Five-ſhilling Pot of their infallible Oyntment, to finiſh the work.</p>
               <p>There are many perſons have thought much to be rationally treated and kept under a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary confinement for ſuch-like Accidents, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have receiv'd information from their Neighbours, that far greater matters have been made light of under the care of a skilful Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetter.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:35377:53"/>
               <p> When I was viſiting a poor man in <hi>S—,</hi> for whom I had reduc'd a fractur'd Clavicle, it was thought a very diſhoneſt Principle in me, becauſe I forewarn'd him of uſing his lame Arm, or putting it on its wonted actions in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt three weeks time. I was much cenſur'd by his Siſter, who ſtood by, and took upon her, from her own knowledge, to aſſure me, that <hi>Boneſetters</hi> were not ſo ſtrict, yet much more ſucceſsful: To confirm this, ſhe told me a Story (I think it may be ſo thought) of her Husband, who had been ſome time before cured by Mr. <hi>T—</hi>in a very little time; but what was moſt admirable, this man, on the ſame Limb, had his Coller-bone broken in three places, his Shoulder put out of Joynt, the two Bones below the Cubit, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Radius</hi> and <hi>Ulna,</hi> were alſo fractur'd, and ſeveral of his Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers wounderfully bruiſed by a violent force; yet notwithſtanding all this, by the application of a ſovereign Pultiſs, her Husband was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly well in little more than a fortnights time, although he could then, with much eaſe, raiſe an hundred weight a great height from the Ground with his broken Arm.</p>
               <p>Where is there ſuch an execrable piece of Impudence to be parallel'd, that dare thus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly contemn the divine Mandates, and prophane even the Authority of Heaven it ſelf?</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:35377:53"/>
               <p> It is the injurious Practice of theſe knaviſh Undertakers makes many Perſons ſo unwilling to ſubmit to a juſt and reaſonable government of themſelves under ſuch-like Calamities; and it has been, I am certain, the ruine of ſome Thouſands, who have been ſo impos'd on, ſtill running from one to another, without redreſs of their Grievances, till at length (having un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone the greateſt Miſery) they have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd themſelves unpitied, and their Infirmities irrecoverable.</p>
               <p>I queſtion not but you have heard the Fame of ſome Country <hi>Plow-jobbers,</hi> who are ſo dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous at the knack of Bone-ſetting, that where a poor man hath been brought to them ten or twenty miles, with his Knee or Ancle out of place, it hath been preſently ſet for Two ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings or Half a crown, when dreſſing him up with a famous Plaiſter of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> or <hi>Barbadoes-Tarr,</hi> he is preſently order'd to put forth his ſtrength, and (if he can) to walk home, whereby, he is told, he may diſperſe and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe naughty Humours which would fall thereon.</p>
               <p>'Tis ſuch a like Rumor as this, that hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd many, and ſome of them of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, who being blinded in their Judgments, have forſaken the moſt eminent Profeſſors here in Town, and convey'd themſelves twenty or thirty miles, to ſome noted <hi>Boneſetter,</hi> where when their Self-experience prompts them to a Repentance of their Folly in ſuffering them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:35377:54"/> to be deluded, they have return'd in a much worſe condition than they went: and I think it is the leſs ſevere, that incredulous men learn by their own Misfortunes to beware for the time to come. It is an ancient Saying, <hi>Exemplo alterius, &amp;c.—</hi>but truly, for the moſt part, another's Miſeries will not caution us, that we fall not on the ſame, who are ſeldom ſo throughly ſatisfied, unleſs we taſte of them our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Is it not a very great Argument of a frail Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, for us to think, that a Limb, by a very conſiderable force diſplac'd, and oftentimes as great a one us'd to reſtore it, whereby an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable fluxion is ſtirr'd up, which produceth Pain, Tumor, and ſometimes Inflammation, attended with an <hi>Ecchymoſis,</hi> or Sugillation of the Blood, oftentimes ſtagnating in the capilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Veſſels and Interſtices of the Muſcles, if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worſe occur? How unlikely, I ſay, is it that ſuch a ſuffering Member as this ſhould (till ſuch Accidents are overcome) be ſafely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the liberty of its accuſtomed Uſe?</p>
               <p>I would not be thought hereby to lay down ſuch a Rule as ſhould admit of no exception, for that I know where a light and trivial Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent hath concur'd to the production of a Diſlocation, in a Member prediſpos'd thereto, by a relaxation of the Ligaments or otherways, the danger is not ſo great, and the Patient (if minded to hazard a Reluxation) ſooner capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated for its uſe, upon a reſtitution: but where
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:35377:54"/> the caſe happens otherwiſe, I am well ſatisfied, that the repoſition of ſuch a Diſlocation, and removing its ſometimes ſevere Attendants, is a work of much greater moment and concern, than we are tempted by the Stories of unlearned men to imagine.</p>
               <p>Hence we would infer this kind of Boneſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be a deceitful perſon, as abuſive as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and a very miſchievous Intruder on the Profeſſion of our Art.</p>
               <p>That he is ſuch as repreſented in this preſent Section, will want no other Proof than his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Endeavours to poſſeſs People with a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of his Abilities for the Practice; and when they get the leaſt miſchance (whereby for the preſent they are in ſome meaſure diſabled) his pretending by a feigned extenſion, and other juggling contrivances, to reduce what before he (falſly) affirm'd to be a Diſlocation.</p>
               <p>Thus I have heard of one of them, who when he came to a Patient, and had buſied himſelf ſome time in an Extenſion of the Limb, at length cunningly turning off his Head near the part ſuppoſed for reduction, would make ſuch an artificial noiſe by the grating of his Teeth, that the by-ſtanders, and the Patient himſelf, were forward enough almoſt to ſwear they heard the disjoynted Bone (which was never out) knap into its place.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:35377:55"/>
               <p> Let us take but a Survey of thoſe Accidents which prove Luxations, and have been mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the moſt famous Boneſetter, I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain we ſhall find him more ignorant and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly robuſtick, more irrational, immetho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical, unſafe, and far more tedious than a Chyrurgeon's Servant of but two years expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</p>
               <p>How many ſtiff and curved Members, what numbers of uſeleſs emaciated Legs and Arms proceeding from Diſlocations, which have been affirmed (but were never) ſet, may we find at this day in <hi>London,</hi> being Fruits of the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings of ſome preſumptuous Boneſetter. And ſhall we ſtill be ſo miſguided in our Opinion, as to ſlight the Labours of the faithful Artiſt, whilſt we confide in the Promiſe of one whom we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count more worthy, only becauſe he takes upon him no other buſineſs than the reducing of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or disjoynted Members.</p>
               <p>Having thus far hinted to you his Dealings, with reference to what he calls a Diſlocation, I ſhall trouble you with a ſhort account of his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour where he meets with a Fractur'd Limb, at leaſt where he takes upon him, right or wrong, ſo to affirm it; and theſe two, <hi>viz.</hi> a diviſion or disjunction in the continuity of a Bone, call'd a Fracture, and a diſtortion of the Head thereof from its <hi>Acetabulum,</hi> nam'd com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly a Bone out of joynt, are the principal or ſole parts of his Employment.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:35377:55"/>
               <p> His treating the former of theſe, is but little different, or varies not much from the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod which he takes in looking after the other. 'Tis true, for the moſt part he reap more Profit and Repute from the one, inaſmuch as a broken Limb is generally look'd on of greater moment, and the cure thereof more valuable than that of a Diſlocation: ſo that where a Contuſion on the Muſcles, or a ſudden wrench of their Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, paſſes under the denomination of a Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and the Patient in a ſhort time (as well he may) recover, you muſt conceive his Skill is then more highly extoll'd, and his Pay ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd.</p>
               <p>But after all, if to diſcover the real Truth, we may be ſo inquiſitive as to trace him where he hath been concern'd indeed, either with a broken or diſplac'd Member, and make our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations on the courſe of his Proceedings, we ſhall find him, I doubt not, ſo far ſhort of the Knowledge requir'd in that difficult part of our Art, that it will be the leaſt of Crimes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count him unworthy of his aſſumed Title, in compariſon with the more able and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienc'd Chyrurgeon.</p>
               <p>His Anatomical Judgment, that abſolutely neceſſary Baſis for this adminiſtration, is ſo very inconſiderable, that I have known ſome of them juſtly reprehended for their ridiculous Talk, by an indifferently well read <hi>Mechanick.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:35377:56"/>
               <p> Comparing Man with other Animals, he preſently concludes, that he alſo hath Bones in his Body; and therefore when the People get any hurt, there muſt forſooth preſently happen a Fracture or Diſlocation in one or other of them, which is neareſt to the part complain'd on by the Patient: But if you raiſe an Argument (although no Critick) you find him no man for Diſcourſe, unleſs you can bear the Burden of his Nonſence.</p>
               <p>Ask him how differently Bones are conjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which of them by <hi>Articulation,</hi> and which by <hi>Symphiſis;</hi> the diſtinction between <hi>Diarthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> and <hi>Synarthroſis;</hi> the ſeveral ways of their connexion under theſe two Heads; ask him which he calls <hi>Enarthroſis, Arthrodia,</hi> and what <hi>Ginglymus;</hi> enquire by how many ſeveral man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Bones are joyn'd by <hi>Symphiſis;</hi> what he means by <hi>Sutura, Harmonia, Gomphoſis;</hi> or what he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands by <hi>Synchondroſis, Synneuroſis, Syſſarcoſis,</hi> or <hi>Syntenoſis;</hi> I ſay, query but theſe things of this wonderful Operator, and (notwithſtanding we muſt own them to be requiſite appurtenances to the Study of the Art, in which no one can be unskill'd, if compleat in the Practice of Bone-ſetting) you ſhall gain as ſatisfactory Anſwers, as if to an Infant you were diſcourſing in ſome unknown Language.</p>
               <p>How can it be ſuppos'd now that any one who is ignorant or unknowing after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and by what means the ſeveral Bones of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:35377:56"/> Humane Bodies are conjoyn'd, ſhould be in a capacity the eaſieſt way, the ſafeſt and moſt commodious, or indeed by any way to repoſe them, when by a Misfortune they are ſlipt from their proper places; is it not farther more improbable, that ſuch a perſon as perfectly knows not where the breach is made, whether any or not; if any, whether <hi>tranſverſe, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, &amp;c.</hi> or how to reſiſt the Accidents which will enſue, and afterwards kindly to aſſiſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the generation of a <hi>Callus,</hi> or, in ſhort, what a <hi>Callus</hi> means; is it not, I ſay, a Preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption to imagine, that a deſir'd Succeſs ſhould attend ſuch an abuſeful Intruder's Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings?</p>
               <p>We find it, I am ſure, a very rare Caſe, to ſee either Leg, or Arm which have been fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctur'd, and the reduction thereof attempted by a pretending Boneſetter, (if they have eſcap'd the tyranny of a <hi>Gangreen</hi> or <hi>Sphacelus,</hi> occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned frequently from their immoderate bandage intercepting the Spirits, and retarding the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation) without ſome or other indubitable mark of their Ignorance and Indiſcretion, as a crooked Member from a common and ſimple Fracture, an ill-favour'd if not painful Protube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which might often have been prevented by Art, but will now, to their no ſmall preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, ſhew they had a broken Limb all their life after.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:35377:57"/>
               <p> This was the ill hap of a poor man, at that time of <hi>L—W—,</hi> who in the morning having fractur'd both <hi>Foeils</hi> of his Leg, was carried to a famous Boneſetter at the other end of the Town, who ignorantly girt him up with half a dozen pieces of a Hoopſtick laid over a ſingle Cloth, which had been ſpread with a ſort of Paſte, next to the bare Leg, and faſten'd with many circumvolutions of a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Filleting; afterwards ordering the poor wretch to be carried home a mile and half, where he was as negligently laid into his Bed, without <hi>Pillow, Junks, Cradle,</hi> or other deſence from the incumbent Bed cloaths.</p>
               <p>Having lain thus whilſt the Evening, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of Pain, his Friends out of pity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted a ſpeedy Viſit from a neighbouring Chyrurgeon, who, with my ſelf, coming to him, we found the Patient roaring after an hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous manner, and taking a view of the fractur'd Limb, could plainly perceive, above and below the Bandage, it was already veſicated, and tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to mortifie from the Foot upwards.</p>
               <p>Having cut away, and otherways with much difficulty ſeparated the Cloaths, which had been daub'd over with ſome very Emplaſtick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, we found the Splints, by a ſtrict com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, had even buried themſelves in the Fleſh, and with abundance of pain and trouble could not be drawn away without excoriating the parts they lay upon.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:35377:57"/>
               <p> When we had thus clear'd our way, (not having an <hi>Elixivium</hi> in readineſs) we or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd ſome common Spirit of Wine to be ſet over the Fire, whilſt we ſnipp'd off the <hi>Veſications,</hi> impleet with a livid <hi>Serum,</hi> and laid down the Leg upon a ſoft and eaſie Pillow, where it was fomented with a ſufficient number of warm <hi>Stuphes,</hi> and at length with a ſuitable Rowler dreſt him up leaving the Limb in as eaſie a poſition as we could contrive. We contented our ſelves for this time with what had been done, not ſo much regarding the Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, till the more important danger of a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification was taken off, which was in a few days afterwards, with all its threatning Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms remov'd, when taking a greater liberty in ſearching for the broken Bones, we perceiv'd a part of the <hi>Tibia</hi> almoſt ready to protrude it ſelf, lying prominent a little above the <hi>Maleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Internus.</hi> But finding that every little motion was extreamly painful, from the uneven ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the fractur'd Bones moleſting and irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Nervous Fibres; and being terribly perplex'd with the thoughts of a Re reduction, he declar'd poſitively his diſſent therefrom, begging for God's ſake that we would deſiſt from troubling him, but lay down his Leg without Plaiſter or Bandage, where it lay eaſie to him; for ſince the danger of its being mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified was over, he was certain in himſelf that the former Undertaker had placed the Bones
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:35377:58"/> right, and that in a little time they would grow together.</p>
               <p>Hereupon (finding him ſo very wiſe) we left him to his own management, having firſt given him to underſtand what he muſt truſt to, if he perſiſted to believe that his Bone was ſet: Thus we parted. Whether or no the Boneſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was afterwards ſent for, to be inform'd of his Work, I know not, but have lately ſeen the Patient a meer emaciated Cripple, ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to walk by the help of Crutches.</p>
               <p>I could give you an account of many more Examples of this Nature, where the Practice hath been of near affinity with this ſo lately mention'd, and the practiſing Pretender ſome famous Boneſetter.</p>
               <p>Indeed, a man ſhall rarely at this time peaceably and quietly diſcharge his Office without interruption; either we muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted unknowing in our Applications, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Patient finds not preſently his wonted Eaſe; or negligent, becauſe we will not, neither can with ſafety open their Limbs every day or two; or, laſt of all, diſhoneſt, intending to make a Prize of them, by keeping them ſo long in hand. All this befals us from their conſideration that ſo many People ſo ſpeedily recover under the care of Boneſetters: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I have told you, every ſimple Contuſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by theſe men repreſented as a Fracture or Diſlocation, the Patient may as ſafely be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35377:58"/> to follow his buſineſs at a week or ten days end, as we can ſuffer one, who hath in reality receiv'd ſuch a Miſchance, in a month or ſix weeks time: and I think all ſuch may be thankful to GOD and their Surgeon, that they eſcape ſo, eſpecially if they conſider how far worſe it happens to ſome under ſuch-like circumſtances, when taken in hand by theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Practitioners in our Art, as in the preceding Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>Amidſt the multitude of ſuch as have moſt unworthily aſſum'd the Character of Boneſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, it were almoſt an inexcuſable omiſſion, ſhould we forget to number the deceaſed <hi>T—,</hi> but ſince it would be a petty kind of Impiety to trample on the Aſhes of the Dead, I ſhall forbear all Reflections of my own, yet cannot paſs by a remarkable Caſe given us by a late Author, where this perſon had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd.</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>A Youth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of about Twelve years of age was ſeiz'd with a Pain in his right Hip, it encreaſing with Tumefaction and great Lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; the Parents ſuſpecting it might be out of joynt, ſent for</hi> T<hi>—the Boneſetter, he declar'd it luxated, and pretended to ſet it, and dreſſed it up his way: The Child continuing lame, they ſent for him again; he aſſur'd them that he had ſet it, and that in time the Child would recover ſtrength in it, and be well: But the Child growing daily</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:35377:59"/> 
                  <hi>more pained, Chyrurgeons were conſulted, and at laſt my ſelf; I ſaw the head of the</hi> Os Foemoris <hi>ſhot upwards, and a large Tumor poſſeſſing the Hip and parts about, under which there ſeem'd to be lodg'd Matter; there was alſo a long white Swelling ſtretching down the forepart of the Thigh, from the Groyn towards the Knee, within four Fingers breadth of it: the Tumor ſeem'd to be full of Matter, and to derive it ſelf from the Hip, and that the Luxation had been made by Fluxion, and encreas'd by Extenſion. But however it was, the Bone was not capable of reduction, nor could I promiſe my ſelf any Credit by my Endeavours there; yet I comply'd with his Parents, reſolving to ſerve them as well as I could, but deſir'd that the Boneſetter might be firſt fetch'd to ſee his Work, I not thinking it ſafe to meddle in the Cure whilſt he inſiſted, that the Bone was reduced: They ſent often for him, but he did not come, till I acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally met him at a Perſon of Honour's Lodgings, and by Threatnings brought him with me to the Child, where he acknowledg'd his Fault, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd the Bone incapable of reduction; yet this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low went directly back to that Perſon of Honour, and upon demand where he had been, declar'd, That he had been with me to ſet my Patient's Hip, and that he had reduced it. This fellow's ſcurvy uſing me almoſt diſcourag'd me in the Undertaking, but after making a Preſentation of it, I attempted the Cure,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:35377:59"/>
               <p> By this account you may perceive the baſe ſhifts and evaſions theſe men are put upon of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes to raiſe their Credit.</p>
               <p>I have ſeen great numbers of People, where I have been converſant, in reducing of Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures and Diſlocations, who when an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity hath preſented, would very commonly affirm, That after a fortnights time, when their Limbs as (they were told) were broken, and had been ſet together by the ſaid <hi>T—,</hi> they were as fit for the moſt weighty and ſtirring buſineſs as before in their whole life-time: A matter as unlikely as impoſſible; for if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that the diviſion of theſe ſolid parts is not conjoyn'd by <hi>Agglutination,</hi> or immediate uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as in Wounds upon a fleſhy part, but by interpoſition of the nutritious Particles, falling off from the little mouths of the ruptur'd Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and other the Pores in the divided medul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary parts of the Bone it ſelf, which at the ſpace of ſo ſhort a time will be no more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd than, like a Jelly or ſoft Wax, receiving any accidental impreſſion, and for want of care, by a diſorderly or irregular poſition, is the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of many crooked and deformed Members. This weighty Conſideration doth infallibly and experimentally indicate, that where ſo early a liberty is given to move their Limbs, and no prejudice enſues from ſuch a liberty, there was no Fracture or <hi>Solution of Continuity</hi> in the Bone.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:35377:60"/>
               <p> I have ſtrictly examin'd and ſearched ſome few, who have been deluded by theſe Pretences, but could never find (nor was it likely that I ſhould) any bearing out of a fractur'd Bone, or other perceptible demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Callus,</hi> which muſt of neceſſity inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene, and is the moſt certain and permanent indication thereof.</p>
               <p>I hope, by what has been ſaid, there are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Arguments given of the Ignorance of a <hi>Boneſetter:</hi> Indeed, the Name is a meer Bubble, or empty Title, wherewith unwary and imprudent People are enſnar'd, and oftentimes too dearly pay for their Experience.</p>
               <p>One would imagine, if this worthy Art were ſo eaſily attain'd as might be conjectur'd from the Preſumption of theſe men, there would be little occaſion for us to put our ſelves to the charge of purchaſing our Experience, under ſome eminent Practitioner, by a ſedulous Study, and a tedious Service therein: nay, it might be not unreaſonably thought, that we are fond of a Confinement, when we conſider, that if a man have but confidence ſufficient to avouch for himſelf, whether or no he be otherwiſe qualified, if he pleaſe hereupon, to take the Profeſſion of a Surgeon upon him, he ſhall meet with the ſame welcome, and by many who have not try'd his Abilities be accounted as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy as the beſt of us all. For confirmation
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:35377:60"/> hereof I will deliver to you on my own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a remarkable inſtance.</p>
               <p>A Weaver in <hi>B—ſtreet</hi> coming home in the Evening much in drink, there aroſe a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between him and his Wife, which grew to ſuch a heighth, that he could bethink himſelf of no other Revenge, at leaſt no better method, to avoid the Storm which was coming on him, than by haſtening back again to his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, where he hoped to be at quiet. Hereupon going to the Door (which the good Woman had beforehand lock'd, reſolving to keep him in) and finding himſelf unable to force his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage there, he fearleſly makes to the Window, and (although a Story high) leaps out thereat, but was receiv'd by the Ground with ſo unkind and rugged an embrace, as made him forcibly content to be carried up again a farther way than he came down, where by the help of his Neighbours, in great miſery he was laid upon his Bed.</p>
               <p>Being immediately call'd in to officiate for my Maſter; upon enquiry, I found, that by his Fall he had fractur'd the <hi>Fibula</hi> or <hi>minor Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> of his Leg; there was already a large Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor and Extravaſation; the Fracture was made obliquely, and the lower end of the Bone pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuberating a little above the <hi>Maleolus Externus;</hi> however, with a little aſſiſtance I reduc'd it, and with a ſmall Compreſs and Defenſative dreſs'd him up, as uſually in ſuch caſes, laying him in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:35377:61"/> as eaſie a poſition as I could, and ordering his Wife in looking after him to keep him ſtill and quiet.</p>
               <p>Thus I left him for that time, and return'd the next morning, when I found my Patient very ſenſible of his condition, and heartily ſorry for his Indiſcretion; there were all things ſafe, and not the leaſt Symptom attending more than commonly intervenes. He promis'd to be rul'd, upon which I told him I did not queſtion but when we came to open it, we ſhould find all in good forwardneſs; and accordingly, on our firſt taking off the Dreſſings, the Leg was ſtreight, without inequality or bearing out of the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctur'd Bone. He reſted well from the firſt night, and ſo continued.</p>
               <p>At the end of One and twenty days I took him out of Bed, and at the expiration of a month he ſet his Foot to the ground, from that time walking by the help of a Crutch, till a ſhort time after that it was laid aſide. And now the Tumor which fell upon his lame Leg, upon his firſt upriſing ſeem'd wholly to be diſcuſs'd, whereupon taking the liberty to walk abroad, and falling to his wonted courſe of drinking Brandy and ſtrong Beer, he contracted ſo ill an habit of Body, that the Humours now abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for want of his accuſtomed labour, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd a new defluxion on the broken Leg, with a ſmall inflammation, and a very troubleſome <hi>Pruritus,</hi> which was certainly caus'd from his
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:35377:61"/> having been for ſome time kept up to a ſpare and moderate Dyet, and now coming of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to make uſe of a more ſtrong and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful nouriſhment; upon this he made his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to us; I told him the reaſon of it, and to prevent farther miſchief, advis'd him to bleed and purge: he deſir'd time to conſider farther of it, and promis'd to return in two or three days; but however it happen'd, we heard no more of him till about five or ſix weeks afterwards, when going by his Houſe, I took the opportunity of calling on him, and was preſently welcom'd by his Wife with the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious Language of a diſhoneſt and unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful perſon; ſhe told me, that I had ruin'd her Husband, and that his Leg was very near to have been cut off ſince I had ſeen him; that it was broken out all over; and farther, that ſhe had taken the Advice of three ſeveral Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, one of them being the King's general Surgeon, who told her, That theſe ſevere Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms were brought upon him by his broken Leg, which had never been well ſet.</p>
               <p>I was very attentive to the Woman's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and did at firſt imagine it to be a Fiction or plauſible Story, invented with a deſign to keep off the Demand of Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for his Cure, till being better inform'd of the buſineſs by others, I began to admire ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly, that any Artiſt (eſpecially the King's Surgeon) ſhould be ſo void of Knowledge, as
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:35377:62"/> well as Honeſty, to impute this defluxion of ſharp Humour upon the Leg to an ill reduction of the Fracture, which had been ſet and united by a confirm'd <hi>Callus,</hi> above a month before. I thought it very ſtrange, that three ſuch Practitioners as they were repreſented ſhould be ſo far ſhort of the Truth, and upon that account endeavour'd all I could to inform my ſelf who they were; the firſt of theſe, I came ſoon after to underſtand, was a Barber in the Neighbourhood, whoſe Frame of Blood-Porringers, and his Cloth ſew'd round with Teeth, were all that render'd him ſo eminent a Profeſſor: the ſecond who had been conſulted was a practiſing Ap—in <hi>S—F—;</hi> this Perſon had forewarn'd the Patient, that he ſhould not bleed, becauſe the Weather was not warm enough; and for the ſame cauſe Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was interdicted. The laſt that had been advis'd with, I found to be an illegal, skulking, Sea Practitioner, who had wheedled himſelf into their good opinion, and by aſſuming the Epithet of a <hi>Regius-Profeſſor,</hi> was look'd upon as an <hi>Oracle,</hi> and his Promiſes already little ſhort of Performance. They thought they could do no leſs than give this ſworded Gentleman his Fee in hand for his Viſit; after which the Doctor took an occaſion to withdraw and ſhow them his backſide, for they could never after hear what became of him.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:35377:62"/>
               <p> Theſe were the three famouſly qualified Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, who had concurr'd in their Opinions, That the Bone was not rightly ſet, and that if they had not been conſulted, the Leg muſt have been cut off.</p>
               <p>I have been the larger in a rehearſal of all circumſtances relating to this caſe, that I might more clearly inveſtigate the whole truth of the matter, and give the plainer demonſtration of the fraudulent Practiſes of ſuch abuſeful Intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders on this noble Art.</p>
               <p>I think the Caſe was here ſo evident, that nothing unleſs a Barber's Ignorance could have made, upon an excoriation, the moſt irrational prediction of an <hi>Amputation:</hi> what other Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient might indeed have been expected, than that from the Patient's acquir'd <hi>Chacochymy</hi> he ſhould be infeſted with ſo troubleſome an Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceration, which was no other than the effect of an acred or ſharp <hi>Serum</hi> in the Blood, more readily redounding on the weak Member than another part.</p>
               <p>Who, unleſs ſuch an imprudent practiſing Ap—, would have forbidden in this caſe <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> with the repetition of appropriate <hi>Catharticks?</hi> or, what Novice other than an unexperienc'd Sea Practitioner would have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd the application of Digeſtives, to encreaſe the pain and fluxion, where when the acidity of the Blood had been corrected, there had needed nothing more than an anodyne <hi>Epu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotick</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:35377:63"/> to have perfected this mighty cure?</p>
               <p>We may hereby inform our ſelves how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable a diſtinction the Commonalty make between a legal Artiſt and a ſpurious or falſe Pretender. They imagine (as we may reaſonably think) that there is no other diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between a Barber's Pole, when his Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow is beſet with Porringers, and the Surgeon's Arms, than in ſome few degrees of a larger purchas'd Knowledge and acquir'd Experience; and therefore whilſt the former calls himſelf a Barber-Surgeon, and will practiſe underhand, it may be for little or nothing, they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſave themſelves a preſent Penny, altho' it coſt them a Pound hereafter; or to let this Perſon try Experiments upon their Bodies, in order for the future Employment of the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon. They can eaſily enough believe, for that the Ap—ſells them out his Balſams, Unguents, and Emplaſters, he muſt certainly be acquainted with their true and proper Uſes; and therefore, if he take upon him the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, they ſcruple not his Fidelity, his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor his Honeſty. But, above all, they ſeem the moſt willing to be impos'd on by the Pretence of a Sea Profeſſor: if he be not altogether ſo arrogant as to take upon him the Title of the King's Surgeon in general, yet his large Experience on the Seas, his having been preſent in ſo many hundred Engagements, where he hath taken off mens Limbs by the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:35377:63"/> dozen, ſeldom eating a morſel till he hath whipp'd off a ſcore Members; where the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets were wont to rattle like Hail about his Ears, ſome taking off his Wig, ſome piercing his Hat, and others (if you'll believe him) have almoſt touched his Heart, yet ſtill, by his unbounded Knowledge in the Art of Healing, he remains alive: he hath ſailed ſo many times into <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſo many to <hi>Arabia,</hi> and as many to the fartheſt parts of <hi>America;</hi> or, if he pleaſe, to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Borders of the Earth; has gone through ſo many ſeveral Hardſhips, and met with ſuch miraculous Deliverances, as would make you ſhake and tremble at the recital: 'Tis this, I ſay, that renders him a man of great repute, and you muſt certainly admire to hear him tell what he underwent to purchaſe Experience in the Medicinal Art, or to render himſelf the more compleatly qualified for the Chyrurgick Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:35377:64"/>
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>AFTER all, as if this ſo worthy Profeſſion had not ſuffer'd by theſe means a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient diminution in its Repute, or its honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Profeſſors had not been hereby enough de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded, we are not wanting of the utmoſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of a <hi>Petticoat Pretender,</hi> to farther our preſent Ignominy and Contempt.</p>
               <p>Were I ſpeaking to any one of a diſcerning Judgment, I would argue nothing more againſt the Sufferance of a practiſing old Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, than the ſingle conſideration of the divine Myſtery of Healing, in the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or theorical part thereof, together with the great and intricate difficulty of its <hi>Practice,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholly above the comprehenſion of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans <hi>Genius,</hi> and vaſtly diſtant from the reach of a Feminine Capacity.</p>
               <p>But ſince I expect to meet with oppoſition from ſome conceited puſilanimous Spirits, I ſhall, for a more general ſatisfaction, take the ſame courſe I have in the preceding Sections, and lay their too common Abuſes open to the naked Eye, that ſo all may ſee (unleſs here and there one will remain blind, and think it a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:35377:64"/> piece of Modeſty to bluſh at the reproach of their Grandams Skill in Surgery) with how great and ſcandalous Reflection on good Litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I had almoſt ſaid, on the Sence and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of all Engliſhmen, the Magiſtracy ſuffer ſuch continual Deluſions, practis'd by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Women, in the Heart of their <hi>Metropolis,</hi> the City of <hi>London,</hi> where there are ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious numbers, who take upon them to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe both in Phyſick and Chyrurgery, that ſcarce a Street, Lane, Court, Alley, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Building therein, which remains unfur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd.</p>
               <p>If you get a Fall, you are no ſooner up again, but advis'd to ſend for the <hi>Cerecloth</hi> of ſome infallible old Wife. If by accident you are wounded, and cannot manage it your ſelf, you are preſently recommended to a skilful Gentlewoman. Nay, if by ill Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany you are drawn aſide, and by an infected <hi>Curteſan</hi> happen to be clapp'd, you ſhall not walk far before you meet with ſome bawdy Doctreſs ready to entertain you, and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to your Infirmities, be they never ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcene. Laſtly, let your Buſineſs be as it will, unleſs very ghaſtly or ill-favour'd to look on, you need not queſtion the Confidence of ſome Female Enterpriſer thereof. So that it is very rare if a Chyrurgeon be now-adays conſulted upon any buſineſs which comes not to him out of the wearied or tired hands, or which hath
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:35377:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> not been nearly ſpoyl'd by the workmanſhip of a Woman.</p>
               <p>If you are minded to take a view of her Cloſet or Surgery, you may find the ſame ſet off with a multitude of conſus'd Preparations, with as many Glaſſes, Gallypots, Boxes, and Plaſters: in the former ſhe keeps <hi>Blackcherry, Bawm, Carduus, Mint,</hi> and other Waters of her own diſtilling, which when mix'd up with a little Syrup of <hi>Gilliflowers,</hi> makes a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial to anſwer all Intentions. In her Gallypots ſhe keeps her Oyntments and Balſams, the chief of which is that of <hi>Lucatellus,</hi> and her Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Marſhmallows.</hi> In her Boxes are Pills, and Spaniſh Flyes to draw Bliſters, and by the help of a Pepper-corn, to make an Iſſue alſo. Her Plaſters in common uſe are <hi>Diachylon,</hi> and <hi>Melilot,</hi> and upon extraordinary occaſions <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelſus</hi> and <hi>Oxycroceum,</hi> for thoſe that will go to the price.</p>
               <p>From the Furniture of her Cloſet we will conduct you to her Library, or the Fountain of her Knowledge; and firſt of all, (as deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the chiefeſt place) we muſt not forget to mention <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as well his <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifry</hi> as his <hi>Engliſh Phyſician,</hi> which Book alone is the chief part of her Treaſury; the reſt, ſuch as the <hi>Good Wife made Doctreſs,</hi> the <hi>Woman's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor,</hi> and the <hi>Plain Rules for Health,</hi> with ſome other Receipt books, being more for the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her Study than for real uſe. I had
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:35377:65"/> almoſt forgot to tell you of thoſe famous <hi>Baths</hi> and <hi>Pultiſſes</hi> (for you muſt conceive ſhe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther approves of <hi>Cataplaſms</hi> nor <hi>Fomentations)</hi> ſhe is likewiſe Miſtriſs of upon occaſion.</p>
               <p>Being thus accompliſh'd, like an honeſt, grave, and diſcreet Matron, ſhe ſets about her Work, which is, firſt of all, if ſhe meets with a green Wound, let it be where or in what part it will, to ſtrow in her <hi>Bole Armeny,</hi> that the <hi>Haemorrbage</hi> (if there be any) may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd. Now, if the 'foreſaid flux proceed from ſome divided Capillary, it may chance to take effect, if not, the Patient muſt ſeek out for other help. Her next or ſecond Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, to cram the Wound full of <hi>Lucatellus Balſam,</hi> and to apply a Cloth with ſome of the ſame daubed over it, and cover'd with a Woollen Clout, for you know it muſt be kept warm: and to talk to her of <hi>Doſſils, Pledgits, Compreſs,</hi> and <hi>Bandage,</hi> you are told, they are the cramp words of <hi>Conjurers</hi> and <hi>Chyrurgeons,</hi> wherewith they amuſe the People, intending to make a Cure of every Trifle, whilſt ſhe, good Woman, (meaning honeſtly) can do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
               <p>This is the exact method of her Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings hitherto, being confirm'd to me by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (I may ſay) hundred Obſervations, where the Event hath been frequently the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> the employing a Chyrurgeon to rectifie the miſtake, and finiſh after a different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:35377:66"/> the deſir'd Cure. What other indeed can be expected from ſuch a treatment, where a Wound hath been plaiſter'd up with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper application of <hi>Lucatellus</hi>'s fam'd <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam,</hi> ſo mightily cry'd up by the People, for the principal Salve neceſſary in a Woman's <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatory?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will by the way take the liberty to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you, that I ſee very little reaſon to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the vulgar Uſe of this Compoſition; neither did I ever find any other effect from its external application, than a <hi>Slough</hi> indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, which covers the bottom as well as lips of the Wound, whereby Digeſtion is retarded, and by conſequence a fluxion of Humour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, begetting Pain, Tumor and Inflammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the Parts about. How then is it likely that Unition in a recent Wound by Conglu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tination, otherwiſe term'd the <hi>firſt Intention,</hi> ſhould ever be procur'd, where the ſides of the Solution are kept diſtended by this clogging Medicament; and there muſt at length be a neceſſity (protracting time) to heal it, as a Wound or Ulcer with loſs of Subſtance, when by Sutures and Bandage, to retain them cloſe, the ſame might have been attain'd in a third part of the time, with far leſs trouble and much more content to the Female Patient, by avoiding of a Scarr, which upon the Neck, Face, Breaſts, or Arms of the fair Sex looks very unſeemly.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:35377:66"/>
               <p> It may here be query'd by ſome, how it ſhould come to paſs, that ſo many and (in their weak Opinion) ſuch conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Wounds, are often Cured by the alone application of this Wonderful Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam.</p>
               <p>I reply hereto, That were it convenient my ſingle Judgment ſhould take place, ſuch an Effect is not ſo much to be imputed to a Vertue latent in the ſaid Medicine, as to the <hi>homogenious</hi> or true and genuine <hi>Craſis</hi> of the Blood, by whoſe Balſamick quality I have heard of many large and ſeemingly dangerous Wounds (where no part of exquiſite Sence hath been divided) which have been heal'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any topick or outward adminiſtration, more than a ſlight covering bound about, to defend them from the Particles of the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambient Air. And of this nature (unleſs I miſtake) are many of thoſe which by ſome fanciful men are ſuppos'd to be wrought by <hi>Sympathy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall be wholly ſilent as to the good or bad effects of this Balſam, when exhibited inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, ſince by ſpeaking thereto I might ſeem to impoſe on the Duty of a Phyſician; but I am well ſatisfied, that ſhould we go about to debar our Female Practiſer of this her moſt admirable Salve, ſhe muſt wholly deſiſt from farther intermeddling in Chyrurgick Practice, there being a great number of them who have
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:35377:67"/> nothing more to ſupport their ridiculous Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences than a Gallypot or Box of <hi>Lucatellus</hi>'s <hi>Balſam,</hi> and a Roll or two of <hi>Paracelſus Plaiſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſhould ſeem reaſonable that I beg excuſe, if in the preſent Section I lay too great an impoſition on the Patience of any judicious Perſon, more particularly on that of my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Chyrurgick Reader. Although it be altogether unlikely to advantage him, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready knows the truth of what I ſhall deliver, yet it ſeem'd highly convenient for the benefit of many in this incredulous Age we live, for illuminating their Underſtandings, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of that Veil of Ignorance which hath beguil'd them, with a falſe proſpect of our juſt and honeſt Intentions.</p>
               <p>I ſhould have had the leſs concern upon me, had I perceiv'd their Frauds to have taken place, and paſs'd undiſcover'd by no other than the inferiour Rabble-Proſelites like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but when I found that the Minds of a more underſtanding People, ſuch of far greater Worth, Reputation, Credit, and ſometimes Quality, were not exempt or freed from the ſame Miſt of Ignorance, this Conſideration gave me Grounds for the moſt profound amazement, as well as pity, and was indeed a great incitement to induce me to lay this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction (not yet, that I know of, ſo fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by others) upon my ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:35377:67"/>
               <p> I ſhall not trouble the Reader with a rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of many particulars; nor do I ſee occaſion, where the general Rule of Practice is altogether prepoſterous.</p>
               <p>Thus, againſt that Maxim of <hi>Contraria con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariis,</hi> in a recent Contuſion, where a repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Topick (as a Defenſative) ſhould take place, we find her tampering with hot Cerecloths or Pultiſſes, whereby a ready way is made for the Influx, and when the Tumor happens to be conſiderable, or the Extravaſation large, there often ſucceeds an incommodious Suppuration or Inflammation, at beſt, a vexatious itching (the old Gentlewoman's ſign of healing) heat and excoriation, accompanied with a very trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſence on the part ſo grieved.</p>
               <p>It is not without cauſe that I am ready to think this to be a great occaſion of our meeting with ſo many obſtinate and perverſe Humours attending an inconſiderable Wound, Ulcer, or Contuſion, whoſe Deſcent hath been firſt invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the improper application of hot Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſes, Unguents, or Emplaſters; ſo that we find that (which if then rationaly treated) would have been little troubleſome, now impoſſible to admit of healing, till the intemperies brought upon the part be carefully removed.</p>
               <p>You will ſcarcely believe that a ſimple Herpes, exaſperated by a Woman's improper appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſhould make ſuch an inveterate im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement in its eroſion, as not to admit a
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:35377:68"/> check under a fortnight's time: and it may ſeem as ſtrange to you, that a bare ſolution of continuity on the ſuperficial parts of the Body, where, 'tis probable, there hath been nothing more than the <hi>Cuticle</hi> and <hi>Cutis</hi> divided by the efficient cauſe, or that a meer Excoriation by the ſcratch of a Pin or Nail, ſhould by impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Medicines (eſpecially where there is a ſalino-ſulphureous Dyſcraſy of the Blood predominant) occaſion three or four months trouble to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</p>
               <p>I was ſome years ſince deſir'd to look upon a Woman, who from a trivial Accident ſuffer'd at that time under the formidable Symptoms of a putrid phagedenick Ulcer upon her Leg, ſo extreamly corroſive, that in a little time it had ſpread it ſelf to the compaſs of a hands breadth, and when the Sordes or Slough was thrown off, it expos'd the fore part of the <hi>Tibia</hi> denudated and carious.</p>
               <p>I will not affirm, this arriv'd at firſt from a famous Doctreſs, her dreſſing the ſaid Leg with an Ointment of Tobacco and Marſhmallows, enwrapping the ſame about with a ſtiptick Plaiſter of <hi>Paracelſus;</hi> but I dare appeal to any diſcriminating Artiſt, whether any thing much better could be expected from ſuch a treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>As I ſhall by no means ſeek to ingratiate my ſelf into the favour of any anti prejudic'd Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or ſuch an one as may unreaſonably bear
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:35377:68"/> an averſion to the honourable Profeſſors of our Art: ſo neither ſhall I require the admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Faith to any thing I have ſaid, far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the prevalency of right Reaſon will conſtrain, or beyond a confirmation of the Truth he may receive from thoſe remarkable Inſtances which continually emerge.</p>
               <p>Let him take but a ſerious view of the weekly Preſentations made to thoſe two ſacred Sanctuaries for the Sick, I mean the Hoſpitals of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> and St. <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> or ſuperviſe thoſe great numbers which are daily offer'd to the Undertakings of the more private Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners in our Art; and after a free enquiry into their Diſtempers, with the former ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement thereof, he will, I doubt not, receive information, that the greater number of their Maladies (ſome of them by delay now grown incurable) had their foundation laid in, or took their original from the hands of ſome confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently-pretending Baggage, or other fair pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing Female Undertaker.</p>
               <p>Is it not a very uſual thing for People to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult us about any troubleſome Accident, being diſſatisfied in their Doctreſs; and we often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times find, where they have been deluded un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of a Sprain, that their Limbs have been obſcurely broken, and a <hi>Callus</hi> (although deform'd for want of Art,) thruſt forth, attended with the diſadvantage of an ill-ſhap'd, crooked, and ſometimes almoſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:35377:69"/> Member. The like may be ſaid of Diſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, which are by baſe unlearned Women treated for no other than ſimple Contuſions, and ſo long neglected, that there is no hope of Remedy; which might at firſt, with as much facility as ſucceſs, have been adminiſtred.</p>
               <p>Indeed, it is much the ſame comparatively in all other caſes where there has been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a Feminine Chyrurgick Operator, who if one undertaking ſucceed, although a ſcore miſcarry, that one proves a ſufficient Baſis for the light Fabrick of her Reputation. Nay, ſhe being moſt commonly the proclaimer of her own Fame, you ſhall not want to hear the flying Stories of her Fortunes, whilſt thoſe of her unbounded Ignorance are buried in as deep a ſilence, and revive not otherwiſe than through the Courteſie of ſome ſorrowful Mother, who is beholden to this famous Doctreſs for making of her Child a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</p>
               <p>She is one, who if ſhe finds you wavering in your Opinion of her Skill, or diſſatisfied at her Proceedings, knows how to terrifie you from falling into the Chyrurgeon's hands, where you are to expect nothing leſs than the unſpeakable Tyranny of <hi>Probation, Inciſion,</hi> and <hi>Scarrification;</hi> whereas ſhe, like a tender-hearted Woman, makes uſe of no ſuch Cruelty; ſhe has none of thoſe frightful Inſtruments to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex and diſquiet you, but is willing to cure
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:35377:69"/> you with her ſoveraign Balſam or Plaiſter, which ſhe will admit you to take off and put on your ſelf.</p>
               <p>This is the pleaſing Subterfuge of Ignorance, and a Bait very eaſily ſwallow'd down by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate People, not ſeldom to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. 'Tis truly the main Objection, why many Perſons are ſo fearful of the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgick Artiſt, <hi>viz.</hi> his ſevere and cruel uſage to his Patients. Now therefore, that I may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riddle this great Myſtery, and expoſe the whole Truth without reſerve, thereby to ſee if the matter in debate be ſuch as repreſented, we will thus argue: If thou ſhouldſt at any time labour of an Infirmity, either Tumor, Wound, Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whether may it be thought more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to confide in him who is throughly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienc'd in the progreſs and event of each Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, which thy ſelf and fellow-Creatures are all prone to, has had his abundant Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge therein confirm'd to him by his Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under ſome learned and ingenious Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner, and is himſelf continually converſant in ſuch-like practical Obſervations? Hadſt thou rather truſt thy ſelf in the hands of ſuch, or in thoſe of ſome ſenceleſs <hi>Petticoat Pretender,</hi> who hath no more Judgment in thy Diſtemper than thy ſelf, neither more Authority to take upon her the Profeſſion, than what ſhe baſely and moſt unjuſtly aſſumes? I can eaſily enough foreſee what may be anſwer'd hereto, that you
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:35377:70"/> the rather prefer a Woman, becauſe ſhe will not cut or make Inciſions upon your Fleſh; ſhe hates thoſe inhumane Cauteries or Searing Irons wherewith Chyrurgeons (who are ſworn to make a Cure) perplex and diſturb you, but will carefully endeavour, by her Ointments and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Salves, without any Severity, to remove your Diſorders.</p>
               <p>To this I could reply, if there were occaſion, that of the Poet,
<q>
                     <l>—immedicabile vulnus,</l>
                     <l>Enſe recidendum—</l>
                  </q> or, That a deſperate Caſe requires as ſevere a Remedy: And whether or no the Diſeaſe be arriv'd at ſuch a ſtate, I think the able and knowing Artiſt the more competent Judge: ſo that it is not to be diſputed, but where neceſſity calls for it, ſo rough and rigorous an admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration is undeniably to be juſtified.</p>
               <p>I do not go about to perſwade, that this muſt be the reſult of every one's particular condition, ſince I would have all to underſtand that it is much beneath the Principle of any Chriſtian Profeſſor of our Art to exerciſe ſuch ſeeming Cruelties upon his Patient, if he could other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways diſcharge the Duty of his Calling, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form what is requir'd of him.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:35377:70"/>
               <p> It ſeems moſt ſtrange to me, and I think this may ſupply the place of a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Argument, that an ignorant unlearned Woman's Judgment ſhould ſurpaſs that of the moſt eminent Artiſt, or that ſhe ſhould in any probability be capable to relieve us, without ſuch handling as we are frighted with, whilſt he whoſe proper buſineſs it is, knows not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the ſame.</p>
               <p>What an extream Folly carries ſome People into a reſolute Belief (which they will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter till they have render'd themſelves Sufferers) that ſuch an one as is unknowing in the cauſe of a Diſtemper, or what the ſame Diſtemper truly is, can make neither <hi>Prognoſtick</hi> nor <hi>Diag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtick</hi> thereof, neither can tell by what appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate Remedies the ſame Diſtemper ſhould be profligated, but hazardouſly preſcribes her fortuitous Medicines, which for all her knowledge, may do more injury than good. That ſhe (I ſay) ſhould notwithſtanding have found out a more eaſie and ſalubrious <hi>Methodus Medendi,</hi> than the more judicious and skilful Practitioner in the ſaid Art.</p>
               <p>I would ſincerely adviſe thoſe who are ſo wonderfully afraid of having their Fleſh cut, (as the only Preſervative therefrom) that they ſhun a pretending Doctreſs, one, who by her Ignorance gives too commonly the firſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſuch unavoidable proceedings, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed many times for that which is of higher
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:35377:71"/> conſequence than a ſmall Inciſion <hi>(viz.) Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,</hi> or (to ſave their Lives) diſmembering of a Limb.</p>
               <p>If they would repair in time to the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of true Knowledge and Underſtanding, they might find from their own experience, there would be no reaſon to apprehend ſuch danger, or thus diſmally to affright themſelves, being ſecure under the induſtrious care of a tender and compaſſionate Artiſt: Or let the caſe be what it will, when you have been miſguided and ſo long neglected your ſelf, and at length repair to him, you may aſſure your ſelf you will find no Surgeon ſo indiſcreet as to undertake (without your free conſent) any thing of a dubious conſideration or event; if he finds your condition perilous, or full of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he propoſeth the method he intends to proceed by, and which is abſolutely neceſſary he ſhould obſerve, if to your full ſatisfaction he diſcharge the Duty incumbent on him. If you diſlike ſuch his Propoſal, you can but reflect upon his Caution, and blame your ſelf for an unwillingneſs to ſubmit thereto. Farther, if you cannot comply with ſuch his intended courſe, yet will ſtill put your ſelf under his care, I am certain you will not find wanting (when he has forewarn'd you of the danger) the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his Endeavours (which ſhould, as I conceive, be much more prevalent than a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's)
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:35377:71"/> to reſtore and cure you without this painful and ſevere uſage.</p>
               <p>I could wiſh that every Patient would make choice of ſuch an honeſt and able Profeſſor of this Art as they might reaſonably confide in, and then wholly, under the Supreme Power, to ſubmit themſelves (without dictating their own erroneous Sentiments) to his management, I would have them baniſh all thoſe childiſh and fearful Apprehenſions of his ſuppoſed Cruelty, and remain ſtedfaſt, in a firm belief, that he will act no otherwiſe by them than himſelf, if under ſuch-like circumſtances; or, that what he does is purely deſign'd for their recovery and well being.</p>
               <p>It is but little ſhort of a Miracle to me, that any one ſhould imagine we can be ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in (what they call) the perſecution of our Neighbours, when we take upon us thoſe troubleſome operations of Inciſing, Cauteriſing, Amputating, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as to account the ſame for Pleaſure or Diverſion, which is no more than what we are prompted to from the urgent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of ſuch miſerable States and Accidents as require ſuch performance.</p>
               <p>Can they think, I wonder, that the clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Shrieks and Outcries of poor ſuffering Creatures are ſuch grateful Concord or harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Melody, to make us fond thereof, if we knew to avoid it? Rather let me inform ſuch who have been too ſubject to cenſure us in this
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:35377:72"/> manner, that every faithful Practitioner is at theſe times of diſtreſs an almoſt equal Sufferer with his Patient, as well by a deep concern for his Affliction, as on the account of that burthenſome Care which then lies upon him, ariſing through the diſturb'd Thoughts and Fears of a Miſcarriage under his hands: Which are, I think, ſufficient grounds for our Belief, that no man in his Senſes would take upon him ſome very troubleſome Operations in our Art, did not an indiſpenſible neceſſity, with the conſcientious diſcharge of his Duty, compel him to the ſame.</p>
               <p>I doubt not in the leaſt but many have ſuffer'd, and that in an extraordinary mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, through the Ignorance of ſome unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable Practitioners in our Art, but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think that any one, unleſs ſome ſtupid Atheiſt, who believes neither the Divine <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience</hi> nor <hi>Omnipreſence,</hi> would dare the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Vengeance, by trying Concluſions and Experiments upon his fellow-Creature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he might be endanger'd of either Limb or Life, or after any other manner witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly torment his diſtreſſed Patient, farther than the urgency of his Caſe commands: and he who hath thus far follow'd the Rules of Art with a good and juſt intent, is undoubtedly to be juſtified, his Actions alſo to be accounted war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable before GOD and Man.</p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:35377:72"/>
               <p> I muſt needs ſay I have ſo high an opinion of all that are known to my ſelf, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them in no wiſe guilty of ſuch impiouſly degenerate and ſordid Practice; and I am ſo far from cenſuring all others of this faculty, that I as little queſtion but that every of them who are legally qualified for the Practice would ſcorn to act the ſame. Let me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore adviſe all malevolent, mean-ſpirited, and ill-principled Perſons, who have unreaſonably contributed to the diſheartening and diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their Friends from being concern'd with the Chyrurgick Artiſt, (in his room pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring an Old Woman) that they deſiſt from ſuch their dangerous Perſwaſions, till they can bring a juſtifiable Accuſation, to countenance what they endeavour to inſinuate againſt us.</p>
               <p>I might here, according to a more orderly proceeding, lay before you a <hi>Scheme</hi> of every individual Woman's Ignorance, and recite to you their Names and Places of reſidence, but truly conſidering the preſent ſtate of affairs, where a feminine preheminence in Chyrurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is made a kind of Diſputation, and that the whole Nation ſounds of their wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Atchievements; the former would be as troubleſome as the latter without number. Since then it were no News to tell you of an Old Wife's Failings in her Pretences to the Practice, and as little ſtrange to be inform'd
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:35377:73"/> where there lives ſuch a famous Gentlewoman, who is turned <hi>Doctreſs,</hi> or other <hi>Petticoat Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaker.</hi> Waving (I ſay) a rehearſal of ſuch-like Fooleries, I ſhall come towards a concluſion of this my laſt Section, not forgetting firſt to acquaint you with the Tranſactions of a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful She Profeſſor beyond <hi>L—B—</hi>who ſeldom intermeddles in any thing ſhort of ſuch difficult buſineſs, as hath been declar'd incurable by the moſt eminent of our City-Chyrurgeons, <hi>viz. Cancers</hi> and <hi>Scrophulous Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors,</hi> which ſhe ſeldom keeps under hand by any long delay, but for the moſt part makes a quick (though painful) diſpatch, giving them a ſpeedy deliverance out of all their Afflictions. 'Tis not the expiation of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Whipping, or any thing leſs than a capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Puniſhment, that can ſo far ſatisfie as to make compleat atonement, or reſtitution to the hands of Juſtice, for this bold Pretender's multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd Offences.</p>
               <p>You will ſcarce believe thoſe unheard of Rarities, found out by the Induſtry of this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſuch as the cure of a confirm'd Cancer upon the Tongue, by a Plaiſter of Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worms, whereby the Patient (though before ſick and weak) was with a little of her help enabled to take a Journey into the other World. Nor is it likely that you have heard who it was that the deceaſed Mr. <hi>W—.</hi> courted as an <hi>Aſſiſtant,</hi> let me tell you then
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:35377:73"/> (as it came from her) 'twas the lately mention'd Gentlewoman who blaz'd it abroad for the encreaſe of her Fame, That this ingenious Artiſt proffer'd her One Hundred Pounds to take the Charge of his moſt difficult Practice. A very likely matter! that ſuch a perſon as a <hi>Serjeant-Surgeon,</hi> who had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulated the greateſt Honours of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, ſhould at length make ſuit to a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly-intruding Goſſip, and proffer her a Stipend to be his <hi>Coadjutrix.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What will not Impudence leave unattem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted, to purchaſe the empty Nothing of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Applauſe?</p>
               <p>It was by ſuch-like Inſinuations that the 'foreſaid Perſon wheedl'd her ſelf into the good Opinion of a Gentleman who had been for ſome time afflicted with an Ulcerated Cancer, ſpreading it ſelf from the <hi>Coronal Suture</hi> on one ſide, reaching over that part of the <hi>Bregma</hi> and <hi>Os Temporis</hi> to the <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible.</hi> The Patient, not content with a pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation of this raging Malady, was induced (by a confident promiſe of Cure) to ſubmit himſelf to her management, under whoſe hands he languiſh'd for ſome time, till he died a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Object, to forewarn the Unwary how they embrace the Poyſon of a Woman's Speech, whilſt they neglect and contemn the Counſel of the Legal Artiſt.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:35377:74"/>
               <p> It would be too burthenſome a Task to give a ſuccinct or compleat Narrative of thoſe groſs Cheats and Abuſes offer'd to the Inhabitants of the City of <hi>London,</hi> by Women pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Art of Surgery. The one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth the Cure of ſore apoſtemated Breaſts, another for ſore Eyes, a third for the <hi>King's Evil,</hi> a fourth for ſore Legs, a fifth for Scald Heads, a ſixth for Cancers, and ſo of the reſt; when at the ſame time making no manner of diſtinction in the Temperaments or Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of Humane Bodies, but having pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd one particular Medicine, as a <hi>Mercurial</hi> or <hi>Vitriolick Water,</hi> a famous Oyntment, Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam, or Plaiſter; and either of theſe having caſually prov'd ſucceſsful, they confuſedly ever after uſe the ſame upon all occaſions, extolling them as the moſt ſoveraign Remedies yet known.</p>
               <p>It is not long ſince I was diſcharg'd by a Gentlewoman, in order for the entertainment of a Woman, who undertook to cure the moſt inveterate <hi>Abſceſs,</hi> with no other application than a Cloth ſpread with equal parts of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilicon,</hi> and an Oyntment of Marſhmallows; But what was the conſequence? When the Tumor ſuppurated, the diſcharge was left to Nature (for, you muſt know, it would have been a piece of Cruelty to have open'd it
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:35377:74"/> either by Cauſtick or Inciſion;) and the more fluid part of the Matter vented it ſelf at a ſmall Orifice, whence the reſidue ſubſiding, her Pain afreſh encreas'd, and I was at length admitted to open it in the more depending part, by which means the ſame in a ſhort time was perfectly healed.</p>
               <p>'Tis moſt certain, where the <hi>Pus</hi> or <hi>Quitture</hi> has no commodious vent, it frequently falls down lower, and begets <hi>Sinus's</hi> or Caverns, which, for want of timely opening, eſpecially where the Humour is corroſive, and the Bone near the ſame becomes carious, the hollowneſs in time growing Callous. And truly, for the moſt part, ſuch kind of Work as this gives us the opportunity of meeting with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny incurable <hi>Fiſtula's,</hi> which oftentimes take their riſe from an inconſiderable <hi>Abſceſs,</hi> whoſe Cavity was never open'd, or otherwiſe deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, than by that baſe pernicious Practice of Injections.</p>
               <p>I ſhall divert you (before I ſumm up all) with an account of ſomewhat of the like tendency with the laſt recited Caſe, out of Mr. <hi>W—</hi>'s Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:35377:75"/>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Whilſt I was dreſſing a Patient</hi> (ſaith the ſaid Author) <hi>in a Citizen's Houſe, I was deſir'd to look upon the Breaſt of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman of the Houſe: She had lately lain in, and from abundance of Milk and ill handling, her right Breaſt had been Apoſte-mated, and broken out in many holes. A Woman famous in the City for dreſſing fore Breaſts was her Chyrurgeon. I had obſerv'd, that the Breaſt had at firſt broke in the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per part, in a ſmall Pin-hole, and the Matter not having had ſufficient diſcharge, had ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſo made the other Openings, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards paſſed an inch lower than any of the Openings, and could not be diſcharg'd other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than as it filled up the</hi> Sinus, <hi>and ran over, or was preſs'd from below upwards with her Hand: By this means the Breaſt continued inflam'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and apoſtemated, inſomuch that it was impoſſible to cure it by that method, till it had apoſtemated the whole Breaſt.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>I pitied the Patient, and wonder'd that a Woman (ſo fam'd for ſuch Cures) could be ſo ignorant, and yet preſerve her Credit with that Sex. I ſhew'd the Patient the Cauſe of her Pain, and the unlikelihood to be ſuddenly cured by ſuch a Chyrurgeon, and prevailed with her to permit me to lay a</hi>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:35377:75"/> 
                  <hi>Cauſtick on the Depending Part; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made an Eſchar the compaſs of a Threepence, open'd it, and gave vent to the Matter, and left her a little</hi> Unguentum Baſilicon, <hi>by which ſhe was Cured in few Days.</hi>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>THE CONCLUSION.</head>
            <p>I Have now diſcharg'd my ſelf of what I thought an Obligation, by endeavouring to evidence the notorious Abuſes ariſing from a ſufferance of unallowable Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners in the Chyrurgick Art, which is ſo dark and obſcure, ſo unintelligible in the Practick as well as Theorical part thereof, to the Judgment of every one, unleſs that of its Profeſſors, that he who is minded to act a diſhoneſt part, or play the Knave therein, ſhall carry on the moſt fraudulent Deſigns imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptibly to the People, and ſo far, it's poſſible, from meeting with interruption, that it is no wonder if he be nobly rewarded, very honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accounted, and as charitably thought of for ſo doing. Indeed, whilſt this liberty is granted to every impertinent Intruder, who hath Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:35377:76"/> enough to carry on his Pretenſions; whilſt their frequent Failings are ſo little heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, their male Practice no ways minded, nor themſelves in the leaſt queſtion'd, how qualified for the ſame; whilſt theſe, I ſay, are buried in ſilence, we muſt expect no other than a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual decay of Knowledge, a diſcouragement of Learned Men, and (let our Care otherways be never ſo great) muſt be incident to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Calamities, occaſion'd from ſo prejudicial and ſhameful a toleration.</p>
            <p>Were either <hi>Galen</hi> or <hi>Hippocrates</hi> now living, to ſee this ſpurious Iſſue made ſo much of, their Pretences unqueſtion'd, their Abuſes even countenanc'd, and they advanc'd, whilſt their legitimate Offspring are degraded and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteem'd; were they inform'd of this worthy Rabble, who baſely take upon them the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of our Art; or did they know how eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Water-flinging <hi>Piſs-prophet</hi> boaſts himſelf as great a Doctor as the moſt gradually-commenc'd Phyſician; how the moſt contemptible Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks, ſuch as <hi>Tinkers, Coblers, &amp;c.</hi> not only make it a point of Controverſie, but endeavour with all their might to monopolize the Art, and exclude the worthy Artiſt; were theſe Worthy men in a capacity of inſpecting theſe matters, we may ſuppoſe they would not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle wonder at the Age we live in, and grieve to behold our miſerable Neglect, who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the moſt honourable of Arts to be
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:35377:76"/> render'd the moſt deſpicable, that Art which they themſelves were not more painful and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious to new model and compleat, than we are careleſs to ſupport and prevent its final over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</p>
            <p>There is truly at this time ſo little care ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to correct and puniſh the Preſumption of any illiterate Perſon, that if a man have but an Inclination thereto, though the moſt injudicious or unknowing, if he have Wit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to hang out a Bloodporringer, to call him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Barber-Surgeon, to ſet forth a Urinal or Scheme of the Celeſtial Houſes, with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Hieroglyphick</hi> of his Skill, he ſhall paſs in the Crowd for the moſt learned Profeſſor of Phyſick as well as Surgery. What is worſe, let his Ignorance be as manifeſt as the Injuſtice of his Claim, he goes on unmoleſted, without danger of oppoſition.</p>
            <p>I believe there are at this time ſome Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of falſe Practitioners in the City of <hi>London,</hi> beſides thoſe whom we more peculiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entitle <hi>Quacks</hi> and <hi>Mountebanks;</hi> at leaſt ſuch as undertake to bleed, cut Iſſues, ſet broken and disjoynted Members, or to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter Phyſick, and the one half of theſe no other than ignorant and fooliſh Women, whoſe enormous Practice hath been one great cauſe, as well to leſſen the number of its Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, as to bring the moſt ridiculous Contempt and Scandal on the beſt of Arts.</p>
            <pb n="132" facs="tcp:35377:77"/>
            <p> If you take a Proſpect of the outparts of the Town, you would imagine there were a plenary Indulgence granted to all <hi>Empiricks, Quacks, Barbers, Old Women,</hi> and others, whom it ſhall pleaſe to take upon them the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chyrurgery; you will either think this Art the moſt eaſily attainable of all others, ſince a meer Pretence to the ſame will carry a man very far into the good Opinion of the People: or, laſt of all, you will find juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to imagine this (formerly ſublime) Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is now become a kind of Sanctuary or Refuge for decay'd Tradeſmen, who know not to live longer upon their own Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <p>
                  <hi>I remember,</hi> (ſaith an ancient Author) <hi>when I was at the Wars of</hi> Mutterell, <hi>in the time of the moſt famous King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth, there was a great Rabblement, that took upon them the Practice of Chyrurgery, ſuch as</hi> Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Sowgelders, Shoemenders, <hi>and the like; this noble Sect perform'd ſuch wondrous Cures, that they got to themſelves a perpetual Name; in two or three dreſſings they moſt commonly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their Patients, making them whole and ſound for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:35377:77"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>When the Duke of</hi> Norfolk, <hi>who was then General, underſtood how the People dy'd of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable Wounds, he ſent for me, and certain other Chyrurgeons, requiring us to make ſearch how theſe men came by their Death, whether it were by the grievouſneſs of their Wounds, or through want of Knowledge in the Undertakers. According to his Command, we made ſearch throughout the Camp, and found many of theſe Good fellows, who took upon them the Titles of Chyrurgeons; not only ſo, but the Salary alſo: We enquir'd with whom they had been brought up; and they ſhameleſly would anſwer, With ſome Skilful Perſon or other, who was dead ſome time ago. We farther demanded to ſee what Medicines they had to Cure the Wounded; and they would readily ſhew us a Pot or Box which they had in a Budget, wherein was ſuch Trumpery as was only fit to greaſe Horſe-heels withal; others, who were</hi> Coblers <hi>and</hi> Tinkers, <hi>made uſe of</hi> Shoemakers-wax, <hi>and the Ruſt of old Pans, wherewith they compounded a</hi> Noble Salve, <hi>as they term'd it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the end this worthy Rabble were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the</hi> Marſhalſea, <hi>and threatned by his Grace to be hang'd for their Wicked Deeds, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they would declare the Truth, what they were, and of what Occupations: They did finally confeſs as I have declar'd to you before; upon</hi>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:35377:78"/> 
                  <hi>which the Duke gave Commandment, That they ſhould immediately avoid the Camp, upon pain of Death; and if after they appear'd there again, they ſhould be hang'd as Murtherers.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>I could wiſh that the preſent Nobility of our Nation, with others the ſupreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Magiſtrates thereof, would imitate the Example of this eminent perſon, and take care to puniſh all ſuch deceitful perſons, who fall from their proper Employments, and moſt unjuſtly aſſume the Profeſſion of Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery.</p>
            <p>I am ſure, if the publick Intereſt, or the Honour of the ſaid Art were ſought to be advanc'd, ſuch a courſe would be taken, whereby inſolent Pretenders might be ſilenc'd in their attempts, their Abuſes prevented by their condign Puniſhment, and the People ſecur'd from ſuffering through Ignorance, in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of their Diſtempers.</p>
            <p>If we reflect on the Care and Induſtry of every private Tradeſman, who is himſelf a Freeman, to diſcover any Stranger who hath unjuſtly encroach'd upon his Privilege, what a buſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie and ſtir he makes to keep out Foreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, never leaving nor deſiſting till for his own and his Company's good he hath routed and put them down. If (I ſay) we conſider the Care taken about inferiour matters, where the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:35377:78"/> Conteſt is upon a ſmall and frivolous occaſion, what are we in the mean time to be accounted, who negligently diſpenſe with thoſe intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Impoſitions made by Strangers, Ignorants, and all others, upon the Practice of Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery, where the Debate is not upon a meer Livelihood, or the advancement of Trade, but here our Health, Limbs, and Lives are the Price of our Contention, and by permiſſion hereof we are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in danger of being Ruin'd in them all.</p>
            <p>It was the Opinion of a Perſon very emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in our Profeſſion, that no one could be qualified for Practice, <hi>Niſi in eadem edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus, exercitatuſque fuit.</hi> With how great Peril do we then (from his words) confide in theſe preſumptuous Undertakers, who cannot ſubſiſt by the Income of their proper Occupations, and have nothing to ſet them off but their Impudence and a little Book-Knowledge, wherewith they amuſe thoſe who take them to be rightly accompliſh'd Phyſicians and Chyrurgeons. They are ſo far from having been initiated under the Care of any Legal Practitioner, or ſo little exerciſed in the ſaid Art, that their ſhort Conference with ſome Confident Empirick or Quack (having thereby purchas'd one or two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Medicines) is the whole Stock of their
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:35377:79"/> Learning, as well as Grounds for ſuch their pernicious Pretences.</p>
            <p>I will however hope, that from the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Obſervations the People may ſee what intolerable Miſchiefs an unskilful Perſon may perpetrate, when countenanc'd the moſt ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally to practice in this Noble Art; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I doubt not but many others have made the like Reflections upon the erroneous Actions of theſe Men, yet I may think, at leaſt, that this publick manifeſtation of their Ignorance and Deceit, from the important ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency thereto, with the unavoidable neceſſity for the ſame, will the rather excite or ſpur on ſome generous Perſon (whoſe ſtation will admit thereof) to perfect in ſome ſence a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation of theſe Abuſes.</p>
            <p>What indeed can we expect from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of ſuch a Sufferance, but that the Medicinal Profeſſion (formerly held in ſo great repute and admiration) is not only likely to ſtand in competition with the moſt mercenary Employment, but that its genuine Profeſſors, meeting with ſo great diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may in time lay aſide and neglect its farther improvement, to the no ſmall diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all true and methodical Knowledge therein, and to the univerſal detriment thereby accrewing to the whole Nation.</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:35377:79"/>
            <p> If he who hath ſpent the greateſt part of his Life hath been inſtructed by the ableſt Maſter of the ſaid Art, by a long and tedious Service therein, and conſtantly habituated to the ſtudy as well as practiſe thereof, all which he finds little enough to render him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf capacitated. If, after all, ſuch a Perſon as this ſhall be no better accounted than an <hi>Upſtart Empirick,</hi> no farther rely'd on than a <hi>Foreign Quack,</hi> no more confided in than a <hi>Practiſing Barber,</hi> his Skill thought ſcarce equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to a <hi>cheating</hi> or <hi>deluding Boneſetter</hi>'s, and himſelf in all reſpects, for his Art, little more eſteem'd than a <hi>Female Enterprizer.</hi> If <hi>Tinkers, Coblers, Heelmakers,</hi> and <hi>Butchers,</hi> with the reſt of this ſpurious and ſordid Tribe, ſhall be as well rewarded as the moſt judicious and faithful Practitioner, what other Fate to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend can we imagine, unleſs that of the irrepairable Confuſion of this once famous Art?</p>
            <p>How profitably a Regulation of theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders might be undertaken for the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing baſe Pretenders to Chyrurgick Practice, where the Concerns of Life it ſelf are daily hazarded, would, I doubt not, ſoon appear with the Product of theſe great Advantages. Firſt of all, the Unwary would be no longer miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided by the plauſible Stories of the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, nor expos'd to the Miſcarriages they
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:35377:80"/> are now ſubjected to. Furthermore, the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Practitioner would not be moleſted or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peded in his Practice by theſe ſurreptitious <hi>Quackſalvers,</hi> whom we ſhould quickly find diſſolved into their priſtine Employments: There would be no Toleration for any of them to enter themſelves as <hi>Cubbs</hi> in an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital, hereupon to be accounted for rightly-conſtituted Chyrurgeons. No Tradeſman would, with polluted Hands, intermeddle in the Medicinal Art, or any other of them preſume upon this Privilege, if not only the Fear but the Effect of a juſt and reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Proſecution could be of ſufficient force to reduce them into their proper Elements.</p>
            <p>How might we rejoyce to ſee the preſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <hi>Piſs prophet</hi> broke to pieces with his Uri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and the Empirical, with the ſtrouling <hi>Bill-Doctor,</hi> forced to take up ſome other Buſineſs, wherein it may be unlikely they ſhould do that injury to the generality of Mankind?</p>
            <p>Let thoſe few, and ſome of them fatal, Inſtances I have given, caution all Perſons how they confide in the Promiſes of any confident Undertaker: Let their frequent Fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings be no longer wink'd at, but let every one who wiſhes well to the Publick uſe his utmoſt diligence, that theſe Abuſes be as well reform'd as detected. It is not ſo trifling a
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:35377:80"/> Concern as may be ſuppoſed, ſince the Lives of ſo many miſerable Creatures are forfeited by our delay herein. And therefore, as we may read in Ancient Authors, what good and wholſome Laws were made to puniſh all ſuch arrogant Perſons, let us endeavour all we can that the ſame, or the like, may be in force, and put in execution againſt thoſe who by their malevolent and ſlanderous Aſperſions, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their moſt deteſted Practiſes, have procur'd as much Miſchief to the People as Contempt to Surgery, and its honourable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors; the well-wiſhing to whoſe Proſperity will be but little available, till there be an Attempt made for the removal of thoſe grand Impediments of their Luſtre and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown.</p>
            <p>I think I cannot more pertinently finiſh what I have to ſay upon this Subject, than in the Words of one of our own Authors to this purpoſe.</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <hi>As you would that this Noble Art ſhould flouriſh, you muſt not be wanting in your Endeavours to take away the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of its Prejudice and Diſrepute; neither yet to acknowledge your depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon the Supreme Being, who hath</hi>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:35377:81"/> 
               <hi>as well created and appointed the Means thou ſhalt think fit to uſe, as ordained thee to be the Instrument of ſuch his Favour. Furthermore, be thou never wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to petition Heaven for Succeſs upon thy Chyrurgick Enterprizes, whereby the Sick may be advantag'd, and an Eternity of Comfort and Satisfaction procur'd to thy ſelf.</hi>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35377:81"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
